<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Legislation Archives -</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/legislation/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Protecting Hearts and Saving Lives</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 14:20:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/simons-fav-icon1.png</url>
	<title>Legislation Archives -</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Testimony for Maryland Ways &#038; Means</title>
		<link>/blog/testimony-for-maryland-ways-means/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2014 14:50:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Legislation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=5897</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Chairwoman Hixson and Committee Members: Thank you for giving me the privilege to testify in support of HB 427: The Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act. My name is Darren Sudman. I am a co-founder and the Executive Director of Simon&#8217;s Fund. I am also Simon&#8217;s dad. I live outside of Philadelphia now. The last time [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/testimony-for-maryland-ways-means/">Testimony for Maryland Ways &amp; Means</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Chairwoman Hixson and Committee Members:</p>
<p>Thank you for giving me the privilege to testify in support of HB 427: The Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act.</p>
<p>My name is Darren Sudman. I am a co-founder and the Executive Director of Simon&#8217;s Fund. I am also Simon&#8217;s dad. I live outside of Philadelphia now. The last time I was at a formal ceremony in Annapolis, I was being sworn in to the Maryland State Bar. It’s been a while.</p>
<p>Nine years ago, my three-month old son passed away. Initially, we were told that it was SIDS, but SIDS really means, “sorry, we don’t know why your baby died.” The medical community was unaware. We were VERY unaware.</p>
<p>Fortunately, we had a curious pediatrician. She told us to get our hearts checked because “babies don’t just die.” Through this process, my wife, Phyllis, was diagnosed with Long QT Syndrome, an arrhythmia.</p>
<p>We learned from the Mayo Clinic that Long QT is responsible for up to 15% of all SIDS deaths. We learned from the American Academy of Pediatrics that about 2,000 children die every year from sudden cardiac arrest. We read stories in the paper about children like Tekau Rasayon from PG County, Santiago Vesperoni from Montgomery County and Jonathan Nolon from Bowie. Like so many other children, they collapsed and died while doing something they loved – playing sports.</p>
<p>We learned that SCA is the #1 cause of death of student athletes.</p>
<p>You see, like most of the residents in Maryland, and every other state in this country, we thought that sudden cardiac arrest was just an adult thing. Unfortunately, we had to pay the highest price to pique our curiosity. We were slowly becoming aware.</p>
<p>Do we really want other families to take the same road to enlightenment, or is there a more effective and humane way to share what we’ve learned.</p>
<p>There are a few ways that we can prevent sudden cardiac arrest from taking the lives of our children.</p>
<p>We can try to detect the conditions before they strike by providing heart screenings. That’s what Simon’s Fund does. We’ve screened over 8,000 students; helping 60 plus discover heart conditions.</p>
<p>Or, we can be prepared when it does by knowing CPR and having AED devices available.</p>
<p>Hopefully, one day, we’ll do all of these things, but the reality is that few people will avail themselves of the screenings, and not many people will reach for the AED device, until they know that SCA is a threat to their child.</p>
<p>On May 28, 2012, very few parents, coaches and players in PA knew about this threat. However, the following day, after the passage of Act 59, sudden cardiac arrest became a household term. Every parent and coach of a student knew that SCA wasn’t just an adult thing. They learned that Gatorade may not be the remedy when a player passes out. They learned that a racing heart isn’t necessarily caused by drinking too much soda.</p>
<p>Pennsylvania didn’t have to spend any money to provide this information, and the parents and coaches didn’t have to lose a child or student to learn this lesson.</p>
<p>Last year, the Journal of the American Board of Family Medicine released a study that found that 72% of all students that experienced sudden cardiac arrest exhibited symptoms.</p>
<p>Don’t we want to share this information with parents and coaches in Maryland? If the answer is yes, then HB 427 is a great vehicle.</p>
<p>Thanks for your time.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/testimony-for-maryland-ways-means/">Testimony for Maryland Ways &amp; Means</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>One Year Later &#8211; The Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act</title>
		<link>/blog/one-year-later-the-sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2013 14:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Legislation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=4705</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Today marks the one year anniversary of the signing of the Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act (Act 59). This is the only law in the country that protects student athletes from sudden cardiac arrest. It&#8217;s really cool to get a law passed, and even cooler to speak at the bill signing, but what kind of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/one-year-later-the-sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/">One Year Later &#8211; The Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div>Today marks the one year anniversary of the signing of the <a href="/protect-this-heart/sudden-cardiac-arrest/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" shape="rect">Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act (Act 59)</a>. This is the only law in the country that protects student athletes from sudden cardiac arrest. It&#8217;s really cool to get a law passed, and even cooler to speak at the bill signing, but what kind of impact has this law had on student athletes? How much safer are student athletes today?</div>
<div>&nbsp;</div>
<div><a href="http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/DSC_26471.jpg"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" class="aligncenter  wp-image-4204" src="https://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2012/11/DSC_26471.jpg" alt="DSC_2647" width="319" height="211"></a></div>
<div>&nbsp;</div>
<div>The&nbsp;<a href="http://www.nfhs.org/content.aspx?id=3282" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" shape="rect">National Federation of State High School Associations</a>&nbsp;conducts an annual participation survey. During the 2011- 12 school year, 7.7 million students participated in high school sports. Pennsylvania ranked 6th with 318,000 high school students participating.</div>
<div>&nbsp;</div>
<div><strong>IMPACT #1</strong>: Over 300,000 student athletes and their parents now know that sudden cardiac arrest is the #1 cause of death of student athletes.</div>
<div>&nbsp;</div>
<div><strong>IMPACT #2</strong>: Tens of thousands of coaches were trained on the warning signs of sudden cardiac arrest. and were required to remove players that exhibited these warning signs.</div>
<div>&nbsp;</div>
<div><strong>IMPACT #3</strong>: These videos, created by the&nbsp;<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WU8F5j-22wE&list=PLJp1XkcEsYNf5UB0zj__ZTOp9hpMSVbBw&index=5" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" shape="rect">Philadelphia Six</a>&nbsp;(NCAA Hoops coaches), Olympic Gold Medalist&nbsp;<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0QuY5kA-bYs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" shape="rect">Dana Vollmer</a>, and NBA Champion&nbsp;<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RA9x1Lv8ZbI" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" shape="rect">Ronny Turiaf</a>, have been seen by thousands of coaches and players.</div>
<div>&nbsp;</div>
<div><strong>IMPACT #4</strong>:&nbsp;<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F8VM5VGUWy8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" shape="rect">Sanjay Gupta</a>&nbsp;introduced millions of people across the country to this law and the risks of sudden cardiac arrest for student athletes.</div>
<div>&nbsp;</div>
<div><strong>IMPACT #5</strong>: Six other states have introduced this law: Illinois, Indiana, Massachusetts, Michigan, New Jersey and Oklahoma.</div>
<div>&nbsp;</div>
<div>Our goal is for a majority of states to pass a version of this law by 2015. Will you help us make that a reality?&nbsp;<a href="mailto:info@simonsfund.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" shape="rect">Email us</a>&nbsp;to&nbsp;find out what&#8217;s happening in your state.</div>
<div>&nbsp;</div>
<div>P.S. &nbsp;We are still checking hearts and saving lives. This school year, we screened over 2,000 students in Philadelphia, Atlanta and Chicago.</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/one-year-later-the-sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/">One Year Later &#8211; The Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Bill Signing &#8211; Our Remarks</title>
		<link>/blog/the-bill-signing-our-remarks/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2012 11:24:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Legislation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Past Events]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3628</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I need to begin by saying thank you to Jennaphr Frederick, Josh Weisman, Brian Kadunc and Representative Mike Vereb.  The universe brought all of us together on April 14, 2011, and as a result, we are here today making a huge difference in the lives students. Representative Vereb, a big thanks to you (and your [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-bill-signing-our-remarks/">The Bill Signing &#8211; Our Remarks</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I need to begin by saying thank you to Jennaphr Frederick, Josh Weisman, Brian Kadunc and Representative Mike Vereb.  The universe brought all of us together on April 14, 2011, and as a result, we are here today making a huge difference in the lives students.</p>
<p>Representative Vereb, a big thanks to you (and your staff) for your tireless efforts.  We did not realize the champion we were getting that day we met in your office.  Governor Corbett, thank you for your leadership and support on this issue. With your pen stroke here today, you will save the lives of children.</p>
<p>A good friend of ours always says that we are members of a club that no one wants to join.  Phyllis and I became members of that club on January 24, 2005, when our three month old son, Simon, died.  There are other club members here today – the Rodgers Family, the Silva Family and the Frazier family.  It was Akhir Frazier’s story that brought me to Representative Vereb’s office.</p>
<p>Like in all clubs, the members get to decide what they want to get out of it.  Our choice was simple.  We wanted to make sure that we were the last members of this club.  We don’t want you to join. We want your kids to be safer.  This bill is a manifestation of our choice.</p>
<p>We believe that there are three approaches to tackling sudden cardiac arrest and death in children. These approaches are not mutually exclusive.  They work together, in concert.</p>
<p>The first approach is DETECTION.  We need to discover these conditions before they hurt our children.  Simon’s Fund works with schools and organizations to provide free heart screenings.  To date, we’ve checked almost 4,000 hearts and helped at least 38 students discover potentially life threatening heart conditions.  Some of those students are sitting here today.</p>
<p>This weekend, we’ll be at the Liacouris Center with the Athlete Health Organization to provide free sports physicals for over 1,000 high school students in Philly.   Every student will receive an ECG exam.</p>
<p>The second approach is REACTION; how do we respond when a child collapses.  By having AED devices spread throughout our communities, and a population that knows how to perform CPR, we will save lives when sudden cardiac arrest strikes.</p>
<p>The third approach is EDUCATION. The Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act accomplishes this.  Representative Mike Vereb summed it up best &#8211; he said that sudden cardiac arrest is now a household term.  Parents will now be AWARE that sudden cardiac arrest kills at least 2,000 students every year and they’ll guard against it.</p>
<p>Coaches will now be AWARE that fainting is not acceptable and Gatorade is not the remedy.  As a State, we will take these symptoms seriously and do a better job of protecting our children.</p>
<p>This is a tremendous step forward in our quest to save young lives.  We are so proud to be a part of it.</p>
<p>I’d like to close on a personal note.  Phyllis and I cherish this moment.  Simon would have been in first grade this year, positioned nicely in between our daughter, Sally and our son, Jaden.   We are so happy that they are here with us today.</p>
<p>We’re never going to get to go to Simon’s soccer games, choir concerts or graduations. Our moments with him are limited. This bill signing is one of those moments.  This is our ceremony for him.</p>
<p>Finally, I want to share a phrase from one of our favorite songs.</p>
<p>You&#8217;ll be with me; Like a handprint on my heart. And now whatever way our stories end; I know you have re-written mine</p>
<p>This legislation will be the handprint of Simon and Representative Mike Vereb on the hearts of children throughout Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-bill-signing-our-remarks/">The Bill Signing &#8211; Our Remarks</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Media Coverage &#8211; Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act</title>
		<link>/blog/media-coverage-sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 May 2012 01:37:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Legislation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3699</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The following links are stories and reports covering the introduction and passage of the first Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act. PA Law Aims to Prevent Sudden Cardiac Arrest in Young Athletes (FOX News; September 10, 2012) Law Protects Young Athletes from Potential Sudden Cardiac Arrest (WJAC TV 6; August 24, 2012) Protecting Young Athletes from [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/media-coverage-sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/">Media Coverage &#8211; Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The following links are stories and reports covering the introduction and passage of the first Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.simonsheart.org/blog/pressarticles/pennsylvania-law-aims-to-prevent-sudden-cardiac-arrest-in-young-athletes/">PA Law Aims to Prevent Sudden Cardiac Arrest in Young Athletes</a> (FOX News; September 10, 2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.wjactv.com/news/news/law-protects-young-athletes-potential-sudden-cardi/nRKHS/">Law Protects Young Athletes from Potential Sudden Cardiac Arrest</a> (WJAC TV 6; August 24, 2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://video.foxnews.com/v/1799022542001">Protecting Young Athletes from Sudden Cardiac Arrest</a> (FOX News; August 22, 2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.mcall.com/news/local/eastpenn/mc-sudden-cardiac-arrest-20120812,0,3457433.story">Sudden Cardiac Arrest Law Raises Awareness</a> (The Morning Call; August 12, 2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://abclocal.go.com/wpvi/html5/video?id=8768181&pid=null&section=null">Sudden Cardiac Arrest Law</a> (ABC6; August 9; 2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.montgomerynews.com/articles/2012/08/06/perkasie_news_herald/news/doc5020259a8a704384356371.txt">Pennridge to Host Sports Safety Presentation</a> (Montgomery Media; August 6, 2012).</p>
<p><a href="http://www.lehighvalleylive.com/breaking-news/index.ssf/2012/08/lehigh_valley_school_districts_1.html">Lehigh Valley School Districts Educate Parents, Coaches About Sudden Cardiac Arrest (Express-Times</a>; August 5, 2012).</p>
<p><a href="http://www.pennlive.com/bodyandmind/index.ssf/2012/07/coaches_learn_to_look_for_sign.html">Pennsylvania Law Aims to Raise Awareness of Sudden Cardiac Arrest</a> (Penn Live; July 8, 2012).</p>
<p><a href="http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/local/state/law-targets-sudden-cardiac-arrests-in-young-638872/">Law Target Sudden Cardiac Arrests in Young</a> (Pittsburgh Post-Gazette; July 3, 2012).</p>
<p><a href="http://athleticbusiness.com/articles/lexisnexis.aspx?lnarticleid=1694886095&lntopicid=136030023&h=New%20rules%20designed%20to%20prevent%20sudden%20cardiac%20arrest%20in%20young%20athletes">Law to Prevent Sudden Cardiac Arrest in Young Athletes</a> (Athletic Business; June 25, 2012).</p>
<p><a href="http://blogs.edweek.org/edweek/schooled_in_sports/2012/06/pa_governor_signs_sudden_cardiac_arrest_law_for_youth_athletes.html">PA Governor Signs Sudden Cardiac Arrest Law for Youth Athletes</a> (Education Week; June 7, 2012).</p>
<p><a href="http://philadelphia.cbslocal.com/2012/05/30/health-pennsylvania-takes-first-of-its-kind-step-to-protect-student-athletes/">Health: Pennsylvania Takes First of its Kind Step to Protect Student Athletes</a> (CBS3; May 30, 2012).</p>
<p><a href="http://nola.com/newsflash/index.ssf/story/pa-law-to-educate-about-sudden-cardiac-arrest/ac12ef0917934b2181b83bb482d2c154">Pa. Law to Educate About Sudden Cardiac Arrest</a> (Associated Press; May 30, 2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.phillyburbs.com/content/tncms/live/phillyburbs.com/news/state/pa/corbett-inks-law-to-educate-students-about-sudden-cardiac-arrest/article_f26df81e-aa91-11e1-a74f-001a4bcf6878.html">Corbett Inks Law to Educate Students about Sudden Cardiac Arrest in Montco</a> (PhillyBurbs.com; May 30,2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.timesherald.com/article/20120530/NEWS01/120539965/gov-corbett-signs-law-to-set-school-standards-to-help-prevent-sudden-heart-attacks">Gov. Corbett signs Law to Set School Standards to Help Prevent Sudden Heart Attacks</a> (Times Herald; May 30,2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://articles.philly.com/2012-06-01/news/31923681_1_sudden-cardiac-arrest-student-athletes-warning-signs">Corbett Signs Bill to Protect Student Athletes</a> (Philadelphia Inquirer; June 1,2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.wfmj.com/story/18708943/high-school-athletes-in-pennsylvania-will-be-required-to-know-the-symptoms-of-sudden-cardiac-arrest-before">High School Athletes in Pennsylvania Will Be Required to Know the Symptoms of Sudden Cardiac Arrest </a>(WFJM; June 6, 2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/local/state/law-targets-sudden-cardiac-arrests-in-young-638872/"> Law Targets Sudden Cardiac Arrest in the Young</a> (Pittsburgh Post Gazette; June 11, 2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.pennlive.com/newsflash/index.ssf/story/new-rules-designed-to-prevent-sudden-cardiac-arrest-in-young-athletes/0bac39c78c384908a45edf348c0137b5">New Rules Designed to Prevent Sudden Cardiac Arrest in Young Athletes</a> (PennLive.com; June 25,2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.digitaljournal.com/pr/773091">PATS 2012 Clinical Symposium Leads the Discussion with the Sudden Cardiac Arrest Forum</a> ( Digital Journal June 30,2012 )</p>
<p><a href="http://plymouthwhitemarsh.patch.com/articles/new-laws-protect-student-athletes-from-concussions-cardiac-arrest">New Laws Protect Student Athletes from Concussions, Cardiac Arrest</a> (Plymouth-Whitemarsh Patch July 28,2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.mcall.com/news/local/eastpenn/mc-sudden-cardiac-arrest-20120812,0,3457433.story">Sudden Cardiac Arrest Law Raises Awareness</a> (East Penn News August 13,2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.wjactv.com/news/news/law-protects-young-athletes-potential-sudden-cardi/nRKHS/">Law Protects Young Athletes from Potential Sudden Cardiac Arrest</a> (WJACTV.Com  August 24, 2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://video.foxnews.com/v/1803422248001/protecting-student-athletes/">Protecting Student Athletes</a> (FOXNEWS August 25, 2012)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.timesherald.com/article/20120923/NEWS01/120929838/rep-mike-vereb-participates-in-heart-screening">Rep. Mike Vereb Participates in Heart Screening</a> (Times Herald September 23,2012)</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/media-coverage-sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/">Media Coverage &#8211; Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>NJ Pushes AED Legislation</title>
		<link>/blog/nj-pushes-aed-legislation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2012 00:53:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Legislation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3483</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>TRENTON – Legislation sponsored by Senator Joseph F. Vitale that would require schools, recreational departments and youth camps to have automated external defibrillators (AED) for youth athletic events was unanimously approved today by the Senate Education Committee. The bill is an attempt to reduce the number of youth athletes who die from sudden cardiac arrest [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/nj-pushes-aed-legislation/">NJ Pushes AED Legislation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>TRENTON – Legislation sponsored by Senator Joseph F. Vitale that would require schools, recreational departments and youth camps to have automated external defibrillators (AED) for youth athletic events was unanimously approved today by the Senate Education Committee.</p>
<p>The bill is an attempt to reduce the number of youth athletes who die from sudden cardiac arrest (SCA) – a condition where the heart’s electrical system malfunctions and stops pumping blood to the rest of the body, often without any visible symptoms.</p>
<p>“In the US, an estimated 7,000 children die each year from sudden cardiac arrest with student athletes two to three times more likely to suffer and die from this silent killer,” said Vitale (D-Middlesex). “By simply having an automated external defibrillator on hand at sporting events and practices and training coaches and staff to properly use these life-saving devices, these deaths could be prevented.”</p>
<p>The bill, S-157, would require that both public and nonpublic kindergarten through twelfth grade schools have an AED available within reasonable proximity of the athletic field or gym where school-sponsored events and team practices take place and that an on-site coach or other staff member is trained in CPR and to use an AED. All municipal or county recreation departments, nonprofit youth-serving organizations and youth camps must also have an AED accessible to athletic events and practices with at least one umpire, coach, counselor or staff member trained in CPR and use of an AED. A state-certified emergency services provider or other first responder could fulfill this requirement.</p>
<p>Read more: <a href="http://njtoday.net/2012/01/23/senate-committee-advances-bill-to-protect-child-athletes-from-sudden-cardiac-arrest/#ixzz1nA6HkmrD">http://njtoday.net/2012/01/23/senate-committee-advances-bill-to-protect-child-athletes-from-sudden-cardiac-arrest/#ixzz1nA6HkmrD</a><br />
Tell everyone to get New Jersey News from WWW.NJTODAY.NET</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/nj-pushes-aed-legislation/">NJ Pushes AED Legislation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>PA Lawmakers Focus on Student Athletes</title>
		<link>/blog/pa-lawmakers-focus-on-student-athletes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2011 16:32:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Legislation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3123</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Kudos to the PA Senate (and previously the PA House) for passing the Safety in Youth Sports Act (SB 200).  They join 30 other states that have passed this type of legislation.  The bill is now waiting to be signed by the Governor. Over the last few years, there has been a big push (driven by the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/pa-lawmakers-focus-on-student-athletes/">PA Lawmakers Focus on Student Athletes</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Kudos to the PA Senate (and previously the PA House) for passing the <a href="http://www.legis.state.pa.us/cfdocs/billInfo/billInfo.cfm?sYear=2011&sInd=0&body=S&type=B&bn=200">Safety in Youth Sports Act (SB 200)</a>.  They join <a href="http://www.sportsconcussions.org/laws.html">30 other states</a> that have passed this type of legislation.  The bill is now waiting to be signed by the Governor.</p>
<p>Over the last few years, there has been a big push (driven by the NFL) to protect the heads of students athletes.  Far too many students experience concussions, and the symptoms are ignored.  This can lead to severe injury or possibly death. This bill prevents such careless behavior by ensuring that any athlete with symptoms must be cleared by a medical professional before returning to competition.</p>
<p>But PA lawmakers aren&#8217;t stopping there.  Unlike the other states, PA is also looking after the hearts of student athletes. Sudden cardiac arrest is the #1 killer of student athletes.  Fainting is the #1 warning sign of sudden cardiac arrest.  So it only makes sense to have a law that protects the heart too.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.legis.state.pa.us/CFDOCS/Legis/PN/Public/btCheck.cfm?txtType=PDF&sessYr=2011&sessInd=0&billBody=H&billTyp=B&billNbr=1610&pn=2118">The Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act (HB 1610)</a> unanimously passed the House in October.  It protects the student athlete by requiring any student who exhibits symptoms of sudden cardiac arrest be examined and cleared by a medical professional before returning to competition.  It is now being considered in the Senate.  We anxiously await its passage and look forward to PA being the first state that protects the head and the heart of our young athletes.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/pa-lawmakers-focus-on-student-athletes/">PA Lawmakers Focus on Student Athletes</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bills to Protect Athletes Head to State Senate</title>
		<link>/blog/bills-to-protect-athletes-head-to-state-senate/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2011 01:43:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Legislation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=2700</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>After she was treated for a concussion at a local hospital, an emergency room doctor gave the high school athlete a note saying she could return to her sport after one week. A week later, though, when the school district&#8217;s athletic trainer retested her brain to see if it was healed, he found it was [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/bills-to-protect-athletes-head-to-state-senate/">Bills to Protect Athletes Head to State Senate</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After she was treated for a concussion at a local hospital, an emergency room doctor gave the high school athlete a note saying she could return to her sport after one week.</p>
<div id="blox-story-text">
<p>A week later, though, when the school district&#8217;s athletic trainer retested her brain to see if it was healed, he found it was not even close to her non-injured baseline score. He benched her until she had an evaluation by a neurologist.</p>
<p>In recent years, more local school districts have taken steps to protect young athletes from injuries, or worse, on the field. Now the Pennsylvania Legislature is considering two bills designed to protect student athletes and increase awareness of brain injuries and undetected heart disorders.</p>
<p>Pennsylvania House members passed the Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention and the Safety in Youth Sports Acts last week. Both bills now move to the Senate, which reconvenes next week. The Senate is expected to pass both bills, which could be forwarded to Gov. Tom Corbett before the end of the year. Both will cover middle and high schools and affilated youth sports groups.</p>
<p>Each bill is similar in scope, including mandatory education and training for coaches about the conditions requiring players to be removed from the playing field if they show symptoms, and requiring medical clearance before a student can return to the sport. They would cover students competing in school-related sports including non-competitive cheerleading.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.phillyburbs.com/blogs/working_my_butt/bills-targeting-student-athletes-head-to-senate/article_2b6206a7-bf43-5615-8e55-38464669517f.html">Full story</a></p>
<p>By Jo Ciavaglia Staff writer</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/bills-to-protect-athletes-head-to-state-senate/">Bills to Protect Athletes Head to State Senate</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Brains, Hearts, Concussions and Cardiac Arrest</title>
		<link>/blog/brains-hearts-concussions-and-cardiac-arrest/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2010 14:40:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Legislation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1140</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Kudos to the State of New Jersey for passing a concussion safety bill.  Governor Christie, accompanied by NFL Commissioner Roger Goodell, Jets owner Woody Johnson and Sen. Richard Codey (D-Essex) signed the bill into law.  Now, student athletes that suffer a concussion on the field must be sidelined until they are cleared by a doctor. There [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/brains-hearts-concussions-and-cardiac-arrest/">Brains, Hearts, Concussions and Cardiac Arrest</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Kudos to the State of New Jersey for passing a <a href="http://www.nj.com/hssports/blog/football/index.ssf/2010/12/gov_christie_signs_legislation_creating_concussion_awareness_and_prevention_program.html">concussion safety bill</a>.  Governor Christie, accompanied by NFL Commissioner Roger Goodell, Jets owner Woody Johnson and Sen. Richard Codey (D-Essex) signed the bill into law.  Now, student athletes that suffer a concussion on the field must be sidelined until they are cleared by a doctor.</p>
<p>There are alot of kids that suffer concussions every year while engaged in sport.  I don&#8217;t know how many of them go on to suffer a debilitating brain injury or die, but does that statistic really matter?  Isn&#8217;t the brain an important enough organ to warrant a little extra caution and care?  I think so.</p>
<p>Which gets me to my next point.  I&#8217;m not sure why this bill didn&#8217;t include the same safeguards for student athletes that faint or collapse on the field.  We know that fainting is the PRIMARY warning sign of sudden cardiac arrest.  We know that kids are fainting and/or passing out regularly while engaged in strenuous sport.  We know that thousands of kids die every year from sudden cardiac arrest.</p>
<p>Shouldn&#8217;t they be required to seek clearance too before they can return to their sport?  Isn&#8217;t the heart an important enough organ to warrant a little extra caution and care?</p>
<p>I applaud the brain injury lobby on their monumental efforts to get this legislation passed.  I hope that the sudden cardiac arrest lobby can unite and do the same.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/brains-hearts-concussions-and-cardiac-arrest/">Brains, Hearts, Concussions and Cardiac Arrest</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
