<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Simon&#039;s Heart News Archives -</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/simons-fund-news/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Protecting Hearts and Saving Lives</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2021 18:29:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/simons-fav-icon1.png</url>
	<title>Simon&#039;s Heart News Archives -</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Philadelphia Phillies</title>
		<link>/blog/philadelphia-phillies/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarita Rajpoot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 13:09:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9930</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Simon’s Heart is the proud recipient of a $20,000 grant from Phillies Charities, Inc. Grants were provided in part from the support of Phillies fans who participated in the team’s auctions, raffles and memorabilia events held this past baseball season. Upon learning of the grant, Simon’s Heart Executive Director Jenn Parrado said, “The support of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/philadelphia-phillies/">Philadelphia Phillies</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Simon’s Heart is the proud recipient of a $20,000 grant from Phillies Charities, Inc. Grants were provided in part from the support of Phillies fans who participated in the team’s auctions, raffles and memorabilia events held this past baseball season. Upon learning of the grant, Simon’s Heart Executive Director Jenn Parrado said, “The support of the Philadelphia Phillies means the world to Simon’s Heart because sudden cardiac arrest is the #1 cause of death in youth athletes. We are grateful to share our mission and save lives!”</p>
<p>The generous grant will be used to provide free heart screenings, AEDs where children learn and play, and CPR Education in communities so that young hearts are protected long into the future. “These remarkable organizations continuously step up to the plate to be there for those who need it most,” said Phillies Charities, Inc. President John Weber. “Thanks to our fans, we are able to help ensure that the much-needed services of our community heroes can continue to make a difference all year long.”</p>
<p>About Simon’s Heart:<br />
SIMON’S HEART is a 501(c)(3) founded in memory of 3-month-old Simon Sudman who died suddenly from an undetected heart condition. The organization is committed to a future in which parents and communities don’t lose children to detectable and treatable heart conditions.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/philadelphia-phillies/">Philadelphia Phillies</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Club saves lives while fundraising during pandemic</title>
		<link>/blog/club-saves-lives-while-fundraising-during-pandemic/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarita Rajpoot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 12:55:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AED Save]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9926</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>WHAT: Colonial Soccer Club is taking steps to protect hearts and place AEDs throughout the Plymouth Meeting, Whitemarsh, and Conshohocken region. The Louis T. Savino, III Foundation and Simon’s Heart collaborated with Colonial Soccer to fund 9 AEDs to 13 soccer fields. AEDs and CPR Education will be provided during the Bill Lapp Soccer Tournament. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/club-saves-lives-while-fundraising-during-pandemic/">Club saves lives while fundraising during pandemic</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>WHAT: Colonial Soccer Club is taking steps to protect hearts and place AEDs throughout the Plymouth Meeting, Whitemarsh, and Conshohocken region. The Louis T. Savino, III Foundation and Simon’s Heart collaborated with Colonial Soccer to fund 9 AEDs to 13 soccer fields. AEDs and CPR Education will be provided during the Bill Lapp Soccer Tournament. Athletes will grab a ball, pick a song, and push to the beat. Surprise, they’re learning CPR! The Club looks to deepen their fundraising efforts to provide 3 more AEDs and further heart safety education in the community before the end of 2021.</p>
<p>WHO: Colonial Soccer Club | Louis T. Savino, III Foundation | Simon’s Heart | 5,000 spectators</p>
<p>WHEN: Saturday October 16th, 2021 | Bill Lapp Soccer Tournament</p>
<p>WHERE: Victory Fields | 201 E Germantown Pike, Colonial Dr, Lafayette Hill, PA</p>
<p>WHY: Sudden Cardiac Arrest isn’t just an adult thing. It is the #1 cause of death of student athletes and takes the lives of thousands of students every year. Colonial Soccer Club partners with The Louis T. Savino, III Foundation and Simon’s Heart to protect<br />
hearts and save lives.</p>
<p>COLONIAL SOCCER CLUB | A note from Brian Cammarota, Health + Safety Coordinator | “It has been a dream of mine to assure that every heart is protected every day on Colonial Soccer Club fields. Thank you to the Louis T. Savino, III Foundation and Simon’s Heart.” <a href="https://www.colonialsoccerclub.org/">www.colonialsoccerclub.org</a></p>
<p>LOUIS T. SAVINO, III FOUNDATION was founded in memory of Louis who died suddenly in 2000 at the age of 15 on a soccer field from an undetected heart condition. An AED could have saved his life. The Foundation is dedicated to increasing awareness of, and preventing, sudden cardiac death (SCD) in youth. <a href="http://www.savinofoundation.org/">www.savinofoundation.org</a></p>
<p>SIMON’S HEART is a 501(c)(3) founded in memory of 3 month old Simon Sudman who died suddenly from an undetected heart condition. The organization is committed to a future in which parents and communities don’t lose children to detectable and treatable heart conditions. <a href="/">www.simonsheart.org</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/club-saves-lives-while-fundraising-during-pandemic/">Club saves lives while fundraising during pandemic</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Welcome, Dominic Folino, to Simon’s Heart!</title>
		<link>/blog/welcome-dominic-folino-to-simons-heart/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jenn Parrado]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2021 07:05:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9845</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>With all eyes on our children as they return to school, it’s more important than ever to continue advocating to protect hearts. For 17 years we have advocated for coaches, athletes, and families to receive education about the signs of Sudden Cardiac Arrest (SCA). In 2012, Simon’s Heart advocacy efforts led Pennsylvania to become the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/welcome-dominic-folino-to-simons-heart/">Welcome, Dominic Folino, to Simon’s Heart!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With all eyes on our children as they return to school, it’s more important than ever to continue advocating to protect hearts. For 17 years we have advocated for coaches, athletes, and families to receive education about the signs of Sudden Cardiac Arrest (SCA). In 2012, Simon’s Heart advocacy efforts led </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Pennsylvania to become the first state in the country to protect students from sudden cardiac arrest. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Since then, fifteen states have followed suit and adopted new legislation to protect hearts.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I’m pleased to share that this month, Dominic Folino has joined our </span><a href="/leadership/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">board of directors</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> as the Director of Advocacy where he’ll spearhead our efforts to expand the <a href="/sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/">SCA Prevention Act</a> to all 50 states. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dom is the President of Spectrum Strategies where his focus is on government affairs, business development, strategic planning, and blockchain education and solutions for various organizations. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Formerly, Dominic was the Vice President of External Affairs at FS Investments. He helped manage the firm&#8217;s political, lobbying, charitable, and community initiatives, including FS&#8217;s political action committee and its charitable affiliate, The FS Foundation.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Before joining FS Investments, Dominic served as the Executive Director of Volunteer Medical Services Corps of Lower Merion and Narberth. He began his career in politics working for various campaigns in Philadelphia and the surrounding area. Dominic also served as Chief of Staff to a member of the Pennsylvania House of Representatives. Service to the community has always been important to Dominic. He helped start the FS Foundation and currently serves as the advisory board co-chair for Volunteer Medical Services Corp of Lower Merion and Narberth and is a board member of the Police Athletic League.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dominic is a graduate of La Salle University. He also completed the Accelerated Management Program at the Yale School of Management and is currently pursuing an MBA at Villanova University.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Thank you, Dom, for protecting hearts and saving lives with us.</span></p>
<p><span class="il">Jenn</span> Parrado | Executive Director</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/welcome-dominic-folino-to-simons-heart/">Welcome, Dominic Folino, to Simon’s Heart!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Next Chapter &#8211; A New Leader</title>
		<link>/blog/the-next-chapter-a-new-leader/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 12:08:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9416</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Today marks another milestone in my journey since the loss of Simon. I step down as Executive Director of Simon’s Heart and welcome Jennifer Parrado with open arms. Jenn comes to us from the Leukemia &#038; Lymphoma Society where she served as the Regional Advancement Director. She has spent the last ten years raising awareness, advocating, and fundraising [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-next-chapter-a-new-leader/">The Next Chapter &#8211; A New Leader</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today marks another milestone in my journey since the loss of Simon. I step down as Executive Director of Simon’s Heart and welcome Jennifer Parrado with open arms.</p>
<p>Jenn comes to us from the Leukemia & Lymphoma Society where she served as the Regional Advancement Director. She has spent the last ten years raising awareness, advocating, and fundraising for some amazing causes. So, she’s qualified. More importantly, she is smart, considerate, passionate, humble and witty. She possesses the qualities we value.</p>
<p>It was June 2012, right after the Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act was signed into law. Simon’s Heart and Representative Mike Vereb made Pennsylvania the first state to pass legislation to protect student athletes <u>from</u> sudden cardiac arrest.  The law requires coaches, parents and students to learn about the risks and warning signs of sudden cardiac arrest. Athletes who are symptomatic must be removed from play and cannot return until cleared by a licensed medical professional.</p>
<p>As we celebrated this major accomplishment, the board asked me a question. If you can host heart screenings and pass a law as a part-time volunteer, what can we accomplish if you do this full time? I had major reservations about making a career out of my loss. I’ll never forget the advice my friend and business partner gave me. Imagine yourself five years from now. Our business and Simon’s Heart are both doing great. Which one makes you more excited and proud?  That’s where you should work. I am so blessed to have wise friends.</p>
<p>The Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act has become law in fourteen states. Every year, two million student athletes across the country, along with their parents and coaches, learn about sudden cardiac arrest. Over one million coaches have been educated by our training video. We have provided heart screenings for 18,000 + students. Data from our registry has been used to publish seven abstracts and two manuscripts. We partnered with the NCAA to fund research. We introduced a new way to teach kids about CPR using music and balls. We placed hundreds of AED devices in youth-related facilities through partnerships with sports teams and our crowdfunding site. We provide educational materials to youth organizations around the country to educate their students.</p>
<p>I am so proud of this organization &#8211; family, co-workers, supporters and partners &#8211; for all of these accomplishments. In the face of unimaginable tragedy, we responded with innovative programs that protect hearts and save lives. It’s hard to believe it’s been fifteen years. I can still feel the energy and urgency that existed when we began.</p>
<p>How do I know I’m making the right decision to step down? I don’t. But, I try to imagine Simon’s Heart five years from now. It’s bigger and better. It has impacted more families and helped change a standard of care. Jenn and Jill are running the show (with others too, hopefully). All of you are rallying behind them. I am contributing as a co-founder and board member.</p>
<p>This vision makes me the most proud and excited. It reveals an impactful, sustainable and lifesaving organization.</p>
<p>Jenn and Jill, my family and the board of directors can’t wait to see the places you’ll go. We’ll be right beside you.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-next-chapter-a-new-leader/">The Next Chapter &#8211; A New Leader</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Simon&#8217;s Heart Begins Executive Search</title>
		<link>/blog/executive-search/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 17:13:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9266</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Today, Darren Sudman, announced that he will stepping down from the day to day operations at Simon&#8217;s Heart this year. Darren and his wife, Phyllis, co-founded the organization fifteen years ago following the sudden and unexpected death of their son, Simon. Over the last eight years, Darren has served as the Executive Director of Simon’s [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/executive-search/">Simon&#8217;s Heart Begins Executive Search</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today, Darren Sudman, announced that he will stepping down from the day to day operations at Simon&#8217;s Heart this year. Darren and his wife, Phyllis, co-founded the organization fifteen years ago following the sudden and unexpected death of their son, Simon. Over the last eight years, Darren has served as the Executive Director of Simon’s Heart and he will continue his work into the Fall to ensure a smooth and successful leadership transition.</p>
<p>As a result, Simon’s Heart is commencing a search for its next inspiring leader and the process will be led by board members, Rayna Jones and Ken Fair. The successful candidate will be curious, passionate and inspiring. S/he will be eager to expand on the programs that have been protecting the lives of children, which include youth heart screenings, a national cardiac registry, a crowdfunding site for AED devices, and a hands-only CPR activation.</p>
<p>“It&#8217;s time for a change,&#8221; said Darren Sudman.  &#8220;After Simon died, there was no obvious path forward. We decided to lean in and use our tragedy to prevent other families from losing children to detectable and treatable heart conditions. The time is right for me to take a step back, exhale and invite another innovative and passionate leader to protect hearts and save lives. I’m excited to see where this leads, and I look forward to serving on the board and being a co-founder. Simon will always be my son and this will always be my cause.&#8221;</p>
<p>“We will miss Darren&#8217;s leadership and passion in day-to-day operations, but we are also excited for the Sudman family,&#8221; said Eldwin Thay, Board Chair.  &#8220;They have sacrificed so much and have shared their grief so publicly to build an organization that educates and engages students and parents about sudden cardiac arrest and death. Simon&#8217;s Heart is in a really good place and we are excited to welcome a new leader to continue our great work in the community.&#8221;</p>
<p>Qualified candidates can find application <a href="/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/ED-Job-Description-Final.pdf">information here.</a></p>
<p>To recommend a candidate, please send an email to <a href="mailto:career@simonsheart.org">career@simonsheart.org</a>.</p>
<p>Darren shares more insight into his decision to step back in this <a href="https://youtu.be/JL8tEWNeKGg">brief video</a>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/executive-search/">Simon&#8217;s Heart Begins Executive Search</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>NFL Picks Simon&#8217;s Fund</title>
		<link>/blog/nfl-picks-simons-fund/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2017 17:40:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AED]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[athlete]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NFL]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.simonsfund.org/?p=7753</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Cleveland Browns will likely pick Myles Garrett. The 49ers, Solomon Thomas, and so on and so forth. But yesterday, at the Draft Kick Off Event, the NFL picked Simon&#8217;s Fund. Ron Jaworski, former Philadelphia Eagles quarterback and co-host of the 2017 Draft, called out Simon&#8217;s Fund, the Philadelphia School District and Urban Roots for their work [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/nfl-picks-simons-fund/">NFL Picks Simon&#8217;s Fund</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Cleveland Browns will likely pick Myles Garrett. The 49ers, Solomon Thomas, and so on and so forth. But yesterday, at the Draft Kick Off Event, the <u><a href="http://www.newsworks.org/index.php/local/arts-culture/103374-nfls-gig-football-fan-fest-includes-community-improvements-for-philly" target="_blank">NFL picked Simon&#8217;s Fund</a></u>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.simonsfund.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/draft.jpg"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" class="aligncenter wp-image-7754 size-full" src="https://www.simonsfund.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/draft.jpg" alt="draft" width="640" height="480" srcset="https://simonsfund.wpenginepowered.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/draft.jpg 640w, https://simonsfund.wpenginepowered.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/04/draft-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></a></p>
<p align="left">Ron Jaworski, former Philadelphia Eagles quarterback and co-host of the 2017 Draft, <a href="https://business.facebook.com/simonsfund/videos/1621582657874890/" target="_blank">called out Simon&#8217;s Fund</a>, the Philadelphia School District and Urban Roots for their work in the community. All of us will receive a Legacy Project grant.</p>
<h4 align="left"><strong>To celebrate this accomplishment, we are giving away two tickets to the upcoming draft for Saturday, April 29!  </strong></h4>
<p align="left"><span class="span_font"><span class="span_font_wrapper">You&#8217;ll get exclusive access to the Eagles Nest &#8211; a reserved viewing area at the NFL Draft Experience. To qualify for this drawing, simply start a campaign at <a href="http://www.gotaed.org/" target="_blank">GotAED</a> and get at least one contribution by 4 PM on Friday, April 28. We&#8217;ll pick the winner and make arrangements to get you the tickets.</span></span></p>
<p align="left"><span class="span_font"><span class="span_font_wrapper">Whether it is heart screenings, advocating for legislation to protect student athletes, gathering data for research, or launching a crowdfunding site to distribute AEDs to youth facilities, awareness is at our core. </span></span></p>
<p align="left"><span class="span_font"><span class="span_font_wrapper">It is incredible that the NFL is willing to lend its voice to our cause, and further validate our campaign &#8211; </span></span><u><span class="span_font"><span class="span_font_wrapper"><a href="https://business.facebook.com/simonsfund/photos/a.165191386847365.34336.155288434504327/1494235460609611/?type=3&theater" target="_blank">&#8220;You&#8217;ve thought about his head. What about his heart?&#8221;</a></span></span></u></p>
<p><span class="span_font"><span class="span_font_wrapper">We are so grateful and blessed to have them as partner in our mission.  </span></span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/nfl-picks-simons-fund/">NFL Picks Simon&#8217;s Fund</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Pediatric Poster Campaign</title>
		<link>/blog/pediatric-poster-campaign/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2014 20:26:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=5909</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Heart Month may be coming to an end, but the battle to raise awareness about sudden cardiac arrest and death in children is a year-round effort.  The American Academy of Pediatrics estimates that two thousand U.S. children die every year from sudden cardiac arrest.  A study from the Mayo Clinic shows that it is responsible [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/pediatric-poster-campaign/">Pediatric Poster Campaign</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Heart Month may be coming to an end, but the battle to raise awareness about sudden cardiac arrest and death in children is a year-round effort.  The American Academy of Pediatrics estimates that two thousand U.S. children die every year from sudden cardiac arrest.  A study from the Mayo Clinic shows that it is responsible for up to 15% of all sudden infant deaths (SIDS).  Furthermore, the AHA recently published a study showing that sudden cardiac arrest isn’t so sudden – there are warning signs.</p>
<p>Armed with this information, Simon’s Fund, a Plymouth Meeting based nonprofit organization founded in memory of Simon Sudman, a seemingly healthy baby boy who died from sudden cardiac arrest, teamed up with the Pennsylvania Chapter of the American Academy of Pediatrics, to produce a full color poster for every pediatric office in the Commonwealth.  The poster campaign educates parents about the warning signs of conditions that lead to sudden cardiac arrest, like fainting during exercise, which is the #1 warning sign.  The posters were created and paid for by Simon’s Fund.</p>
<p>“We are very excited to be working with Simon’s Fund on this campaign. It is our hope that these posters will supplement the efforts of our pediatricians to educate patients and families about sudden cardiac arrest,” says Allen Nussbaum, MD, FAAP, President of the PA Chapter of the AAP.</p>
<p>“This project fits perfectly within our mission,” says Darren Sudman, Executive Director and Co-Founder of Simon’s Fund.  We need to make sudden cardiac arrest a household term so that students, parents and coaches appreciate the threat of sudden cardiac arrest and recognize the symptoms.  This bright and engaging poster will deliver that information in a very positive and upbeat tone.”</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/SimonsFund_PediatricPoster.jpg"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-5910" src="https://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/SimonsFund_PediatricPoster-250x300.jpg" alt="simonsheart_PediatricPoster" width="250" height="300" /></a><a href="http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/AAP-Poster-Campaign.pdf"><br />
</a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/pediatric-poster-campaign/">Pediatric Poster Campaign</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Heartfelt Mission</title>
		<link>/blog/a-heartfelt-mission/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2011 17:25:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1638</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Simon&#8217;s Fund honors a tot whose sudden death has long-lasting impact on research Rachel Vigoda Jewish Exponent Feature March 10, 2011 Simon Prushan, 12, is getting ready for his Bar Mitzvah this fall. He&#8217;s learning the aliyahs, practicing his Haftorah portion &#8212; and setting up heart screenings for students in the Radnor School District. For [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/a-heartfelt-mission/">A Heartfelt Mission</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>Simon&#8217;s Fund honors a tot whose sudden death has long-lasting impact on research</h4>
<p>Rachel Vigoda<br />
Jewish Exponent Feature<br />
March 10, 2011</p>
<p>Simon Prushan, 12, is getting ready for his Bar Mitzvah this fall. He&#8217;s learning the aliyahs, practicing his Haftorah portion &#8212; and setting up heart screenings for students in the Radnor School District. <img decoding="async" class="alignright" title="The Sudman Family" src="https://www.jewishexponent.com/images/publications/mar102011/health.jpg" alt="" width="165" height="179" /></p>
<p>For his mitzvah project, recommended for all Bar Mitzvah-age members of Main Line Reform Temple, Beth Elohim in Wynnewood, Prushan teamed up with Simon&#8217;s Fund (simonsheart.org), a local nonprofit that aims to prevent sudden cardiac arrest in kids by raising both awareness about heart conditions and money for heart screenings.</p>
<p>Prushan&#8217;s goal is to organize a day of screenings for 300 Radnor students next month and to convince the athletic department at his school, Radnor Middle, to make screenings mandatory for all student athletes.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.jewishexponent.com/article/23052/">FULL STORY</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/a-heartfelt-mission/">A Heartfelt Mission</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>By Providing Free Heart Screenings, Simon&#8217;s Fund Teams with Children&#8217;s Hospital to Honor Akhir Frazier and Prevent Other Student Athlete Deaths</title>
		<link>/blog/by-providing-free-heart-screenings-simons-fund-teams-with-childrens-hospital-to-honor-akhir-frazier-and-prevent-other-student-athlete-deaths/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2010 14:49:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1072</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Simon’s Fund Continues Mission to Help Save Children’s Lives Through Free Heart Screenings in Memory of Three Month Old Son NORRISTOWN, PA – October 27, 2010 – This Saturday, October 30th, Simon’s Fund will host a free heart screening for students of the Norristown School District, ages 10 – 19 from 8:30am to 4pm at [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/by-providing-free-heart-screenings-simons-fund-teams-with-childrens-hospital-to-honor-akhir-frazier-and-prevent-other-student-athlete-deaths/">By Providing Free Heart Screenings, Simon&#8217;s Fund Teams with Children&#8217;s Hospital to Honor Akhir Frazier and Prevent Other Student Athlete Deaths</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;"><strong><em>Simon’s Fund Continues Mission to Help Save Children’s Lives Through Free Heart Screenings in Memory of Three Month Old Son </em></strong></p>
<p>NORRISTOWN, PA – October 27, 2010 – This Saturday, October 30th, Simon’s Fund will host a free heart screening for students of the Norristown School District, ages 10 – 19 from 8:30am to 4pm at Norristown Area High School. Conducted by the medical team from Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia (CHOP) led by Dr. Victoria Vetter, each student will receive an ECG exam, a physical exam, and if necessary, an echocardiogram. Simon’s Fund’s Norristown screening is being held in memory of Akhir Frazier, a standout basketball player, who collapsed suddenly while playing basketball at the Hank Gather’s Rec Center.  Frazier was supposed to attend Norristown Area High School this year.</p>
<p>Every year thousands of children like Akhir die too soon from sudden cardiac arrest. A simple heart screening, like the one being offered by Simon’s Fund this Saturday, will detect up to 85 percent of the conditions that lead to sudden cardiac arrest and death. Students may register for the screening at simonsheart.org/register.</p>
<p>Simon’s Fund and CHOP have been providing heart screenings for students for the past four years and have screened more than 2,000 students.  Aggregated data from the screenings shows that 1 out of every 100 children screened will discover a potentially fatal heart condition.  These findings are consistent with studies conducted in Italy where all young athletes are screened.  In Italy, the incidence of sudden cardiac death in young adults has decreased by 89 percent since implementing the mandatory screenings.</p>
<p>Simon’s Fund was created by Phyllis and Darren Sudman following the passing of Simon Sudman, their three-month-old son who died suddenly in his sleep in January 2004. While investigating the cause of his death, the Sudman Family was advised to get ECG exams. As a result, Phyllis Sudman was diagnosed with Long QT Syndrome, a condition that can lead to sudden cardiac arrest and/or death.  Most of these conditions can be detected with an ECG exam and treated with medication.  Simon&#8217;s Fund is committed to raising awareness about these conditions and providing free heart screenings to students in the region.</p>
<p>&#8220;All of our children get their eyes examined.  They get a hearing test.  We need to start checking their hearts too,&#8221; says Phyllis Sudman, co-founder of Simon&#8217;s Fund.  “By providing this very inexpensive, painless and effective exam, we will decrease the number of children that drop dead from sudden cardiac arrest.&#8221;</p>
<p>To register and attend the screening, please visit dev.simonsheart.org/register or email events@simonsfund.org.</p>
<p>###</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/by-providing-free-heart-screenings-simons-fund-teams-with-childrens-hospital-to-honor-akhir-frazier-and-prevent-other-student-athlete-deaths/">By Providing Free Heart Screenings, Simon&#8217;s Fund Teams with Children&#8217;s Hospital to Honor Akhir Frazier and Prevent Other Student Athlete Deaths</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Simon&#8217;s Fund Captured by Please Touch Museum</title>
		<link>/blog/simons-fund-captured-by-please-touch-museum/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2010 21:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1025</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This video was produced by Please Touch Museum for the Great Friend to Kids Award.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/simons-fund-captured-by-please-touch-museum/">Simon&#8217;s Fund Captured by Please Touch Museum</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZCJ4vaNnZLQ">video</a> was produced by Please Touch Museum for the Great Friend to Kids Award.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZCJ4vaNnZLQ"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-1027" title="GFTK" src="https://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2010/10/GFTK.jpg" alt="" width="120" height="120" /></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/simons-fund-captured-by-please-touch-museum/">Simon&#8217;s Fund Captured by Please Touch Museum</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
