<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Nonprofits Archives -</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/nonprofits/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Protecting Hearts and Saving Lives</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 05:15:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/simons-fav-icon1.png</url>
	<title>Nonprofits Archives -</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Being a Part of Something Bigger</title>
		<link>/blog/being-a-part-of-something-bigger/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2014 22:18:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[A Parent's Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nonprofits]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=5826</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I am on my way home from the 9th Annual Parent Heart Watch Conference. I sit on the Board and Simon&#8217;s Fund was a sponsor. It is a great organization that brings families and organizations together. Here are some thoughts that I shared with the attendees. Simon’s Fund is really happy to join the likes [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/being-a-part-of-something-bigger/">Being a Part of Something Bigger</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am on my way home from the 9th Annual <a href="http://www.parentheartwatch.org/">Parent Heart Watch Conference</a>. I sit on the Board and Simon&#8217;s Fund was a sponsor. It is a great organization that brings families and organizations together. Here are some thoughts that I shared with the attendees.</p>
<p>Simon’s Fund is really happy to join the likes of the Acomporas and sponsor this Conference because it is something very special. We all have something in common &#8211; our lives have been touched by sudden cardiac arrest. However, we are all in this room together because we want to do something about it.</p>
<p>As we saw in the Members&#8217; Rock Presentation this morning, many of us are doing great things in our hometown, but at a place like this, we figure out how to do it bigger and better. We make new discoveries. We find new friends. We talk about best practices. We connect the dots. Really, the possibilities of what we can accomplish are endless.</p>
<p>Let me share a few examples. This past year, with the help of the Nick of Time Foundation, we launched a new website called Screen Across America. It identifies over forty organizations across the country who regularly provide youth heart screenings.</p>
<p>It shows the world that heart screenings aren’t just the pet projects of grieving parents, but that they are part of a national movement.  This concept would not have been developed without our involvement in Parent Heart Watch.</p>
<p>Two years ago, we passed the Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act in Pennsylvania. It has already been introduced in six other states, and is expected to be introduced in six more by the end of 2014.  We have worked with many of you in this room on this legislation. This success would not have happened without our involvement in Parent Heart Watch.</p>
<p>I want to take a second and give a shout out to one of these groups because they blow me way.  There are eight students here this weekend from Florida. In 2007, they lost their high school teammate and friend, Rafe. In response, they formed Who We Play For. It is six years later and they are all in college now. They are meeting at 7 AM on Tuesday mornings, going to Orlando to help Martha with heart screenings, traveling to Tallahassee to meet with lawmakers, and placing AEDs around their community. You guys are inspiring. You are also showing up all of us old people.</p>
<p>I hope that this is a very meaningful conference for all of you. I hope that it helps you heal and inspires you to go home to do great things. I also hope that it makes you a believer in the power of Parent Heart Watch, so that as we continue our personal journeys, we will also be thinking about how we can support each other and this great organization.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/being-a-part-of-something-bigger/">Being a Part of Something Bigger</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Trade Secrets</title>
		<link>/blog/trade-secrets/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2013 02:09:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nonprofits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nick of Time]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trade secrets]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=4400</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Imagine this . . . Yuengling, America&#8217;s oldest brewery in the country (and based outside of Philly) is invited to visit Mike&#8217;s Hard Lemonade in Seattle. The purpose of the trip is for Mike&#8217;s Hard Lemonade to share all of its trade secrets with Yuengling. Yes, all of the recipes, all of the infrastructure, all [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/trade-secrets/">Trade Secrets</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Imagine this . . . Yuengling, America&#8217;s oldest brewery in the country (and based outside of Philly) is invited to visit Mike&#8217;s Hard Lemonade in Seattle. The purpose of the trip is for Mike&#8217;s Hard Lemonade to share all of its trade secrets with Yuengling. Yes, all of the recipes, all of the infrastructure, all of the processes. Yeah, right.</p>
<p>Today, Simon&#8217;s Fund and several other organizations attended a heart screening hosted by the Nick of Time Foundation (NOTF). The invite was extended so that many organizations could learn how to host heart screenings &#8211; organization, recruitment, medical teams, equipment, etc. NOTF laid the blueprint on the table.</p>
<p>What inspires this type of collaboration in the nonprofit space? This would never happen in the for profit space. It is because the goal of these nonprofits is similar &#8211; to make heart screenings the standard of care for children in this country. Our metrics are similar too &#8211; we want to screen as many kids as possible and use best practices in the process.</p>
<p>We are not competing (although it is hard to fundraise). We are not in it for the money. We are not concerned with market share. Our profits are lives saved and we know that we can accomplish more together.</p>
<p>The Nick of Time Foundation did an amazing thing today. Sure, it checked about 200 hearts at the screening and probably found two students with heart conditions. But more importantly, it gave other organizations a game plan and the confidence to go home and to do heart screenings themselves. That&#8217;s where the real impact happens. That&#8217;s how we scale. That&#8217;s how we check more hearts and save more lives.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/trade-secrets/">Trade Secrets</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Great Nonprofits at Work on Sudden Cardiac Arrest</title>
		<link>/blog/great-nonprofits-at-work-on-sudden-cardiac-arrest/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2012 00:46:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Nonprofits]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3479</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>It was started in honor of Pleasanton resident Michael Gable, who suddenly died in 2009 at the age of 38, killed by a heart disease he didn&#8217;t even know he had. Pleasanton wife and mother Michelle Gable was still reeling from the sudden death of her husband Michael from cardiac arrest on Sept. 17, 2009, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/great-nonprofits-at-work-on-sudden-cardiac-arrest/">Great Nonprofits at Work on Sudden Cardiac Arrest</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It was started in honor of Pleasanton resident Michael Gable, who suddenly died in 2009 at the age of 38, killed by a heart disease he didn&#8217;t even know he had.</p>
<p>Pleasanton wife and mother Michelle Gable was still reeling from the sudden death of her husband Michael from cardiac arrest on Sept. 17, 2009, when she noticed two weeks later that her baby daughter Grace&#8217;s cough was worsening and took her to the emergency room. Doctors discovered that Grace was suffering from an enlarged heart, a potentially life-threatening situation.</p>
<p>Little Grace spent her first birthday fighting for her life in the intensive care unit, where she stayed for one month, and was subsequently diagnosed with dilated cardiomyopathy, or DCM. Her father Michael had died of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, or HCM.</p>
<p>&#8220;When she was admitted to ICU back in October 2009, she was in complete heart failure,&#8221; Michelle said. &#8220;She has made a remarkable recovery, a true miracle in my book. For the past year and a half, she has been stable at an 85% heart working capacity.&#8221;</p>
<p>Grace is now 3, and her brother Matteo will be 6 in March. In response to these traumas, Michelle Gable and her friend Amy Mayo founded Gable Heart Beats Foundation to raise awareness of the heart disease. Their husbands were both in the San Francisco-based band, Segue, with Michael the singer and Stefan Mayo the guitarist and harmonica player.</p>
<p>&#8220;My husband Stefan wrote all the songs with Michael,&#8221; Amy Mayo said. &#8220;The band was pretty devastated.<br />
&#8220;Michelle tried to cope with Grace, and I had the idea, let&#8217;s start a foundation. We knew Michael would want to save lives. And we wanted to honor him.&#8221; HCM, an excessive thickening of the heart muscle, is the No. 1 cause of sudden cardiac arrests in young athletes, said Mayo, and it also affects one out of 100,000 children.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.pleasantonweekly.com/news/show_story.php?id=8690">Full story</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/great-nonprofits-at-work-on-sudden-cardiac-arrest/">Great Nonprofits at Work on Sudden Cardiac Arrest</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
