<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>ecg Archives -</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/tag/ecg/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Protecting Hearts and Saving Lives</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 May 2019 17:06:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/simons-fav-icon1.png</url>
	<title>ecg Archives -</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>What is a Standard of Care?</title>
		<link>/blog/screening-show-us-your/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2019 11:28:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[heart]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mammogram]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8832</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the past century, we’ve seen extraordinary advances in medicine and technology. The ways we detect, diagnose, and treat disease have changed the course of humankind. Among these changes is the method by which we screen for disease in a seemingly healthy population. It’s called preventative medicine. There is a wide variety of routine screenings [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/screening-show-us-your/">What is a Standard of Care?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the past century, we’ve seen extraordinary advances in medicine and technology. The ways we detect, diagnose, and treat disease have changed the course of humankind. Among these changes is the method by which we screen for disease in a seemingly healthy population. It’s called preventative medicine.</p>
<p>There is a wide variety of routine screenings to help detect and reduce the risk of disease. They are based on factors like age, sex, and family history. Some of the most common are mammograms, colonoscopy, Pap smear, PSA (prostate cancer), and blood glucose. At birth, we screen for genetic disorders and in schools we assess vision and hearing. Today, these tests are routine – part of our standard of care. However, at their inception, their effectiveness and utility were called into question.</p>
<p>The road to standardization was full of research. There were false positives, false negatives, bad techniques and large sums of money spent. However, the results proved the benefits of early detection and intervention. The process is pretty typical when purusing a new standard of care. Costs and mistakes are high in the beginning as we seek to define and understand the unknown. Over time, as our experience and exposure increases, the costs and mistakes subside. We settle into an affordable and effective outcome.</p>
<p>The United States Army was one of the first to implement health screenings (1940). It utlitized mental health screenings in the application process. A standardized pencil and paper test identified at risk men seeking military service. This initiative established the criteria for developing and vetting screening programs.</p>
<p>Screening programs would need to answer the following questions: (1) Does early treatment improve prognosis; (2) how valid and repeatable is the screening test; and (3) among those with a positive screening, how many of them are true cases? And, there would need to be an effective way to treat the disease. Screenings needed to prove their specificity and sensitivity. Be <u>sensitive</u> enough to detect the condition almost every time, and <u>specific</u> enough to find the condition being sought.</p>
<p>The first breast cancer screening emerged in the 1930s. Dr. Stafford Warren used direct radiographic exposure. This method was successful in identifying malignant and benign breast cancer that were found during an exam, but the technique was not very successful when seeking out less advanced breast cancers that were not detectable during an exam. This was a major flaw. Hence, research and evolution.</p>
<p>Contrast injections were next. This technique improved the outcomes but they caused inflammation, and the images were not clear. Thirty years later, radiologists Gershen-Cohen and Egan discovered a low-contrast technique that could detect unsuspected cancers not discovered during the examination. This became the first reproducible technique for breast cancer screening, but it didn’t stop there. Advancements like film-screen mammography and digital mammography continued to improve the safety, accuracy and outcomes.</p>
<p>Our ability to detect and treat breast cancer has evolved. We experimented using the best, yet flawed, methods known at the time. We learned from our failures to arrive where we are today. This progression took nearly 70 years. We saw countless clinical trials, huge sums of money spent, bad side effects and lots of mistakes.</p>
<p>Critics of early breast cancer screenings questioned whether screenings could change the course of the disease a manner significant enough to warrant the poking, proding and spending. There was no real evidence that an individual&#8217;s life would be improved. There was no data showing that the quality and design of the screening had an acceptable sensitivity and specificity to improve outcomes. We did not know how breast cancer looked in different populations. One doctor even proclaimed, “if I can’t feel it on examination, it’s not there.”</p>
<p>As clinical data emerged, these concerns waned. Through trial and error, we simply got smarter. Incidence and mortality rates declined, vital statistics improved, and people shared testimonials of how screening changed their life’s trajectory.</p>
<p>What would life be like today if the critics prevailed? How many friends or family members would you have lost to breast cancer? Would feeling for lumps been sufficient or did they benefit from some improved method of detection?</p>
<p>Medicine is interesting. Every disease and condition requires a unique treatment. Actually, each patient may require a unique treatment. Despite this, the path to discovering treatments is very similar. Idea. Try it out on lots of people. Analyze the results. Repeat. It’s expensive in the beginning. Mistakes are made while we learn. Hopefully, it gets cheaper and more effective.</p>
<p>Sudden Cardiac Arrest is the leading cause of death of adults in the United States. However, it is not just an adult thing. It is the #1 cause of death of student athletes and takes the lives of thousands of children every year. Today, the standard of care is the equivalent of “it’s not there unless I can feel it.” Parents answer a few questions about heart conditions in the family, and a doctor listens to the child’s heart. So, it’s more like “it’s not there unless I can hear it”</p>
<p>Heart screenings using electrocardiograms (ECG) and echocardiograms (echo) have been shown to improve our ability to detect abnormalities. In an evaluation of NCAA student athletes, 72% of heart conditions were found only after the use of the ECG. They were missed by feeling and listening. Additionally, the false positive rate (someone thinks you have a problem only to find out you do not) are quite low at 3.4 percent.</p>
<p>In 1930, in an effort to save lives, we accepted injections of highly toxic materials in the bodies of our mothers and sisters. That was the beginning of a long and uncertain road that has saved countless lives. Today, critics of heart screenings are not willing to accept the placement of stickers or a little gel on a student’s chest. It is too expensive. We don’t know what heart conditions look like in different pediatric popluations. We don’t know if detecting conditions will save lives. Sound familiar?</p>
<p>There is only one path forward. Idea. Try it out on lots of people. Analyze the results. Repeat. It’s expensive in the beginning. Mistakes are made while we learn. We get smarter. Fortunately, the research and future look promising.</p>
<p>A special thanks to our research fellow, Chris Koilor, for educating us about the history of screenings.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/screening-show-us-your/">What is a Standard of Care?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Doris Toran Goldman</title>
		<link>/blog/doris-torin-goldman/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2009 20:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cardiac arrhythmia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Doris Toran Goldman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[echo]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Long QT Syndrome]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Philadelphia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[screening]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/blog/?p=29</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>There are so many things that I encounter in life that are easier because of the actions that others took before me.  I&#8217;ll never say that losing a son was easy, or made easier, by anyone&#8217;s conduct, but it is clear that the mission of Simon&#8217;s Fund was forged decades ago by Doris Toran Goldman. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/doris-torin-goldman/">Doris Toran Goldman</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There are so many things that I encounter in life that are easier because of the actions that others took before me.  I&#8217;ll never say that losing a son was easy, or made easier, by anyone&#8217;s conduct, but it is clear that the mission of Simon&#8217;s Fund was forged decades ago by Doris Toran Goldman.</p>
<p>If it were not for Doris&#8217; actions, the world may not have known about Long QT Syndrome.  We would not have known  the cause of Simon&#8217;s death, or how to treat the health condition shared by Phyllis.  We may not appreciate the importance of heart screenings for our children.  The organization C.A.R.E (www.longqt.org) would not exist.  The list goes on.</p>
<p>I got to speak to Doris a couple of years ago.  I wanted to hear from the expert about what we should be doing.  She was focused, passionate and spunky.  We know that there is still so much to be done to raise awareness about conditions that lead to sudden cardiac arrest and death in children.  However, we want to thank Doris for clearing the brush and paving the road.  It is an honor to continue what she started.</p>
<p>Here is her brief story &#8211;</p>
<p>Doris Toran Goldman, 77, was born and raised in Philadelphia, PA, and lived in Laguna Wood, CA.  She passed away on July 29 from lung cancer.</p>
<p>What could be worse than the sudden, unexpected and unexplained death of one of your children? Especially if that 20 year old son looked as healthy and handsome as Jack did on his last day of backpacking in Grand Teton National Park, Wyoming. And yet, it was to be his final day. Just hours after climbing comfortably into his sleeping bag, he died in his sleep with no apparent medical explanation for his death.</p>
<p>The only thing worse would be to have this happen again &#8211; and it did! This time, it was my youngest child, 29 year old Sharon, relishing her new marriage and happily loving her new role as a mother.</p>
<p>But she too died in her sleep, leaving behind a distraught husband and a now &#8220;motherless&#8221; five month old son. My son Jack and daughter Sharon were in their 20&#8217;s and living life to the fullest, when their lives were abruptly snatched away. Refusing to accept the fact that the medical community seemed to offer no absolute answers, my surviving daughter Nancy and 1, together with Dr. William Mandel, began an investigation in a desperate attempt to finally resolve this mystery. We did family trees of all four family lines and asked everyone to send cardiograms to Dr. Mandel.</p>
<p>Most of our relatives complied, and a pattern soon began to emerge.</p>
<p>It was apparent that many members of my maternal line had the Long QT syndrome, including Nancy, and Sharon&#8217;s infant son &#8211; and that I was the carrier. If only some doctor had asked to see my cardiogram while Sharon was alive, they would have seen that I clearly have the Long QT Syndrome, as do 21 members of my family. Those considered &#8220;at risk&#8221; are taking medication that is highly effective in preventing a lethal incident.</p>
<p>What Nancy and I learned was that when nothing shows on autopsy, the cause of death might be determined from the living &#8211; if the cause is genetic. If this could happen to us, how many more people were out there who had lost a child and did not have a clue as to the cause of their death?</p>
<p>Perhaps they could follow our lead, and with routine screening of surviving family members, actually determine the cause of death &#8211; saving the lives of other family members.</p>
<p>Nancy and I then embarked on a nationwide campaign several years ago to make the public aware of a disorder about which most people had never heard. This outreach resulted in thousands of calls coming into a hot line, and many callers or their relatives were ultimately diagnosed with LQTS and other heart rhythm disorders, saving many lives.</p>
<p>An historic scientific breakthrough occurred in March 1995 when Dr. Mark Keating of the Howard Hughes Medical Institute at the University of Utah called to tell me that he had just discovered two genes that cause Long QT syndrome. This discovery actually shed light on the workings of the electrical activity of the heart, and is expected to impact other potentially lethal arrhythmias. And then in January 1996, a third gene for LQTS was also identified. The scientists are working with incredible speed &#8211; and they need our support NOW! Their immediate goal is to develop a simple blood test &#8211; and a cure.</p>
<p>These discoveries were the impetus that led to the formation of Cardiac Arrhythmias Research and Education Foundation, Inc. in April 1995.</p>
<p>This came too late to save Jack and Sharon, but the lives of many more innocent children and young adults will be saved through our efforts. For additional information, you can call me at the C.A.R.E. Foundation office at (800) 404-9500.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/doris-torin-goldman/">Doris Toran Goldman</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
