<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Uncategorized Archives - GotAED.org</title>
	<atom:link href="/product-category/uncategorized/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2023 09:16:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>AED&#8217;s for Kids Sports</title>
		<link>/product/aeds-for-kids-sports/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[danikdemers@gmail.com]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 18:22:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/aeds-for-kids-sports/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>5 years ago my husband went down while reffing a Collegiate soccer game with a heart attack. Thankfully the right people were present with the right care that he is still here today. We spend the majority of our time on the Soccer Pitch where no AED's are present. I am a huge advocate for [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/aeds-for-kids-sports/">AED&#8217;s for Kids Sports</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>5 years ago my husband went down while reffing a Collegiate soccer game with a heart attack. Thankfully the right people were present with the right care that he is still here today.  We spend the majority of our time on the Soccer Pitch where no AED&#8217;s are present. I am a huge advocate for getting AED&#8217;s into every place we can because they SAVE LIVES.  With 100&#8217;s of kids on the soccer pitch&#8217;s on any given night, we need an AED at these locations in case one is ever needed.  I&#8217;d rather have one there that never gets used, than not have one when one is needed. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/aeds-for-kids-sports/">AED&#8217;s for Kids Sports</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Boys &#038; Girls Clubs of Delaware</title>
		<link>/product/boys-girls-clubs-of-delaware/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Got AED Admin account]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Jul 2023 09:56:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/boys-girls-clubs-of-delaware/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>For over 90 years, our clubs have provided a safe place for youth to learn, grow, and interact with their peers. Boys &amp; Girls Clubs of Delaware have impacted thousands of lives across Delaware, providing a place in the community where kids can go for recreation, companionship, and growth opportunities. Boys &amp; Girls Clubs of [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/boys-girls-clubs-of-delaware/">Boys &#038; Girls Clubs of Delaware</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For over 90 years, our clubs have provided a safe place for youth to learn, grow, and interact with their peers. Boys &amp; Girls Clubs of Delaware have impacted thousands of lives across Delaware, providing a place in the community where kids can go for recreation, companionship, and growth opportunities. Boys &amp; Girls Clubs of Delaware provide safe havens for youth with programming and mentorships that facilitate growth. Our 42 locations teach foundational life skills, like conflict resolution and character development, within nurturing environments that improve decision-making skills</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/boys-girls-clubs-of-delaware/">Boys &#038; Girls Clubs of Delaware</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Elk Lake AED Campaign</title>
		<link>/product/elk-lake-aed-campaign/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caleb Datto]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2023 19:59:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/elk-lake-aed-campaign/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>My name is Caleb Datto. I am the son of Cece McGovern and grandson of Paul and Cecelia McGovern on the West Shore of Elk Lake in Waymart, PA. I am also a rising sophomore at Saint Joseph’s University in Philadelphia. When I was five years old, I was diagnosed with a cardiac arrhythmia that [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/elk-lake-aed-campaign/">Elk Lake AED Campaign</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My name is Caleb Datto. I am the son of Cece McGovern and grandson of Paul and Cecelia McGovern on the West Shore of Elk Lake in Waymart, PA. I am also a rising sophomore at Saint Joseph’s University in Philadelphia. </p>
<p>When I was five years old, I was diagnosed with a cardiac arrhythmia that put me at high risk of Sudden Cardiac Arrest (SCA). I was lucky to stumble upon my condition, but many don’t realize that they have underlying conditions until it is too late. </p>
<p>For the past five years, I have worked with a non-profit called Simon’s Heart to fundraise for free youth heart screenings, educate on CPR, and to place AEDs (automated external defibrillators) in schools and athletic facilities. Anyone can collapse from sudden cardiac arrest, and it is best that we as a community are prepared in case of an emergency. This crowdfunding site, GotAED, is a Simon’s Heart project. All donations will go toward the AED to benefit our Elk Lake community. </p>
<p>If an AED is used within the first minute of a cardiac arrest occurrence, the survival rate for victims can be as high as 90%. For every minute that defibrillation is delayed, however, the chance of survival decreases by 10% (American Heart Association). The Wayne County, PA average EMS response time is 15 minutes (PA Department of Health). Being ten miles away from the nearest hospital and having a community with young children, this AED is a necessity. </p>
<p>Once funded, I will be the site coordinator of the AED, which will be stored at the Community Pavilion on the West Shore. In case of an emergency, come to the pavilion by foot, golf cart, car, or boat. I recognize the need for more AEDs around the lake, but this location, as a public space, is an easy starting place that can still benefit Elk Lakers from every shore. </p>
<p>I will also have a CPR and AED demo for any Elk Lakers interested in learning the proper Chain of Survival. </p>
<p>Donate Here: ​​https://shorturl.at/isMWX</p>
<p>Nota bene</p>
<p>AEDs cannot be stored at temperatures less than 32°F. Due to accessibility laws around AEDs, it must be stored in a location that is public and accessible to all (not in a locked building). Therefore, the AED will be stored off-site from mid-October through mid-April annually.</p>
<p>42 PA CSA § 8331-8338  THE GOOD SAMARITAN AND RELATED ACTS<br />
Provides complete protection of individuals who try to assist during a medical emergency from civil and criminal charges. Any questions can be directed toward info@simonsheart.org</p>
<p>AEDs are designed to be used by nonmedically-trained personnel. It is impossible to deliver a shock to an individual who is not in need thanks to EKG analyzing technology (Stanford Medicine). AEDs provide step by step usage instructions. Anyone can save a life. </p>
<p>Sources</p>
<p>Elk Lake GotAED Campaign https://shorturl.at/isMWX</p>
<p>American Heart Association https://shorturl.at/vxHT8</p>
<p>Pennsylvania Department of Health https://shorturl.at/gyE37</p>
<p>42 PA CSA § 8331-8338 https://shorturl.at/fE012<br />
Stanford Medicine https://shorturl.at/eryR3  </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/elk-lake-aed-campaign/">Elk Lake AED Campaign</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>North Judson Youth League AED Help</title>
		<link>/product/north-judson-youth-league-aed-help/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alexis Simchak]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 17:43:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/north-judson-youth-league-aed-help/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hello my name is Tristan Frazier I am a local volunteer firefighter soon to be a full time firefighter/EMT as well, my wife is a member of the league's board, and our son is a student who plays football for the league. Due to recent events in the NFL where an athlete had a sudden [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/north-judson-youth-league-aed-help/">North Judson Youth League AED Help</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hello my name is Tristan Frazier I am a local volunteer firefighter soon to be a full time firefighter/EMT as well, my wife is a member of the league&#8217;s board, and our son is a student who plays football for the league. Due to recent events in the NFL where an athlete had a sudden cardiac arrest in the middle of the field, the youth league is seeking assistance to get two AEDs &#8211; (One to be stationed at the field in an outdoor cabinet, and one in a backpack that can be taken to other fields and away games).</p>
<p>If a adult athlete who is healthy as can be can have this happen than it can happen to our kids. I will be at every event personally and I will use it to keep our kids safe if the need arises. Let’s keep our kids safe.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/north-judson-youth-league-aed-help/">North Judson Youth League AED Help</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Courage to save an athlete&#8217;s heart</title>
		<link>/product/courage-to-save-an-athletes-heart/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meg Thompson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 20:01:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/courage-to-save-an-athletes-heart-2/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>It could be your athlete or family member at a middle school game that needs an AED to save their life. I am the Head Athletic Trainer at Lake Norman High School and I’m advocating to get AEDs specifically for our middle school athletic departments. Eight out of the 9 middle school do not have [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/courage-to-save-an-athletes-heart/">Courage to save an athlete&#8217;s heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It could be your athlete or family member at a middle school game that needs an AED to save their life. I am the Head Athletic Trainer at Lake Norman High School and I’m advocating to get AEDs specifically for our middle school athletic departments. Eight out of the 9 middle school do not have this necessary life-saving tool. Access to an AED at any given time is critical to the safety of student athletes, and sometimes proves to be a moving target or secured behind a locked door. We have 2090 student athletes at our 9 middle school campuses and with the obstacles coaches face it leaves so many events without an AED within 2-3 mins of a SCA. This is not acceptable for our student athletes.</p>
<p>All Iredell-Statesville Schools campuses also host several community events like youth league athletics, local churches, FCA events, and more. When there are multiple events occurring on the same day, our school system currently has the 1 school AED to be prioritized to the venue in this order: Football, Basketball, Track, Soccer, Cross Country, Baseball, Wrestling, Tennis, Softball, and Volleyball ((based on info from National Center for Catastrophic Injury – UNC-Chapel-Hill). Six of these sports are all in the spring season and not always on the same property.</p>
<p>It is vital that we do better for our student athletes and our community. Your consideration for this grant is greatly appreciated, and together we will resolve this nationwide threat of SCA in our schools.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/courage-to-save-an-athletes-heart/">Courage to save an athlete&#8217;s heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mesa Lacrosse</title>
		<link>/product/mesa-lacrosse/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mesa Lacrosse]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 15:35:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/mesa-lacrosse-2/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Mesa is a youth and high school lacrosse club. It has handled kids needing emergency care and is working to have resources that kids need to be healthy and stay healthy. We have already fulfilled our goal of obtaining one AED and are fundraising for two more devices as we have teams in multiple locations [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/mesa-lacrosse/">Mesa Lacrosse</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mesa is a youth and high school lacrosse club. It has handled kids needing emergency care and is working to have resources that kids need to be healthy and stay healthy. We have already fulfilled our goal of obtaining one AED and are fundraising for two more devices as we have teams in multiple locations at one time. Thank you so much for the support!</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/mesa-lacrosse/">Mesa Lacrosse</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Guam Department of Guam</title>
		<link>/product/guam-department-of-guam/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[banwarq@gmail.com]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 00:02:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/guam-department-of-guam/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I am one of the school nurses for the Dept of Education on the island of Guam which serves over 25,0000 students, and 2800 employees we have over 40 schools in our Dept of Education and none of our schools have an AED. Our school children deserve to have a life-saving device in case of [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/guam-department-of-guam/">Guam Department of Guam</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am one of the school nurses for the Dept of Education on the island of Guam which serves over 25,0000 students, and 2800 employees we have over 40 schools in our Dept of Education and none of our schools have an AED. Our school children deserve to have a life-saving device in case of an emergency. It&#8217;s our duty to ensure that students get the best care and to provide a life-saving device when an emergency happens.<br />
The goal of this campaign is to ensure that each school has an AED in its respective schools.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/guam-department-of-guam/">Guam Department of Guam</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Buffalo Collegiate Charter School AED Donation</title>
		<link>/product/buffalo-collegiate-charter-school-aed-donation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[egiglia@buffalocollegiate.org]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 18:55:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/buffalo-collegiate-charter-school-aed-donation/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We are a charter school in Buffalo, NY that serves children and families grades 4-8. We are a 501(c)3 organization. We opened our doors in 2018, and were quickly closed again for almost 2 years due to the pandemic. We hired our first full-time nurse in the 21-22 school year, and we have since established [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/buffalo-collegiate-charter-school-aed-donation/">Buffalo Collegiate Charter School AED Donation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We are a charter school in Buffalo, NY that serves children and families grades 4-8. We are a 501(c)3 organization. We opened our doors in 2018, and were quickly closed again for almost 2 years due to the pandemic. We hired our first full-time nurse in the 21-22 school year, and we have since established a full-time Medical Emergency Team as of this school year, all members of which are First Aid, CPR, and AED certified.</p>
<p>What we really need is an additional AED to keep on our second and third floors so that we are able to quickly respond to an emergency medical need within 3 minutes or less, as per the American Heart Association recommendations. Our goal is to keep our children and staff safe and to provide an environment where our students have access to immediate intervention and potentially life-saving care.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/buffalo-collegiate-charter-school-aed-donation/">Buffalo Collegiate Charter School AED Donation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Have a heart</title>
		<link>/product/have-a-heart/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lizzet.perez@choosepace.org]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2022 19:49:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/have-a-heart/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>My name is Lizzet Perez. I am a new school nurse, but I have been a surgical nurse for 28 years. I was invited to be the school nurse at Pace Academy, this school has only been up and running for 1 year. I was to be retired, however I could not decline since the [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/have-a-heart/">Have a heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My name is Lizzet Perez. I am a new school nurse, but I have been a surgical nurse for 28 years. I was invited to be the school nurse at Pace Academy, this school has only been up and running for 1 year. I was to be retired, however I could not decline since the need was urgent. The school nurse that was present was only there for the year and has resigned.<br />
My son attends this specialized charter school for Dyslexia, ADHD, and autism. This school was founded by a mother who was frustrated with the public school system. How could I decline? She is now responsible for running an entire school. I just knew I had to step in and help.  I have experienced first hand the cardiac arrest of a school teacher after a school trip. It was traumatizing not having equipment on hand to help.<br />
Please consider a donation for this amazing school. This will allow funding /donations to go to other areas for education. Thank you</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/have-a-heart/">Have a heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>An AED for the Boys &#038; Girls Club of Mount Vernon, NY</title>
		<link>/product/bgcmvny-aed/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elopez@bgcmvny.org]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 19:54:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/bgcmvny-aed/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>My name is Edwin Lopez. I'm the Director of Safety and Security of the Boys and Girls Club of Mount Vernon, New York. We are required to have an AED in the facility in case of an emergency. Getting an AED has become costly and challenging. So with said we would appreciate the assistance. Thank [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/bgcmvny-aed/">An AED for the Boys &#038; Girls Club of Mount Vernon, NY</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My name is Edwin Lopez. I&#8217;m the Director of Safety and Security of the Boys and Girls Club of Mount Vernon, New York.</p>
<p>We are required to have an AED in the facility in case of an emergency. Getting an AED has become costly and challenging.</p>
<p>So with said we would appreciate the assistance.</p>
<p>Thank you,</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/bgcmvny-aed/">An AED for the Boys &#038; Girls Club of Mount Vernon, NY</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
