<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Medical Archives -</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/medical/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Protecting Hearts and Saving Lives</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2021 14:40:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/simons-fav-icon1.png</url>
	<title>Medical Archives -</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Covid-19 and the Heart</title>
		<link>/blog/covid-19-and-the-heart/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jenn Parrado]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2021 14:39:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Medical]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9795</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic is due to a severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and was first reported in late 2019. This virus has had a massive global impact resulting in the deaths of millions of people. COVID-19 has a broad range of clinical presentations from completely asymptomatic to affecting every organ system [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/covid-19-and-the-heart/">Covid-19 and the Heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic is due to a severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and was first reported in late 2019. This virus has had a massive global impact resulting in the deaths of millions of people. COVID-19 has a broad range of clinical presentations from completely asymptomatic to affecting every organ system of the body.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Based on data collected during the pandemic, we know that individuals with cardiovascular disease are at increased risk of death or severe illness from COVID-19. The virus is dangerous not only to those with preexisting heart disease, but to those with no preexisting medical conditions at all.</span></p>
<h2><b>COVID-19 can damage the heart muscle in many ways</b></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The virus can either directly damage the heart itself, or it can cause secondary damage due to the inflammatory response caused by the virus affecting other organs in the body. Generally, this secondary damage to the heart is due to increased demands on the heart combined with limited oxygen availability to the heart. In order for the heart to pump blood effectively, it needs to be supplied with enough oxygen.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When the heart is not supplied with the amount of oxygen it needs to perform the work that is required of it, damage to the heart muscle occurs. This oxygen supply and demand mismatch is what leads to the various types of heart attacks.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Additionally, damage can result from inflammation in the heart due to an inappropriate immune system response to the infection. It has become increasingly clear that this inflammatory immune response to the infection is responsible for some of the devastating consequences of the COVID-19 infection.</span></p>
<h2><strong>What tests can be used to detect heart muscle damage?</strong></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There have been many studies looking at blood tests and imaging studies to detect damage to the heart caused by COVID-19. Though the field of evidence is still growing, it is well known that individuals who become severely ill with COVID-19, or who have to be hospitalized, are at a relatively high risk of having damage to the heart.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blood levels of troponin, a heart muscle enzyme, can be used to detect damage to the heart muscle. In addition to blood test, ultrasound imaging of the heart or computed tomography or magnetic resonance imaging of the heart can be used to detect the inflammation or damage caused by the infection.</span></p>
<h2><b>How does a virus affect the heart?</b></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are multiple possible ways that viral infections such as influenza or COVID-19 can affect the heart. One of the most common forms of heart muscle damage from viral infections is myocarditis, or inflammation of the heart muscle. This has been well described in individuals who have viral infections such as COVID-19 and the symptoms that occur are variable.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Some individuals are asymptomatic, while others become severely ill and require hospitalization. In addition to direct viral infection and damage to the heart, cardiac damage from COVID-19 and other viral infections can be due to the systemic inflammation that often occurs.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Specifically for COVID-19, based on the risk of heart muscle damage from symptomatic infection, it has been recommended that those individuals who develop severe symptoms such as chest pain or shortness of breath be evaluated for cardiac risk stratification to determine whether any damage has occurred, and to ensure that it is safe to resume regular activity.</span></p>
<h2><b>What symptoms might I have if COVID-19 has affected my heart?</b></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Symptoms can range in severity from none at all to severe chest pain and shortness of breath. For individuals who are having shortness of breath, chest pain, or signs of low oxygen levels, it is important to seek medical attention so a physician can provide supportive care and determine if additional therapies are needed.</span></p>
<h2><strong>When should I see a doctor to make sure my heart is healthy after COVID-19, and when can I return to exercise?</strong></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You should see a doctor for a cardiac evaluation if you had moderate to severe COVID-19, are age 65 or older, or experienced any cardiovascular symptoms. It recommended that individuals quarantine for a 10-day period after initial diagnosis of infection.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For athletes, even if asymptomatic, it is recommended to abstain from exercise for 10 days before gradual supervised resumption.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For those who had moderate to severe symptoms, those with pre-existing cardiovascular conditions, those with prolonged symptoms (&gt;10 days), and those older than 65, it is reasonable to undergo cardiovascular risk stratification to ensure it is safe to resume exercise.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If cardiac involvement is diagnosed during the post COVID-19 infection period, then return to physical activity should be delayed until determined to be safe from a physician.</span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/covid-19-and-the-heart/">Covid-19 and the Heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>We Need To Be Prepared</title>
		<link>/blog/we-need-to-be-prepared/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 14:32:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[aed-donations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Student Athlete Collapse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sudden Cardiac Death]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AED]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AED awareness week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cleveland Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cpr awareness week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[defibrillator]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Samantha Krouse]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8827</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Dermot Phelan MD, Ph.D., FESC, FASE, FACC a staff cardiologist from the Cleveland Clinic interviews Samantha Krouse, Manager of GotAED about sudden cardiac arrest, the importance of early defibrillation and resources to get AED devices. Dr. Phelan: The sudden cardiac death of a young athlete or pupil has a profound effect on the community [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/we-need-to-be-prepared/">We Need To Be Prepared</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>Dr. Dermot Phelan MD, Ph.D., FESC, FASE, FACC a staff cardiologist from the Cleveland Clinic interviews Samantha Krouse, Manager of GotAED about sudden cardiac arrest, the importance of early defibrillation and resources to get AED devices.</h4>
<p><strong>Dr. Phelan:</strong> The sudden cardiac death of a young athlete or pupil has a profound effect on the community at large. It often leaves people asking what more could have been done to prevent this tragic event. Could you describe the scope of this problem and what are the most common underlying causes of sudden cardiac death in the young?</p>
<p><strong>Samantha:</strong> We believe that thousands of children die every year from sudden cardiac arrest.&nbsp; Unfortunately, we don’t know for sure because our medical community didn’t start tracking the causes of death of minors until recently.&nbsp; The NIH and CDC created the <a href="https://www.nih.gov/news-events/news-releases/nih-cdc-launch-registry-sudden-death-young">sudden death registry</a> and it is being piloted in a handful of states. For instance, when a student is found at the bottom of a pool, the death certificate will say drowning or asphyxiation. But, what caused this student to drown?&nbsp; It could have been an arrhythmia, which is undetectable once the heart stops beating. The same for babies who die of SIDS or young adults who die in single-car accidents when the weather is good and there is no evidence of alcohol or drugs.</p>
<p>We can prevent these tragedies in a few ways:</p>
<ol>
<li>We must know that sudden cardiac arrest is not just an adult thing.&nbsp; There are some warning signs for us to watch:&nbsp; fainting during or right after exercise, a racing heart and sudden death of a family member under the age of 50.</li>
<li>Our kids should get their hearts screened.&nbsp; Research shows that an ECG exam, when done with a physical and history, is more effective at detecting heart conditions.</li>
<li>We need to be prepared. We need to know how to do chest compressions and have an AED around.&nbsp; The AED is the only tool that can save someone in cardiac arrest.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Dr. Phelan:</strong> Could you please tell us about the importance of early effective CPR and early defibrillation on outcomes in these events?</p>
<p><strong>Samantha:</strong> CPR and early defibrillation are critical, but let’s remember that they are the backup plan.&nbsp; We need these tools because we failed to detect the condition before it causes harm. CPR or chest compressions circulate blood throughout the body when the heart stops pumping.&nbsp; Without blood and oxygen, our organs will quickly fail.</p>
<p>The AED delivers a lifesaving shock to our heart. It resets the rhythm. It is the only tool that can do this.&nbsp; If someone provides bystander CPR and the use of an AED device is used within 3-5 minutes of the collapse, the survival rates are between 41%-74% (<a href="https://ksi.uconn.edu/">Korey Stringer Institute</a>). If you aren’t able to use an AED device or the device is inaccessible, the survival rates decline 7-10% per minute, every minute that defibrillation is delayed. That is why the best practice to save lives during a cardiac arrest event is to start chest compressions within 1 minute of collapse and grab the defibrillator within 3 minutes of collapse.</p>
<p><strong>Dr. Phelan:</strong> How can we improve education on basic life support in our communities?</p>
<p><strong>Samantha:</strong> The first step to improving education is demystifying the process.&nbsp; For decades, the heart community has required hours of training, certifications, and fees. There are stickers on AED cabinets claiming that the devices are professional use only.&nbsp; The public is scared and intimidated &#8211; for good reason.&nbsp; This stuff is easy. It’s super important but so easy.&nbsp; All students should be taught how to perform CPR and how to use an AED device in school. There are 38 states that encourage CPR education before graduation.&nbsp; That’s a start.</p>
<p>There is also technology like the <a href="https://www.pulsepoint.org/">PulsePoint</a> app that alerts bystanders about cardiac arrests nearby so they can assist until the first responders arrive. Pulse Point also has an AED registry, so the devices are easier to find.</p>
<p><strong>Dr. Phelan:</strong> Where should AEDs be made available?</p>
<p><strong>Samantha:</strong> AED devices should be made available everywhere, including where kids learn and play. Think about all of the safety tools we have but rarely (or never) use &#8211; fire extinguisher, smoke detector, smoke alarm, and burglar alarm. These all add value and mitigate risk.&nbsp; So, does an AED device.&nbsp; Sudden cardiac arrest is the leading cause of death of adults in the US.&nbsp; The only tool that can prevent it should be everywhere.</p>
<p><strong>Dr. Phelan:</strong> How much does an AED cost?</p>
<p><strong>Samantha:</strong> AEDs range in value like every other appliance or tool. They can retail for $1,100 &#8211; $2,500. <a href="https://www.cardiopartners.com/">Cardio Partners</a> is our AED partner for crowdfunding site, <a href="https://www.gotaed.org/">GotAED</a>. We are able to provide devices at a lower cost because of the nature of our site.</p>
<p><strong>Dr. Phelan:</strong> Please tell us about the work that <a href="https://www.gotaed.org/">GotAED</a> does?</p>
<p><strong>Samantha:</strong> GotAED is an initiative of <a href="/">Simon’s Heart</a>, a nonprofit organization dedicated to raising awareness about the warning signs and conditions that lead to sudden cardiac arrest and death in kids. We created this site to empower places to get AEDs even when they don’t have the budget to do so. We heard too many stories about youth facilities that wanted an AED but gave up because they didn’t have the money.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.gotaed.org/">GotAED</a> allows youth related facilities to quickly set up a campaign and raise funds. It takes a few minutes to get started. The cost is the same for everyone &#8211; around $900 &#8211; depending on the way that you want to store the device (and your state’s sales tax).&nbsp; Once the campaign is fully funded, the device and storage container is delivered right to the door. We also partner with <a href="https://www.projectadam.com/ProjectADAM">ProjectADAM</a> to help create cardiac emergency response plans for the youth facility.</p>
<p>Within its first year, GotAED helped 30 different schools, youth organizations, libraries, community centers, sports clubs/associations, and museums get AED devices in over 18 states.</p>
<p>GotAED also launched an awareness campaign with the Philadelphia Flyers. It is called the <a href="https://www.nhl.com/flyers/news/flyers-make-first-gotaed-overtime-challenge-device-donation--philadelphia-flyers/c-298661578">Overtime Challenge</a>.&nbsp; Every time the game enters the sudden death period, an AED is donated to a local youth facility.&nbsp; Sudden death is an exciting way to win a game, but a terrible way to lose a teammate.</p>
<p><strong>Dr. Phelan:</strong> If someone in the community wishes to purchase an AED, where should they go to get information.</p>
<p><strong>Samantha:</strong> There are a few places that provide funding for AED grants. However, money is scarce.&nbsp; So, if funding is not available, visit <a href="https://www.gotaed.org/">GotAED.org</a> and click the red button to “<a href="https://www.gotaed.org/add-campaign/">Start a Campaign</a>.”&nbsp; I am always available to answer questions &#8211;&nbsp;samantha@gotaed.org.</p>
<p>If you have funds, we recommend Cardio Partners.&nbsp; To receive a special discount, please enter the code SIMONSHEART2019 on <a href="https://www.aed.com/">AED.com</a> to get 20% off your total purchase.&nbsp; For more information, please contact Frank Mannino at francesco.mannino@cardiopartners.com.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>Dermot Phelan, MD, Ph.D., FESC, FASE, FACC</strong> is a staff cardiologist in the section of Cardiovascular Imaging in the <a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/departments/heart/depts/cardiovascular-medicine">Robert and Suzanne Tomsich Department of Cardiovascular Medicine,</a> and Medical Director of the <a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/departments/heart/depts/sports-cardiology-center">Sports Cardiology Center</a> in the Sydell and Arnold Miller Family Heart & Vascular Institute at <a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/">Cleveland Clinic</a>. He is an Assistant Professor at the<br />
<a href="https://case.edu/medicine/">Cleveland Clinic Lerner College of Medicine</a> of Case Western Reserve University. As Medical Director of the Sports Cardiology Center, Dr. Phelan is actively involved in the care of athletes of all levels. He has a national and international reputation as a passionate advocate for the promotion and protection of the cardiac health of athletes.</p>
<p><strong>Samantha Krouse</strong>, 24, is the Manager of Programs and Initiatives at Simon’s Heart, an organization dedicated to raising awareness about the warning signs and conditions that lead to sudden cardiac arrest and death in kids. By providing free heart screenings, advocating for legislation to protect student-athletes, promoting research through its national cardiac registry of seemingly healthy kids, distributing AED devices through its crowd-funding site, and raising awareness with strategic partnerships and cause marketing programs, Simon’s Heart is protecting hearts and saving lives. Samantha manages GotAED placing over 50 AED devices across the country, runs GotAED Overtime Challenge with the Philadelphia Flyers, launched a scholarship program for high school students with Montgomery County and PulsePoint to improve the county registry of AED locations, and directs AED Madness working with NCAA basketball teams to educate fans about cardiac arrest. Samantha was also honored as the recipient, on behalf of Simon’s Heart, for the <a href="https://www.nba.com/sixers/community/gamechanger">Game Changer Award at the Philadelphia 76ers</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/we-need-to-be-prepared/">We Need To Be Prepared</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Today, My Heart is in Michigan</title>
		<link>/blog/a-buckeyes-heart-is-in-michigan/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2014 18:38:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=5933</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I grew up in Ohio. I graduated from Ohio State. I met my wife there.  I love the Buckeyes.  However, today, as they hold the funeral service for Ryan Fischer, my heart is in Michigan.  Ryan was Grandville’s hockey team captain and he died from an enlarged heart on the eve of the state championship. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/a-buckeyes-heart-is-in-michigan/">Today, My Heart is in Michigan</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I grew up in Ohio. I graduated from Ohio State. I met my wife there.  I love the Buckeyes.  However, today, as they hold the funeral service for <a href="#http://www.mlive.com/sports/grand-rapids/index.ssf/2014/03/grandville_doesnt_win_for_ryan.html">Ryan Fischer</a>, my heart is in Michigan.  Ryan was Grandville’s hockey team captain and he died from an enlarged heart on the eve of the state championship.</p>
<p>Michigan is no stranger to losing students to heart conditions.  In 2013, it was track runner, <a href="http://www.mlive.com/news/detroit/index.ssf/2013/03/ferndale_high_school_student_m.html">Mario Campbell</a>.  In 2012, it was a <a href="http://foxnewsinsider.com/2012/06/06/kindergarten-student-collapses-and-dies-during-school-field-day">kindergartner</a> at Field Day.  In 2011, it was high school basketball standout, <a href="http://abcnews.go.com/Health/HeartDisease/high-school-basketball-star-dies-court/story?id=13055595">Wes Leonard</a>, who collapsed and died after making the winning shot.</p>
<p>Leonard’s death received a lot of media attention and Fischer’s is too.  That’s what happens when our most gifted athletes, our children, collapse and die for no apparent reason, from conditions that are detectable and treatable.</p>
<p>Following Wes’ death, this headline read, <a href="http://www.mlive.com/news/grand-rapids/index.ssf/2011/03/study_finds_student_athlete_su.html">“Study finds student athlete sudden cardiac deaths like Fennville star Wes Leonard are as rare a deaths from lightening.”</a>  The headline was based on a paper appearing in <i>Circulation</i>, an American Heart Association publication, and was titled <a href="http://circ.ahajournals.org/content/119/8/1085.full?sid=9eb114c9-d6b3-408f-8436-b9b2f110ce40"><i>Sudden Death in Young Competitive Athletes – Analysis of 1866 deaths in the United States, 1980 – 2006</i></a><i>.</i></p>
<p>According to a cursory Google search, at least four Michigan students have died from sudden cardiac arrest in the last two years.  It is probably more accurate to say that four deaths have been picked up by the media.  So, what is the real number?  How many children die from sudden cardiac arrest?</p>
<p>This lightning analogy appeared in <i>Circulation, </i>a publication of the American Heart Association in 2009.  The death count was rooted in the US National Registry on Sudden Death in Athletes, a creation of the Minneapolis Heart Institute Foundation.  This “registry” is based on LexisNexis, Burrelle’s Information Services, Internet searches, reports from various governmental agencies and independent organizations.</p>
<p>I am shocked (no pun intended) that this resource can be identified and accepted as a registry in the medical world.  The term registry connotes official, legitimate, scientific and comprehensive.  At best, these sources offer an unscientific and incomplete glimpse of the picture.  They are better suited for students completing research papers.  To use this “registry” as the basis to influence healthcare policy and debate a standard of care is misleading and reckless.</p>
<p>Case in point.  Nicholas Bennett, a student athlete from Ionia Middle School (also Michigan), died September 25, 2013.  At the time, <a href="http://www.legacy.com/obituaries/sentinel-standard/obituary.aspx?pid=167172945">his obituary</a> was the only record of his passing, and it did not reference sudden cardiac arrest.  It wasn’t until the passing of Ryan Fischer, six months later, that we learned more about Nicholas from <a href="http://fox17online.com/2014/03/08/father-remembers-son-who-died-of-an-enlarged-heart/#axzz2vXBPnlOw">this article</a>.  How many more Nicholases are not being counted?</p>
<p>This “registry” suggests that approximately 72 student athletes die nationwide every year.  So, how many student athletes are dying from lightning strikes?</p>
<p>According to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, <a href="http://www.lightningsafety.noaa.gov/stats/03-12_deaths_by_state.pdf">seven</a> people died from lightning in the State of Michigan between 2003 &#8211; 2012.  To put another way, 0.7 people died each year from lightning.  By the way, all seven were adults.</p>
<p>This debate isn’t about Michigan though.  It is about the United States and this number doesn’t take into account states like Florida and Texas that have many more lightning deaths.</p>
<p>The American Academy of Pediatrics estimates that <a href="http://www.aap.org/en-us/about-the-aap/aap-press-room/pages/Understanding-Pediatric-Sudden-Cardiac-Arrest.aspx">2,000 children</a> die in the U.S. every year from sudden cardiac arrest.  When extrapolated over a fifty-three year period, this number is 106,000.</p>
<p>During this same period (1959 – 2012), the NOAA recorded <a href="http://www.lightningsafety.noaa.gov/stats/59-12_State_Ltg._Fatality_Map-rates.pdf">4,002 deaths</a> from lightning strikes, and the overwhelming majority of the deaths were adults.</p>
<p>The conditions that cause our children to drop dead are detectable and treatable.  We have a cure . . . it’s called prevention.  While it is tragic to read about the deaths of Wes, Nicholas, Ryan and Mario, the real tragedy lies within a very well respected segment of the medical community that confuses and misguides the public about the incidents of sudden cardiac arrest and death in children.  If we can’t rely on them to help us define the scope of the problem, we’ll never solve the problem, and we’ll continue to bury children like Ryan.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/a-buckeyes-heart-is-in-michigan/">Today, My Heart is in Michigan</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Study Suggests Sudden Death Happens Off the Field</title>
		<link>/blog/study-suggests-sudden-death-happens-off-the-field/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2012 23:37:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Medical]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=4123</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This is an interesting conclusion. The best part is that they are spending time researching this issue.  Furthermore, if SCA occurs more frequently off the field, then it&#8217;s happening a lot, because it is also the #1 cause of death of student athletes. TORONTO &#8211; The stories are always shocking: A young, often super fit [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/study-suggests-sudden-death-happens-off-the-field/">Study Suggests Sudden Death Happens Off the Field</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is an interesting conclusion. The best part is that they are spending time researching this issue.  Furthermore, if SCA occurs more frequently off the field, then it&#8217;s happening a lot, because it is also the #1 cause of death of student athletes.</p>
<p>TORONTO &#8211; The stories are always shocking: A young, often super fit teenager or young adult drops like a stone during an athletic event, dead before they hit the ground.</p>
<p>The obvious incongruity of sudden cardiac death in an athlete perplexes the public and alarms parents of young sportsmen and sportswomen, who may see their own children in the lifeless bodies of the stricken.</p>
<p>A new Canadian study may relieve some of those concerns. It finds that the majority of sudden cardiac death cases don&#8217;t happen during exercise, at least in young adults.</p>
<p>In fact, the highly visible deaths of athletes — or the deaths averted because of rapid resuscitation, as in the cases of former NHL player Brett MacLean or Premier League footballer Fabrice Muamba earlier this year — are the exceptions. Most sudden cardiac deaths happen off the field of play, among people who are not exerting themselves.</p>
<p>Read more:</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/study-suggests-sudden-death-happens-off-the-field/">Study Suggests Sudden Death Happens Off the Field</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Science Proves the Need for Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act</title>
		<link>/blog/science-proves-the-need-for-sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2012 01:51:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3793</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Earlier this month, a study was published in the Journal of American Board of Family Medicine.  The study finds that 72% of all students that experienced sudden cardiac arrest exhibited symptoms.  This number is much higher than previously thought.  The study also confirms that many of the symptoms are ignored because of a lack of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/science-proves-the-need-for-sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/">Science Proves the Need for Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Earlier this month, a study was published in the Journal of American Board of Family Medicine.  The study finds that 72% of all students that experienced sudden cardiac arrest exhibited symptoms.  This number is much higher than previously thought.  The study also confirms that many of the symptoms are ignored because of a lack of awareness.</p>
<p>We knew that the Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act was good law.  Now there is science to back up our claim.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.jabfm.org/content/25/4/408.abstract?rss=1">Text of Study</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/science-proves-the-need-for-sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/">Science Proves the Need for Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Guidelines to Protect Student Athletes</title>
		<link>/blog/new-guidelines-to-protect-student-athletes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2012 12:14:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Medical]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3505</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>New guidelines outlining the causes and prevention of sudden death among athletes were released this week by the National Athletic Trainer’s Association (NATA) in the United States. “These guidelines were developed for any level of sports participation, and to truly help save a life,” NATA President Marjorie Albohm said in an association news release. “It [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/new-guidelines-to-protect-student-athletes/">New Guidelines to Protect Student Athletes</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>New guidelines outlining the causes and prevention of sudden death among athletes were released this week by the National Athletic Trainer’s Association (NATA) in the United States.</p>
<p>“These guidelines were developed for any level of sports participation, and to truly help save a life,” NATA President Marjorie Albohm said in an association news release. “It is also critical that a school, team or league’s medical professionals have an emergency action plan in place. In the event that an injury occurs, every minute counts when it comes to appropriate care and transport of the athlete.”</p>
<p>“While collegiate and professional teams have athletic trainers on staff to prevent and treat injuries, only 42 percent of high schools have access to our members,” Albohm noted. “Legislation is improving, though, with 35 states and Washington, D.C., having passed youth sports safety laws. And the NFL just mandated new guidelines requiring athletic trainers in booths during games to watch for hard hits and concussions.”</p>
<p>The new position statement includes many recommendations for preventing sudden death among athletes. Here are some of the highlights:</p>
<ul>
<li>An athlete’s chances of survival are much greater if there is an established, site-specific emergency plan.</li>
<li>Recognition of the type of problem is key to treatment. Sudden cardiac arrest should be suspected in any athlete who has collapsed and is unresponsive.</li>
<li>Public access to early defibrillation is critical. The time between when an athlete collapses and receives the first shock from an automated external defibrillator should be less than three to five minutes.</li>
<li>If a serious brain injury is suspected in an unresponsive athlete, medical staff must be prepared to transport the athlete to a health-care facility, while ensuring adequate ventilation and elevating the head to help decrease intracranial pressure.</li>
<li>In cases of suspected heatstroke, the athlete’s core temperature must be determined soon after collapse to ensure accurate and immediate assessment.</li>
<li>Ensure athletes with asthma are properly educated about their condition and how to recognize good or bad breathing days. A structured warm-up program may decrease their risk of an asthma attack or their reliance on asthma medications.</li>
</ul>
<p>The position statement appears in the February issue of the <em>Journal of Athletic Training</em>.</p>
<p><a href="http://news.health.com/2012/02/22/new-guidelines-seek-to-prevent-sudden-death-in-young-athletes/">Full Story</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/new-guidelines-to-protect-student-athletes/">New Guidelines to Protect Student Athletes</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Database Tracks Infant Deaths</title>
		<link>/blog/new-database-tracks-infant-deaths/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2012 14:44:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Medical]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3343</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This is a huge step in the right direction.  We can&#8217;t have an informed discussion about kids dying until we really know how many died and WHY they died.  I hope that this database will also track how many of these kids died from cardiac events.  Did you know that research from Dr. Michael Ackerman [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/new-database-tracks-infant-deaths/">New Database Tracks Infant Deaths</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a huge step in the right direction.  We can&#8217;t have an informed discussion about kids dying until we really know how many died and WHY they died.  I hope that this database will also track how many of these kids died from cardiac events.  Did you know that research from Dr. Michael Ackerman at Mayo suggests that up to 30% of all unexplained infant deaths are attributed to a cardiac arrhythmia?</em></p>
<p>In recent years, the number of reported cases of sudden infant death syndrome (SIDS) has declined, with a 50 percent drop reported since 1990.</p>
<p>While that&#8217;s good news on the surface, researchers are now hoping to determine whether this is due to true public health improvements, or is simply a difference in how deaths are recorded, by creating a new database.  Details about how the database, called the Sudden Unexpected Infant Death Case Registry, will help researchers answer the questions that surround SIDS are described today in an article by researchers from the <a href="http://www.foxnews.com/topics/health/medicine/center-for-disease-control.htm#r_src=ramp">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</a> (CDC).</p>
<p>&#8220;Right now, when we want to do surveillance and actually monitor <a href="http://www.myhealthnewsdaily.com/1374-breast-feeding-sudden-infant-death-syndrome-sids.html">trends in SIDS</a> and other infant deaths… we&#8217;re limited by the data collected [in U.S. mortality records],&#8221; said article co-author Carrie Shapiro-Mendoza, a senior scientist at the CDC.</p>
<p><a href=" http://www.foxnews.com/health/2012/01/09/unexplained-infant-deaths-to-be-recorded-in-new-database/#ixzz1jA20jY6F">Full story</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/new-database-tracks-infant-deaths/">New Database Tracks Infant Deaths</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Pulse Ox &#8211; What It Means to Simon&#8217;s Fund</title>
		<link>/blog/pulse-ox-what-it-means-to-simons-fund/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[creativemms]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2011 16:22:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1901</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A Federal Government Advisory Committee is urging the use of this test.  Two Governors (Maryland and New Jersey) recently signed laws mandating the use of this test.  Clearly, the hearts of newborns are front of mind. These laws require that a Pulse Ox test be performed on all newborns.  The test measures the level of oxygen [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/pulse-ox-what-it-means-to-simons-fund/">Pulse Ox &#8211; What It Means to Simon&#8217;s Fund</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/08/22/earlyshow/living/parenting/main20095411.shtml">Federal Government Advisory Committee </a>is urging the use of this test.  Two Governors (<a href="http://www.childrensnational.org/pressroom/NewsReleases/md-governor-signs-bill-mandating-newborn-screening-for-congenital-heart-disease.aspx">Maryland</a> and <a href="http://www.nj.com/jjournal-news/index.ssf/2011/06/jersey_becomes_first_state_to.html">New Jersey</a>) recently signed laws mandating the use of this test.  Clearly, the hearts of newborns are front of mind.</p>
<p>These laws require that a <a href="http://www.childrensnational.org/PulseOx/FAQ.aspx">Pulse Ox</a> test be performed on all newborns.  The test measures the level of oxygen in the blood.  Low levels can indicate problems with the heart and/or lungs.</p>
<p>Why is this important?  The test is cheap and non-invasive.  It leads to the detection of congenital (inherited) heart defects – the most common birth defect.  The reality is that the Pulse Ox has been widely used for many years and is a standard of care in many major hospitals.  However, these laws guarantee its use in ALL hospitals.</p>
<p>Simon’s Fund is very pleased with this development.  The laws will save lives.  They will raise awareness about the prevalence and prevention of heart conditions in children.  They create a precedence of utilizing inexpensive and non-invasive methods to screen for heart conditions in children, which is core to Simon’s Fund’s mission.</p>
<p>However, these laws don’t replace our efforts.  We are providing ECG exams to all newborns at the <a href="http://www.amh.org/forthemedia/2009/amh-opens-new-obgyn-center.aspx">Corrine Santerian Newborn Clinic</a> because we believe this will detect other structural and electrical conditions that lead to sudden cardiac arrest and death.  We are providing heart screenings for students around the Philadelphia area because far too many of them are dropping dead.</p>
<p>Our screenings, which involve an ECG and Echocardiogram, do not look for the same conditions as the Pulse Ox.  Furthermore, many of the conditions that are detected through our screenings may not be present at birth (the Pulse Ox is done 24 hours after birth).</p>
<p>We need laws and initiatives like this.  We need compassionate legislators and Governors.  We need nonprofits to screen the hearts of students.  There is plenty of room under this umbrella.  There are plenty of ways to check hearts and save lives.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/pulse-ox-what-it-means-to-simons-fund/">Pulse Ox &#8211; What It Means to Simon&#8217;s Fund</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>It&#8217;s the Doctors, Not the Test</title>
		<link>/blog/its-the-doctors-not-the-test/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[creativemms]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2011 19:55:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Medical]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1915</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Stanford study released this week shows that pediatric cardiologists are not very good at interpreting the ECG exams.  This is an institutional problem that should be corrected by the medical community.  Unfortunately, articles like the one below, are misleading the public by suggesting that the tests that look for heart condition in student athletes are innacurate.   Electrocardiograms [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/its-the-doctors-not-the-test/">It&#8217;s the Doctors, Not the Test</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The Stanford study released this week shows that pediatric cardiologists are not very good at interpreting the ECG exams.  This is an institutional problem that should be corrected by the medical community.  Unfortunately, articles like the one below, are misleading the public by suggesting that the tests that look for heart condition in student athletes are innacurate.  </em></p>
<p>Electrocardiograms are an inaccurate way to screen for heart defects that can cause sudden cardiac arrest in young athletes, according to a study in <em>The <a title="More news, photos about Journal of Pediatrics" href="http://content.usatoday.com/topics/topic/Journal+of+Pediatrics">Journal of Pediatrics</a></em>.</p>
<div>
<div id="columnistmug">The overall accuracy of the cardiologists was 67%. The findings add to the growing debate about how to protect the health of young athletes on playing fields. Sports programs in the <a title="More news, photos about USA" href="http://content.usatoday.com/topics/topic/Places,+Geography/Countries/United+States">USA</a> have come under increasing pressure to require electrocardiograms in light of reports that sudden cardiac arrests (CSAs) are the leading cause of death of young athletes.</div>
</div>
<p>One of the most recent tragedies involved Michigan high school basketball player Wes Leonard, who collapsed and died March 3 when his heart stopped moments after sinking a game-winning basket to close his team&#8217;s perfect 20-0 season. The Fennville High athlete was 16.</p>
<p>While some European countries make the ECG tests mandatory, the American Heart Association&#8217;s 2007 guidelines call for a thorough pre-participation checkup — short of recommending an ECG — for the nation&#8217;s 10.7 million young athletes.</p>
<p>According to the <a title="More news, photos about National Federation of State High School Associations" href="http://content.usatoday.com/topics/topic/National+Federation+of+State+High+School+Associations">National Federation of State High School Associations</a>, the frequency and thoroughness of pre-performance physical exams varies from state to state. &#8220;Some are every year, while others are every two years,&#8221; spokesman Bob Colgate says. &#8220;There might still be some who don&#8217;t require exams.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="http://www.usatoday.com/news/health/2011-07-14-ECG-heart-defect-athlete_n.htm">Full Story</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/its-the-doctors-not-the-test/">It&#8217;s the Doctors, Not the Test</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Study Confirms Students Should Get Hearts Screened</title>
		<link>/blog/study-confirms-students-should-get-hearts-screened/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2011 10:44:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Medical]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1809</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Congrats to our friend, Dr. Joe Marek, for getting this study published.  He is proving that hearts screening for our kids are effective, affordable, managable and save lives.  This issue is debated, but there are no U.S. studies that show hearts screenings are ineffective, unaffordable, unmanagable and don&#8217;t save lives.   That side of the argument [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/study-confirms-students-should-get-hearts-screened/">Study Confirms Students Should Get Hearts Screened</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://ad.doubleclick.net/click;h=v8/3b00/0/0/%2a/i;44306;0-0;0;49595676;32414-468/648;0/0/0;;~okv=;kw=healthnews;kw=familyhealth;kw=heart;kw=articles;kw=healthday;kw=heartdisease;kw=health;kw=exerciseandfitness;sz=468x648;tile=2;~aopt=2/1/50/0;~sscs=%3f" target="_top"><img decoding="async" src="https://s0.2mdn.net/viewad/817-grey.gif" alt="Click here to find out more!" border="0" /></a><em>Congrats to our friend, Dr. Joe Marek, for getting this study published.  He is proving that hearts screening for our kids are effective, affordable, managable and save lives.  This issue is debated, but there are no U.S. studies that show hearts screenings are ineffective, unaffordable, unmanagable and don&#8217;t save lives.   That side of the argument just likes to rely on opinion.  Instead of believing that this is not a good idea, let&#8217;s join together to gather data to PROVE whether it is or is not a good idea. </em></p>
<p><em>Thanks Joe for your commitment and dedication.</em></p>
<p><strong>By Steven Reinberg</strong><br />
<em>HealthDay Reporter</em></p>
<p>THURSDAY, April 5 (HealthDay News) &#8212; Checking the hearts of teenagers, athletes and non-athletes alike, could save thousands of lives, a new study suggests.  The heart check recommended is an electrocardiogram (ECG), which records the electrical activity in the heart and identifies those at risk for sudden cardiac arrest.</p>
<p>&#8220;I think we should do this testing and find the kids who are at risk for sudden death and potentially save their lives,&#8221; said the study&#8217;s <a id="KonaLink0" href="http://health.usnews.com/health-news/family-health/heart/articles/2011/05/05/screening-teens-hearts-could-be-lifesaving#"><span style="color: #005497;">lead researcher</span></a>, Dr. Joseph Marek, founder and medical director of the Midwest Heart Foundation in Oakbrook Terrace, Ill. ECGs are especially important for teens who are going to take part in sports, he said.</p>
<p>&#8220;To me as a parent, this is a no-brainer,&#8221; Marek said. &#8220;I think <a id="KonaLink1" href="http://health.usnews.com/health-news/family-health/heart/articles/2011/05/05/screening-teens-hearts-could-be-lifesaving#"><span style="color: #005497;">doctors</span></a> should be recommending ECGs to their teen patients.&#8221;  Not everyone agrees, however. One of the main objections to doing extensive ECG testing has been cost, but Marek said the tests in his study cost less than $10 each. For the study, his team raised money for the testing through community donations.</p>
<p>Marek said that some also feared that testing teens would swamp the medical system because the rate of abnormal heart rhythms among young adults was thought to be in the 10 percent to 40 percent range. But, he said, &#8220;our study shows that number is well under 3 percent,&#8221; so that idea &#8220;doesn&#8217;t hold water.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;ECG testing of young adults is certainly feasible,&#8221; he said.  Each year in the United States, more than 250,000 people die from sudden cardiac arrest, including an estimated 2,000 young adults, according to the study.  But, according to Marek, &#8220;sudden cardiac death in young adults can be identified before they have a catastrophe in a cost-effective manner by doing ECG testing.&#8221;</p>
<p>For an ECG test, small patches called electrodes are put on the skin in several places on the body and attached by wires to a machine that will print out wavy lines that indicate the heart&#8217;s electrical activity, according to the U.S. National Library of Medicine. The person lies very still for the test, which usually takes only a few minutes.</p>
<p>Between 2006 and 2010, Marek&#8217;s research team gave ECGs to 50,665 teens, 14 to 18 years old, including athletes and non-athletes. The screening was done in 32 schools in suburban Chicago during the regular school day.  Screening identified 1,096 teens with abnormal ECGs, indicating a heart irregularity that could result in sudden cardiac death. Of those teens, 150 were found to have left ventricular hypertrophy, which can lead to hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, the most common cause of sudden cardiac death. Another 145 had a condition called prolonged QTc, which could indicate long QT syndrome, also linked to sudden cardiac death.</p>
<p>The findings were to be presented Thursday in San Francisco at the Heart Rhythm Society&#8217;s annual scientific sessions. Experts note that research presented at meetings should be considered preliminary because it has not been subjected to the rigorous scrutiny given to research published in medical journals.</p>
<p>A similar study done in Italy over a 26-year period found that ECG screening cut the number of cardiac deaths by 89 percent, Marek said.  Dr. Gregg Fonarow, the associate chief of cardiology at the University of California, Los Angeles, <a id="KonaLink2" href="http://health.usnews.com/health-news/family-health/heart/articles/2011/05/05/screening-teens-hearts-could-be-lifesaving#"><span style="color: #005497;">medical school</span></a> said that &#8220;sudden cardiac death in the young can have devastating impact on families, care providers and the community.&#8221;</p>
<p>Though some of the abnormalities that cause these deaths can be detected by screening ECGs, Fonarow said, &#8220;the routine use of screening ECGs in the young is controversial.&#8221;  <a id="KonaLink3" href="http://health.usnews.com/health-news/family-health/heart/articles/2011/05/05/screening-teens-hearts-could-be-lifesaving#"><span style="color: #005497;">Further studies</span></a> of ECG screening are needed to evaluate the resource requirements, reliability, reproducibility, effectiveness of preventing sudden cardiac arrest and potential harmful effects of screening,&#8221; he said.</p>
<p><a href="http://health.usnews.com/health-news/family-health/heart/articles/2011/05/05/screening-teens-hearts-could-be-lifesaving">Full story</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/study-confirms-students-should-get-hearts-screened/">Study Confirms Students Should Get Hearts Screened</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
