<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Products Archive - GotAED.org</title>
	<atom:link href="/shop/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/shop/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 20:15:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>NCE Cares, Inc. Giving November AED Drive</title>
		<link>/product/nce-cares-inc-giving-november-aed-drive/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[nce.cares@gmail.com]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 20:15:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/nce-cares-inc-giving-november-aed-drive/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This Giving November, NCE Cares, Inc. is raising funds to purchase an AED (automated external defibrillator), a crucial piece of life-saving equipment for Nor*Cal Elite Allstars San Jose location.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/nce-cares-inc-giving-november-aed-drive/">NCE Cares, Inc. Giving November AED Drive</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This Giving November, NCE Cares, Inc. is raising funds to purchase an AED (automated external defibrillator), a crucial piece of life-saving equipment for Nor*Cal Elite Allstars San Jose location. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/nce-cares-inc-giving-november-aed-drive/">NCE Cares, Inc. Giving November AED Drive</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Emmanuel Baptist Church AED Campaign</title>
		<link>/product/emmanuel-baptist-church-aed-campaign/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Luke Altman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 18:42:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/emmanuel-baptist-church-aed-campaign/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Emmanuel Baptist Church can be found in the small community of White Oak, Texas. We exist to exalt Jesus Christ while loving one another, caring for needs, and sharing the gospel with each other, the region, and the world around us. As our church grows, we must be prepared for the unexpected, so we are [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/emmanuel-baptist-church-aed-campaign/">Emmanuel Baptist Church AED Campaign</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Emmanuel Baptist Church can be found in the small community of White Oak, Texas. We exist to exalt Jesus Christ while loving one another, caring for needs, and sharing the gospel with each other, the region, and the world around us. As our church grows, we must be prepared for the unexpected, so we are initiating a campaign to purchase an Automated External Defibrillator (AED) and provide training to our congregation. </p>
<p>Sudden cardiac arrest (SCA) is a leading cause of death in the United States, and it can happen to anyone, anywhere, at any time. Having an AED on hand can mean the difference between life and death for someone experiencing an SCA. With this campaign, we could purchase an AED that would be readily available in our church in an emergency.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/emmanuel-baptist-church-aed-campaign/">Emmanuel Baptist Church AED Campaign</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tornado Heart Rescue</title>
		<link>/product/tornado-heart-rescue/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[nsistrunk@phillytornadoes.com]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2023 16:00:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/tornado-heart-rescue/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Philadelphia Public School District is a Title I school in an extreme poverty area. Our District has an emergency plan in place but we don't have the AED for the emergency that may arise. We have the staff trained and ready to execute if the need arises. We hope we never have to use it [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/tornado-heart-rescue/">Tornado Heart Rescue</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Philadelphia Public School District is a Title I school in an extreme poverty area. Our District has an emergency plan in place but we don&#8217;t have the AED for the emergency that may arise. We have the staff trained and ready to execute if the need arises. We hope we never have to use it but we want it to be here if the emergency takes place. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/tornado-heart-rescue/">Tornado Heart Rescue</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Universe Living</title>
		<link>/product/universe-living-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[youniverselivingllc@gmail.com]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 04:22:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/universe-living-2/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>My name is Kieyona Walker I am the founder of Youniverse living. My involvement with the agency is to work alongside DHHS, and the local probation office to assist the youth with intellectual disabilities, developmental disabilities, and mental health disabilities who are involved in the juvenile justice system to successfully administer a system of person-centered [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/universe-living-2/">Universe Living</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My name is Kieyona Walker I am the founder of Youniverse living. My involvement with the agency is to work alongside DHHS, and the local probation office to assist the youth with intellectual disabilities, developmental disabilities, and mental health disabilities who are involved in the juvenile justice system to successfully administer a system of person-centered community supports and services that will aid, foster independence, exercise their right to make choices, grow and contribute to their community and improve quality of life for individuals who suffer intellectual and developmental disabilities. The facility &#8220;Youniverse Living &#8221; will receive the AED. This agency needs the AED as a result of the agency&#8217;s association with serving a tremendously diverse subset of youth who experience many medical conditions causing sudden cardiac arrest. With the opportunity to be gifted an AED will increase the survival rate. Having experienced performing CPR on a child who suffered a cardiac arrest in the past year and realizing that with an AED on hand would have decreased the amount of time and increased her survival rate.  </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/universe-living-2/">Universe Living</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Universe Living</title>
		<link>/product/universe-living/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[youniverselivingllc@gmail.com]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 04:22:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/universe-living/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>My name is Kieyona Walker I am the founder of Youniverse living. My involvement with the agency is to work alongside DHHS, and the local probation office to assist the youth with intellectual disabilities, developmental disabilities, and mental health disabilities who are involved in the juvenile justice system to successfully administer a system of person-centered [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/universe-living/">Universe Living</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My name is Kieyona Walker I am the founder of Youniverse living. My involvement with the agency is to work alongside DHHS, and the local probation office to assist the youth with intellectual disabilities, developmental disabilities, and mental health disabilities who are involved in the juvenile justice system to successfully administer a system of person-centered community supports and services that will aid, foster independence, exercise their right to make choices, grow and contribute to their community and improve quality of life for individuals who suffer intellectual and developmental disabilities. The facility &#8220;Youniverse Living &#8221; will receive the AED. This agency needs the AED as a result of the agency&#8217;s association with serving a tremendously diverse subset of youth who experience many medical conditions causing sudden cardiac arrest. With the opportunity to be gifted an AED will increase the survival rate. Having experienced performing CPR on a child who suffered a cardiac arrest in the past year and realizing that with an AED on hand would have decreased the amount of time and increased her survival rate.  </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/universe-living/">Universe Living</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Colectivo USA</title>
		<link>/product/colectivo-usa/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[eileen@colectivousa.com]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 06:20:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/colectivo-usa/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Our mission is to promote inclusive sports and healthy habits for people with Down Syndrome and intellectual disabilities that are done through sponsorship activities.  Empowering their integration to society as outstanding citizens and athletes is one of the many goals we have for them. As you may already know, children with down syndrome are at [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/colectivo-usa/">Colectivo USA</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Our mission is to promote inclusive sports and healthy habits for people with Down Syndrome and intellectual disabilities that are done through sponsorship activities.  Empowering their integration to society as outstanding citizens and athletes is one of the many goals we have for them.<br />
As you may already know, children with down syndrome are at a much higher risk for congenital heart disease. Unfortunately, we currently do not have an AED onsite. Having an AED onsite, where many of them gather to practice sports in a daily basis, could save many lives. We need to be prepared in case of an emergency so we could do our best to help save a life.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/colectivo-usa/">Colectivo USA</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Anchor Bay High School Athletics</title>
		<link>/product/anchor-bay-athletics/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[elanda@abs.misd.net]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2023 19:13:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/anchor-bay-athletics/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I am the certified and licensed athletic trainer at Anchor Bay High School. We are looking to obtain 2 additional AEDs to place outdoors. One AED being at our baseball/softball restroom facilities, and the other to be attached to the brick shed of our tennis courts. The locations of these AEDs will play a viable [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/anchor-bay-athletics/">Anchor Bay High School Athletics</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am the certified and licensed athletic trainer at Anchor Bay High School. We are looking to obtain 2 additional AEDs to place outdoors. One AED being at our baseball/softball restroom facilities, and the other to be attached to the brick shed of our tennis courts.<br />
The locations of these AEDs will play a viable role in Anchor Bay High School to become a Michigan HeartSafe school, as well as providing appropriate response time to rescue someone who may be in cardiac arrest.<br />
As of now, Anchor Bay High School has 3 outdoor AEDs that are placed throughout the athletic facilities. Adding these two AEDs will be a positive attribute to high school athletics, as well as to the organizations that rent the facilities out to have their sporting events.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/anchor-bay-athletics/">Anchor Bay High School Athletics</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Great Escape ELC</title>
		<link>/product/great-escape-elc/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Newlife1222@yahoo.com]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 02:32:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/great-escape-elc/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hi my name is Melissa Burkett, I recently accepted a job at a church preschool program as there new UPK teacher. I recently discovered that they only have one AED in the building, which is on the top floor of the church. As a pre-k teacher I know the benefits of having one close by [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/great-escape-elc/">Great Escape ELC</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hi my name is Melissa Burkett, I recently accepted a job at a church preschool program as there new UPK teacher. I recently discovered that they only have one AED in the building, which is on the top floor of the church. As a pre-k teacher I know the benefits of having one close by in our area of the building. That 2-3 minutes it would take to grab the one we have in the building could be detrimental. We service about 70 children from 12 months to 5 years old, not to mention some of the elderly staff we have. Like I said I am new to the program and want to prove my value to to company.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/great-escape-elc/">Great Escape ELC</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>AED for Early Childhood Education Center</title>
		<link>/product/aed-for-early-childhood-education-center/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kspiva@monicaros.org]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2023 21:20:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/aed-for-early-childhood-education-center/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Monica Ros School is a non-profit school serving residents in the Ojai Valley. Our current Head of School, Kate Spiva, is a former EMT who knows the importance of AEDs being readily accessible in emergency situations. Monica Ros serves students of all races, ethnicities, gender identities and economic status.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/aed-for-early-childhood-education-center/">AED for Early Childhood Education Center</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Monica Ros School is a non-profit school serving residents in the Ojai Valley. Our current Head of School, Kate Spiva, is a former EMT who knows the importance of AEDs being readily accessible in emergency situations.<br />
Monica Ros serves students of all races, ethnicities, gender identities and economic status. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/aed-for-early-childhood-education-center/">AED for Early Childhood Education Center</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Suring School Football Field AED</title>
		<link>/product/suring-school-football-field-aed/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[schoco@suringk12.org]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2023 18:18:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">/product/suring-school-football-field-aed/</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Our school is a 3k-12 school. We have 2 AEDs currently but nothing at our off site track/football field. Currently we are taking one from the school over, as long as someone remembers to grab it. We host a lot of different districts during track season and football season along with the crowds. The school [...]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/suring-school-football-field-aed/">Suring School Football Field AED</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Our school is a 3k-12 school. We have 2 AEDs currently but nothing at our off site track/football field. Currently we are taking one from the school over, as long as someone remembers to grab it. We host a lot of different districts during track season and football season along with the crowds. The school and closest AED is 3 blocks away if no one remembered to grab it.  We would love to house one at the field so we do not have to worry about not having one available. </p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/product/suring-school-football-field-aed/">Suring School Football Field AED</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">GotAED.org</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
