<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>NCAA Archives -</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/tag/ncaa/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Protecting Hearts and Saving Lives</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 08:39:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/simons-fav-icon1.png</url>
	<title>NCAA Archives -</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>The Madness of March, 2019</title>
		<link>/blog/the-madness-of-march-2019/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Simon's Heart]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 18:02:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Student Athlete Collapse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sudden Cardiac Death]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AED]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Final Four]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[March Madness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NCAA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sudden cardiac arrest]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8758</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The competition throughout the NCAA basketball season is always high but as soon as March rolls around it changes dramatically. March Madness. Teams are no longer just competing against other teams, but they are competing for spots, wins, and championships. Brackets start forming, bets are on the table and the conversations start. Conversations about upsets, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-madness-of-march-2019/">The Madness of March, 2019</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The competition throughout the NCAA basketball season is always high but as soon as March rolls around it changes dramatically. March Madness. Teams are no longer just competing against other teams, but they are competing for spots, wins, and championships. Brackets start forming, bets are on the table and the conversations start. Conversations about upsets, final four and championships but never heart conditions, AED devices or sudden cardiac arrest.</p>
<p>When you sit and watch the games, your main focus is that game. You aren’t thinking about injuries, the what-ifs or even heart issues. I know Shaquille O’Neal does. His 19-year-old son, <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/sports/ncaab/2018/09/28/uclas-shareef-oneal-to-miss-season-with-heart-ailment/37975417/">Shareef</a> was diagnosed with a heart condition at the end of last year.</p>
<blockquote><p>Sudden cardiac arrest is the number one cause of death of student-athletes. In fact, every three days a young athlete in the US collapses and dies due to an undetected heart condition.</p></blockquote>
<p>People typically don’t pay attention to the statistics unless it&#8217;s newsworthy and they read about it on their sports app. NCAA basketball players have a 1 in 3,000 chance of experiencing a sudden cardiac arrest event. In this NCAA tournament alone, there are three players and two coaches that have dealt with a heart-related issue. That is about 8%.</p>
<p>Minnesota a No. 10 seed will play today at 12:15 pm against No. 7 seed Louisville in the first round of the NCAA tournament. Did you know that Jarvis Johnson, a four-star prospect out of high school, recruited by ISU, was never able to suit up for Minnesota? Why? A heart condition called hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. He was never cleared to play competitively and his career as a basketball player was cut short. As a sixth man, he is watching and cheering on his teammates from the sidelines.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.toledoblade.com/sports/ohio-state/2019/02/13/once-an-unheralded-recruit-Andre-Wesson-rises-up-for-Ohio-State/stories/20190213011">Andre Wesson</a> from Ohio State is a prized defender. There was a good chance that Ohio State wouldn’t have been at the No. 11 seed if it wasn’t for his skills, attitude, and progression this season. It is a big surprise to learn that Wesson had a slow start last season due to a heart issue that was discovered by the Ohio State’s team doctors.</p>
<p>Making it this far in the NCAA tournament felt like an impossibility to <a href="http://theacc.com/news/2019/3/13/mens-basketball-virginia-techs-ty-outlaw-named-bradley-award-winner.aspx">Ty Outlaw</a> at Virginia Tech in 2015 when he was diagnosed with a heart condition. A heart condition that threatened to end his Hokies career. Outlaw was having difficulties recovering after drills during the preseason. Virginia Tech knew about a septal defect that Outlaw was born with that caused murmurs along with his high blood pressure. His struggles continued when he learned about his diagnosis of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. That was enough to shut him down in the 2015-2016 season. Now Outlaw has the reputation as being one of the top 3-point shooters in the ACC. Pretty impressive for someone with a heart condition.</p>
<p>No. 2 Michigan and No. 15 Montana will be facing off today at 9:20 pm. Who would have thought that both coaches have dealt with heart issues? Michigan <a href="http://www.espn.com/mens-college-basketball/story/_/id/24796749/john-beilein-michigan-reflects-offseason-heart-surgery">Coach John Beilein</a> had a double bypass heart operation. <a href="http://406mtsports.com/college/frontier-conference/university-of-providence/providence-men-s-basketball-coach-steve-keller-on-the-mend/article_96d8b9ea-5bd4-521c-9e90-b8791313107c.html">Montana Coach Steve Keller</a> endured a heart attack just a few months ago.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the players above have happy endings. They might not be able to follow their dreams to play in the tournament or even the NBA but their life wasn’t cut short. In this month alone there were six teens that lost their lives from an undiagnosed heart condition or sudden cardiac arrest. <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/health/pennsylvania-teen-13-dies-after-sudden-cardiac-arrest-school-says">Daron Lewis Godbee</a>, 13; <a href="https://www.phillyvoice.com/newville-teen-big-spring-pennsylvania-basketball-heart-attack/">Jonathan “JT” Kuhn</a>, 16; <a href="https://www.ktbs.com/news/caddo-parish-schools-mourns-the-loss-of-domanique-jones/article_34c9d6f6-3aeb-11e9-90af-8355eee1db59.html">Domanique Jones</a>, 18; <a href="https://www.fredericksburg.com/news/local/fredericksburg/jmhs-mourns-death-of-student-who-collapsed-during-gym-class/article_2e3a087c-c281-5383-bbc3-718fd03a8e29.html">Anonymous student</a>, 16; <a href="https://nypost.com/2019/03/07/high-school-football-player-dies-after-passing-out-in-weight-room/">Jermaine Falcaer</a>, 16; and Scott Krulcik, 22.</p>
<blockquote><p>These deaths could have been prevented with heart screenings or the use of an AED device.</p></blockquote>
<p>Simon’s Heart is dedicated to changing the standard of care to screen all kids and make AED devices readily available in all schools and youth facilities. You never know if a seemingly healthy athlete could have a ticking time bomb.</p>
<p>As you continue to follow the NCAA tournament, change your perspective. Learn about the warning signs that lead to sudden cardiac arrest. Understand what an AED device is. Recognize where the closest device might be. Get your hearts checked.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-madness-of-march-2019/">The Madness of March, 2019</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>No Drugs! Death, Maybe</title>
		<link>/blog/no-drugs-death-maybe/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 18:44:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cardiac arrest]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NCAA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[steroids]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8710</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>How many student athletes die from steroid use? That was the first thought to cross my mind after hearing that Clemson players, Dexler Lawrence, Zach Giella and Braden Galloway, were suspended from the BCS Championship Playoff. Despite having filed an appeal last week, they won’t be on the field tonight in the Championship Game. I [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/no-drugs-death-maybe/">No Drugs! Death, Maybe</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>How many student athletes die from steroid use? That was the first thought to cross my mind after hearing that Clemson players, Dexler Lawrence, Zach Giella and Braden Galloway, <a href="https://www.cbssports.com/college-football/news/clemson-dl-dexter-lawrence-two-other-suspended-players-wont-play-vs-alabama/">were suspended</a> from the BCS Championship Playoff. Despite having filed an appeal last week, they won’t be on the field tonight in the Championship Game.</p>
<p>I don’t believe that death is the only consequence. Steroids are unhealthy, and using them is considered cheating. However, when steroid use is viewed against the backdrop of sudden cardiac arrest and death in sport, it really makes me wonder about our priorities.</p>
<p>The NCAA set forth its policy on steroid use in the <a href="http://www.ncaa.org/sport-science-institute/ncaa-drug-testing-program">NCAA Drug Testing Program</a>. The policy identifies drugs that are “potentially harmful to the health and safety of the student-athlete.” The rationale for the policy seems to reflect a “dedication to the ideal of fair and equitable intercollegiate competition at their championships and postseason bowl games.</p>
<p>So, we’ve accepted the reality that our student athletes can be randomly tested for drugs during the season. Before the “big” game, that testing should be mandatory. We have also accepted that these tests are reliable enough to warrant suspension from “big” games, even if there’s a chance we’re wrong. In the case of the Clemson players, there are <a href="https://www.usada.org/growing-evidence-ostarine-athlete-risk/">thirty-six supplements</a> that contain the banned substance of ostarine. This is a very different approach than we’re taking to sudden cardiac arrest and death.</p>
<p>Four years ago, <a href="mailto:https://www.wsj.com/articles/ncaa-doctor-backs-off-recommending-heart-tests-for-athletes-1429291801">Brian Hainline</a>, the Chief Medical Officer of the NCAA, suggested that all high risk athletes, namely basketball and football players, be required to undergo a cardiac exam before taking the field or court. <a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Drezner_ECG-Screening-in-NCAA-Athletes_AJC-2016.pdf">Research</a> supports this position and shows that heart screenings are far more effective at detecting heart conditions in NCAA athletes.</p>
<p>The backlash was brutal and the idea was quickly scrapped.</p>
<p>All or nothing shouldn’t be the only choice when setting policy for the health and safety of student athletes. It’s not for steroids.</p>
<p>Last year, the news media reported the deaths of nine student athletes from suspected sudden cardiac arrest. Yet, no student athlete was randomly tested for heart conditions this season, and none of the players from Notre Dame, Oklahoma, Clemson and Alabama were required to get a heart screening before the BCS Championship Playoffs. Some schools do provide heart screenings for their student athletes. This year, <a href="https://www.mcall.com/sports/college/psu/mc-spt-penn-state-football-nana-asiedu-20180627-story.html">Penn State football</a> discovered career-ending conditions in two of its players.</p>
<p>If steroids pose a significant health risk for our student athletes, I welcome testing. If steroid use threatens the integrity of sport, let’s prevent and punish its use. But, is this about health or cheating? If it’s about health, let’s apply the same or stricter standards to testing for heart conditions. I think that we can all agree that losing a game because of cheating sucks, but losing a player is tragic.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/no-drugs-death-maybe/">No Drugs! Death, Maybe</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sudden Death is for Hockey, not NCAA Basketball Players</title>
		<link>/blog/sudden-death-is-for-hockey-not-ncaa-basketball-players/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2013 00:30:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Final Four]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NCAA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sudden-death]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=4620</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>All eyes are set on Atlanta this weekend as it hosts the NCAA Final Four.  For weeks, millions of Americans have been glued to their TVs to see if their team survives into the next round. But for some players and coaches in the NCAA, survival means much more than advancing in the tournament. Sudden [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/sudden-death-is-for-hockey-not-ncaa-basketball-players/">Sudden Death is for Hockey, not NCAA Basketball Players</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>All eyes are set on Atlanta this weekend as it hosts the NCAA Final Four.  For weeks, millions of Americans have been glued to their TVs to see if their team survives into the next round.</p>
<p>But for some players and coaches in the NCAA, survival means much more than advancing in the tournament.</p>
<p>Sudden cardiac arrest is the #1 cause of death of student athletes. According to the American Academy of Pediatrics, it takes the lives of 2,000 students every year.  By many accounts, this number is low because we don’t track the causes of death of children in this country.</p>
<p>The sudden death of Hank Gathers 23 years ago is always mentioned when discussing the topic of sudden cardiac arrest, but we don’t need to look beyond this season, or even this year’s tournament to recognize the tragic impact that sudden cardiac arrest is having on our sport and our young athletes.</p>
<p>Coach Fred Hoiberg led the Iowa State Cyclones into the Round of 32.  He retired from the NBA seven years ago after discovering a heart condition.</p>
<p>Creighton University advanced into the Round of 32 without their guard, Josh Jones.  He retired from basketball earlier this year after undergoing a procedure to correct a heart condition.</p>
<p>Carl Hall, a starting forward for Wichita State, retired from basketball in 2009 due to a heart condition.  With medication, he has returned and is leading the Shockers to their first Final Four since 1965.  Guy Alang-Ntang, also a Shocker, was not as lucky.  He was recruited to play for the Shockers in 2007.  During an exhibition game, he collapsed and died.  Coach Gregg Marshall was in the stands the night he collapsed.</p>
<p>A <a href="http://circ.ahajournals.org/content/early/2011/04/05/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.004622.abstract">recent study</a> published by the American Heart Association shows that 1 out of every 3,100 NCAA Division I male basketball players is at risk of dying from sudden cardiac arrest (SCA) every year.  This year, it was Nathaniel Joshua “Erv” Ervin.  He collapsed and died during a basketball game at Mars Hill College.  It could have also been Danny Berger, a forward at Utah State University, who collapsed as well.  Fortunately for Berger, an AED device was able to shock his heart and save his life.</p>
<p>Is it acceptable that every year at least one NCAA basketball player will die from a detectable and preventable condition?  Josh Jones and Carl Jones had symptoms.  As such, they got their hearts checked.  Nathaniel Ervin and Danny Berger didn’t report any symptoms – their hearts did not get checked.</p>
<p>Checking the hearts of our student athletes makes sense.  In Italy, all of their student athletes get their hearts checked.  This practice reduced the incidence of sudden cardiac death there by 89 percent.  The NBA was the first professional league to institute mandatory heart screenings for its players.  Fred Hoiberg is just one of the many beneficiaries of this policy.  Last year, it was Jeff Green (Celtics) and LeMarcus Aldrige (Trailblazers).</p>
<p>A study published in the American Medical Society for Sports Medicine establishes that an ECG exam, coupled with a physical and complete medical history is the best way to detect and prevent conditions that lead to sudden cardiac arrest.</p>
<p>We need to start checking the hearts of our students because sports are supposed to be fun, not deadly.  It’s OK for us to wager on our Final Four pools.  It’s not OK for us to gamble with our children’s lives.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/sudden-death-is-for-hockey-not-ncaa-basketball-players/">Sudden Death is for Hockey, not NCAA Basketball Players</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Wichita State &#8211; Final Four &#038; Sudden Cardiac Arrest</title>
		<link>/blog/wichita-state-final-four-sudden-cardiac-arrest/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 12:59:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Student Athlete Collapse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sudden Cardiac Death]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Final Four]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NCAA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sudden cardiac arrest]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=4608</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Download Release Millions of Americans filled out their brackets and hoped that their team would survive on the Road to the Final Four. However, for some players, survival takes on a whole new meaning.  A recent study published by the American Heart Association shows that 1 out of every 3,100 NCAA Division I male basketball [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/wichita-state-final-four-sudden-cardiac-arrest/">Wichita State &#8211; Final Four &amp; Sudden Cardiac Arrest</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/Wichita-State-Release-4.2.13.pdf">Download Release</a></p>
<p>Millions of Americans filled out their brackets and hoped that their team would survive on the Road to the Final Four. However, for some players, survival takes on a whole new meaning.  A <a href="http://circ.ahajournals.org/content/early/2011/04/05/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.004622.abstract">recent study</a> published by the American Heart Association shows that 1 out of every 3,100 NCAA Division I male basketball players is at risk of dying from sudden cardiac arrest (SCA). <a href="/ways-to-give/simons-club/">Simon’s Fund</a>, a Philadelphia based organization, is trying to reduce that risk providing a free heart screening for over 300 students in an Atlanta suburb on Sunday.</p>
<p><b>Wichita State Has Firsthand Experience with Heart Conditions</b></p>
<p>Guy Alang-Ntang was recruited by the Shockers in 2008. He would have graduated last year, and with a little good fortune, played in the NBA. Instead, Alang-Ntang <a href="http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/news/story?id=2840755">dropped dead</a> of an undetected heart condition during a pick up basketball game months before starting at Wichita State.  Coach Gregg Marshall was there the night he collapsed and died.</p>
<p>Around the same time, Carl Hall, a senior forward for the Shockers, was told that his basketball career was over because he kept fainting during competition &#8212; the primary warning sign of SCA.  He took two years off from basketball, and in 2009, was prescribed medication to control his heart condition.  He made his way to Wichita State in 2011 and on Saturday night, he will lead the Shockers in their first Final Four appearance since 1965.</p>
<p>“Watching Carl Hall play in the Final Four inspires us to continue to raise awareness about the importance of heart screenings for student athletes,” says Darren Sudman, Executive Director of Simon’s Fund, who lost his son Simon to SCA. “The big difference between Alang-Ntang and Hall is that Hall got his heart checked and treated. That’s why he’s here playing.”</p>
<p><b>Local Atlanta Community Shocked by Sudden Death of Two Promising Basketball Players</b></p>
<p>Last year, in a suburb of Atlanta, Buford High School junior, <a href="http://www.ajc.com/news/sports/high-school/buford-high-basketball-player-dies-after-collapsin/nSCxt/">Adam Smith</a>, and Buford Middle School student, <a href="http://www.ajc.com/news/news/buford-player-12-collapses-during-game-and-/nTn45/">Jeremy Nelson</a>, died from SCA. They were both basketball standouts. Both may have been on the road to the Final Four. SCA ended their journeys.</p>
<p>On April 7, 2013, Simon’s Fund, working with the Cardiovascular Group in Lawrenceville, GA, will provide over 300 free heart screenings to students from the Buford and Gwinnett County School Districts.  In its eight- year history, Simon’s Fund has provided free heart screenings to 5,500 students.  One out of every 100 students checked discovers a heart condition.</p>
<p>At the screening, every student completes a medical history, has vital signs checked, and receives an ECG – a painless, non-invasive test that takes a couple of minutes. The ECG will be evaluated by local cardiologists.  Some students will receive an echocardiogram.</p>
<p>“As coaches, we spend so much time preparing our players, because we don’t we don’t to lose a game. We need to focus on sudden cardiac arrest, because losing a student athlete is much worse,” said Phil Martelli, men’s basketball coach of the St. Joseph’s University Hawks and First Vice President of the National Association of Basketball Coaches, which is meeting in Atlanta during the Final Four.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/wichita-state-final-four-sudden-cardiac-arrest/">Wichita State &#8211; Final Four &amp; Sudden Cardiac Arrest</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
