<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Student Athlete Collapse Archives -</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/student-athlete-collapse/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Protecting Hearts and Saving Lives</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 14:32:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/simons-fav-icon1.png</url>
	<title>Student Athlete Collapse Archives -</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>We Need To Be Prepared</title>
		<link>/blog/we-need-to-be-prepared/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 14:32:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[aed-donations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medical]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Student Athlete Collapse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sudden Cardiac Death]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AED]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AED awareness week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cleveland Clinic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cpr awareness week]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[defibrillator]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Samantha Krouse]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8827</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Dermot Phelan MD, Ph.D., FESC, FASE, FACC a staff cardiologist from the Cleveland Clinic interviews Samantha Krouse, Manager of GotAED about sudden cardiac arrest, the importance of early defibrillation and resources to get AED devices. Dr. Phelan: The sudden cardiac death of a young athlete or pupil has a profound effect on the community [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/we-need-to-be-prepared/">We Need To Be Prepared</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4>Dr. Dermot Phelan MD, Ph.D., FESC, FASE, FACC a staff cardiologist from the Cleveland Clinic interviews Samantha Krouse, Manager of GotAED about sudden cardiac arrest, the importance of early defibrillation and resources to get AED devices.</h4>
<p><strong>Dr. Phelan:</strong> The sudden cardiac death of a young athlete or pupil has a profound effect on the community at large. It often leaves people asking what more could have been done to prevent this tragic event. Could you describe the scope of this problem and what are the most common underlying causes of sudden cardiac death in the young?</p>
<p><strong>Samantha:</strong> We believe that thousands of children die every year from sudden cardiac arrest.&nbsp; Unfortunately, we don’t know for sure because our medical community didn’t start tracking the causes of death of minors until recently.&nbsp; The NIH and CDC created the <a href="https://www.nih.gov/news-events/news-releases/nih-cdc-launch-registry-sudden-death-young">sudden death registry</a> and it is being piloted in a handful of states. For instance, when a student is found at the bottom of a pool, the death certificate will say drowning or asphyxiation. But, what caused this student to drown?&nbsp; It could have been an arrhythmia, which is undetectable once the heart stops beating. The same for babies who die of SIDS or young adults who die in single-car accidents when the weather is good and there is no evidence of alcohol or drugs.</p>
<p>We can prevent these tragedies in a few ways:</p>
<ol>
<li>We must know that sudden cardiac arrest is not just an adult thing.&nbsp; There are some warning signs for us to watch:&nbsp; fainting during or right after exercise, a racing heart and sudden death of a family member under the age of 50.</li>
<li>Our kids should get their hearts screened.&nbsp; Research shows that an ECG exam, when done with a physical and history, is more effective at detecting heart conditions.</li>
<li>We need to be prepared. We need to know how to do chest compressions and have an AED around.&nbsp; The AED is the only tool that can save someone in cardiac arrest.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Dr. Phelan:</strong> Could you please tell us about the importance of early effective CPR and early defibrillation on outcomes in these events?</p>
<p><strong>Samantha:</strong> CPR and early defibrillation are critical, but let’s remember that they are the backup plan.&nbsp; We need these tools because we failed to detect the condition before it causes harm. CPR or chest compressions circulate blood throughout the body when the heart stops pumping.&nbsp; Without blood and oxygen, our organs will quickly fail.</p>
<p>The AED delivers a lifesaving shock to our heart. It resets the rhythm. It is the only tool that can do this.&nbsp; If someone provides bystander CPR and the use of an AED device is used within 3-5 minutes of the collapse, the survival rates are between 41%-74% (<a href="https://ksi.uconn.edu/">Korey Stringer Institute</a>). If you aren’t able to use an AED device or the device is inaccessible, the survival rates decline 7-10% per minute, every minute that defibrillation is delayed. That is why the best practice to save lives during a cardiac arrest event is to start chest compressions within 1 minute of collapse and grab the defibrillator within 3 minutes of collapse.</p>
<p><strong>Dr. Phelan:</strong> How can we improve education on basic life support in our communities?</p>
<p><strong>Samantha:</strong> The first step to improving education is demystifying the process.&nbsp; For decades, the heart community has required hours of training, certifications, and fees. There are stickers on AED cabinets claiming that the devices are professional use only.&nbsp; The public is scared and intimidated &#8211; for good reason.&nbsp; This stuff is easy. It’s super important but so easy.&nbsp; All students should be taught how to perform CPR and how to use an AED device in school. There are 38 states that encourage CPR education before graduation.&nbsp; That’s a start.</p>
<p>There is also technology like the <a href="https://www.pulsepoint.org/">PulsePoint</a> app that alerts bystanders about cardiac arrests nearby so they can assist until the first responders arrive. Pulse Point also has an AED registry, so the devices are easier to find.</p>
<p><strong>Dr. Phelan:</strong> Where should AEDs be made available?</p>
<p><strong>Samantha:</strong> AED devices should be made available everywhere, including where kids learn and play. Think about all of the safety tools we have but rarely (or never) use &#8211; fire extinguisher, smoke detector, smoke alarm, and burglar alarm. These all add value and mitigate risk.&nbsp; So, does an AED device.&nbsp; Sudden cardiac arrest is the leading cause of death of adults in the US.&nbsp; The only tool that can prevent it should be everywhere.</p>
<p><strong>Dr. Phelan:</strong> How much does an AED cost?</p>
<p><strong>Samantha:</strong> AEDs range in value like every other appliance or tool. They can retail for $1,100 &#8211; $2,500. <a href="https://www.cardiopartners.com/">Cardio Partners</a> is our AED partner for crowdfunding site, <a href="https://www.gotaed.org/">GotAED</a>. We are able to provide devices at a lower cost because of the nature of our site.</p>
<p><strong>Dr. Phelan:</strong> Please tell us about the work that <a href="https://www.gotaed.org/">GotAED</a> does?</p>
<p><strong>Samantha:</strong> GotAED is an initiative of <a href="/">Simon’s Heart</a>, a nonprofit organization dedicated to raising awareness about the warning signs and conditions that lead to sudden cardiac arrest and death in kids. We created this site to empower places to get AEDs even when they don’t have the budget to do so. We heard too many stories about youth facilities that wanted an AED but gave up because they didn’t have the money.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.gotaed.org/">GotAED</a> allows youth related facilities to quickly set up a campaign and raise funds. It takes a few minutes to get started. The cost is the same for everyone &#8211; around $900 &#8211; depending on the way that you want to store the device (and your state’s sales tax).&nbsp; Once the campaign is fully funded, the device and storage container is delivered right to the door. We also partner with <a href="https://www.projectadam.com/ProjectADAM">ProjectADAM</a> to help create cardiac emergency response plans for the youth facility.</p>
<p>Within its first year, GotAED helped 30 different schools, youth organizations, libraries, community centers, sports clubs/associations, and museums get AED devices in over 18 states.</p>
<p>GotAED also launched an awareness campaign with the Philadelphia Flyers. It is called the <a href="https://www.nhl.com/flyers/news/flyers-make-first-gotaed-overtime-challenge-device-donation--philadelphia-flyers/c-298661578">Overtime Challenge</a>.&nbsp; Every time the game enters the sudden death period, an AED is donated to a local youth facility.&nbsp; Sudden death is an exciting way to win a game, but a terrible way to lose a teammate.</p>
<p><strong>Dr. Phelan:</strong> If someone in the community wishes to purchase an AED, where should they go to get information.</p>
<p><strong>Samantha:</strong> There are a few places that provide funding for AED grants. However, money is scarce.&nbsp; So, if funding is not available, visit <a href="https://www.gotaed.org/">GotAED.org</a> and click the red button to “<a href="https://www.gotaed.org/add-campaign/">Start a Campaign</a>.”&nbsp; I am always available to answer questions &#8211;&nbsp;samantha@gotaed.org.</p>
<p>If you have funds, we recommend Cardio Partners.&nbsp; To receive a special discount, please enter the code SIMONSHEART2019 on <a href="https://www.aed.com/">AED.com</a> to get 20% off your total purchase.&nbsp; For more information, please contact Frank Mannino at francesco.mannino@cardiopartners.com.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>Dermot Phelan, MD, Ph.D., FESC, FASE, FACC</strong> is a staff cardiologist in the section of Cardiovascular Imaging in the <a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/departments/heart/depts/cardiovascular-medicine">Robert and Suzanne Tomsich Department of Cardiovascular Medicine,</a> and Medical Director of the <a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/departments/heart/depts/sports-cardiology-center">Sports Cardiology Center</a> in the Sydell and Arnold Miller Family Heart & Vascular Institute at <a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/">Cleveland Clinic</a>. He is an Assistant Professor at the<br />
<a href="https://case.edu/medicine/">Cleveland Clinic Lerner College of Medicine</a> of Case Western Reserve University. As Medical Director of the Sports Cardiology Center, Dr. Phelan is actively involved in the care of athletes of all levels. He has a national and international reputation as a passionate advocate for the promotion and protection of the cardiac health of athletes.</p>
<p><strong>Samantha Krouse</strong>, 24, is the Manager of Programs and Initiatives at Simon’s Heart, an organization dedicated to raising awareness about the warning signs and conditions that lead to sudden cardiac arrest and death in kids. By providing free heart screenings, advocating for legislation to protect student-athletes, promoting research through its national cardiac registry of seemingly healthy kids, distributing AED devices through its crowd-funding site, and raising awareness with strategic partnerships and cause marketing programs, Simon’s Heart is protecting hearts and saving lives. Samantha manages GotAED placing over 50 AED devices across the country, runs GotAED Overtime Challenge with the Philadelphia Flyers, launched a scholarship program for high school students with Montgomery County and PulsePoint to improve the county registry of AED locations, and directs AED Madness working with NCAA basketball teams to educate fans about cardiac arrest. Samantha was also honored as the recipient, on behalf of Simon’s Heart, for the <a href="https://www.nba.com/sixers/community/gamechanger">Game Changer Award at the Philadelphia 76ers</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/we-need-to-be-prepared/">We Need To Be Prepared</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Madness of March, 2019</title>
		<link>/blog/the-madness-of-march-2019/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Simon's Heart]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 18:02:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Student Athlete Collapse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sudden Cardiac Death]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AED]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Final Four]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[March Madness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NCAA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sudden cardiac arrest]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8758</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The competition throughout the NCAA basketball season is always high but as soon as March rolls around it changes dramatically. March Madness. Teams are no longer just competing against other teams, but they are competing for spots, wins, and championships. Brackets start forming, bets are on the table and the conversations start. Conversations about upsets, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-madness-of-march-2019/">The Madness of March, 2019</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The competition throughout the NCAA basketball season is always high but as soon as March rolls around it changes dramatically. March Madness. Teams are no longer just competing against other teams, but they are competing for spots, wins, and championships. Brackets start forming, bets are on the table and the conversations start. Conversations about upsets, final four and championships but never heart conditions, AED devices or sudden cardiac arrest.</p>
<p>When you sit and watch the games, your main focus is that game. You aren’t thinking about injuries, the what-ifs or even heart issues. I know Shaquille O’Neal does. His 19-year-old son, <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/sports/ncaab/2018/09/28/uclas-shareef-oneal-to-miss-season-with-heart-ailment/37975417/">Shareef</a> was diagnosed with a heart condition at the end of last year.</p>
<blockquote><p>Sudden cardiac arrest is the number one cause of death of student-athletes. In fact, every three days a young athlete in the US collapses and dies due to an undetected heart condition.</p></blockquote>
<p>People typically don’t pay attention to the statistics unless it&#8217;s newsworthy and they read about it on their sports app. NCAA basketball players have a 1 in 3,000 chance of experiencing a sudden cardiac arrest event. In this NCAA tournament alone, there are three players and two coaches that have dealt with a heart-related issue. That is about 8%.</p>
<p>Minnesota a No. 10 seed will play today at 12:15 pm against No. 7 seed Louisville in the first round of the NCAA tournament. Did you know that Jarvis Johnson, a four-star prospect out of high school, recruited by ISU, was never able to suit up for Minnesota? Why? A heart condition called hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. He was never cleared to play competitively and his career as a basketball player was cut short. As a sixth man, he is watching and cheering on his teammates from the sidelines.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.toledoblade.com/sports/ohio-state/2019/02/13/once-an-unheralded-recruit-Andre-Wesson-rises-up-for-Ohio-State/stories/20190213011">Andre Wesson</a> from Ohio State is a prized defender. There was a good chance that Ohio State wouldn’t have been at the No. 11 seed if it wasn’t for his skills, attitude, and progression this season. It is a big surprise to learn that Wesson had a slow start last season due to a heart issue that was discovered by the Ohio State’s team doctors.</p>
<p>Making it this far in the NCAA tournament felt like an impossibility to <a href="http://theacc.com/news/2019/3/13/mens-basketball-virginia-techs-ty-outlaw-named-bradley-award-winner.aspx">Ty Outlaw</a> at Virginia Tech in 2015 when he was diagnosed with a heart condition. A heart condition that threatened to end his Hokies career. Outlaw was having difficulties recovering after drills during the preseason. Virginia Tech knew about a septal defect that Outlaw was born with that caused murmurs along with his high blood pressure. His struggles continued when he learned about his diagnosis of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. That was enough to shut him down in the 2015-2016 season. Now Outlaw has the reputation as being one of the top 3-point shooters in the ACC. Pretty impressive for someone with a heart condition.</p>
<p>No. 2 Michigan and No. 15 Montana will be facing off today at 9:20 pm. Who would have thought that both coaches have dealt with heart issues? Michigan <a href="http://www.espn.com/mens-college-basketball/story/_/id/24796749/john-beilein-michigan-reflects-offseason-heart-surgery">Coach John Beilein</a> had a double bypass heart operation. <a href="http://406mtsports.com/college/frontier-conference/university-of-providence/providence-men-s-basketball-coach-steve-keller-on-the-mend/article_96d8b9ea-5bd4-521c-9e90-b8791313107c.html">Montana Coach Steve Keller</a> endured a heart attack just a few months ago.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the players above have happy endings. They might not be able to follow their dreams to play in the tournament or even the NBA but their life wasn’t cut short. In this month alone there were six teens that lost their lives from an undiagnosed heart condition or sudden cardiac arrest. <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/health/pennsylvania-teen-13-dies-after-sudden-cardiac-arrest-school-says">Daron Lewis Godbee</a>, 13; <a href="https://www.phillyvoice.com/newville-teen-big-spring-pennsylvania-basketball-heart-attack/">Jonathan “JT” Kuhn</a>, 16; <a href="https://www.ktbs.com/news/caddo-parish-schools-mourns-the-loss-of-domanique-jones/article_34c9d6f6-3aeb-11e9-90af-8355eee1db59.html">Domanique Jones</a>, 18; <a href="https://www.fredericksburg.com/news/local/fredericksburg/jmhs-mourns-death-of-student-who-collapsed-during-gym-class/article_2e3a087c-c281-5383-bbc3-718fd03a8e29.html">Anonymous student</a>, 16; <a href="https://nypost.com/2019/03/07/high-school-football-player-dies-after-passing-out-in-weight-room/">Jermaine Falcaer</a>, 16; and Scott Krulcik, 22.</p>
<blockquote><p>These deaths could have been prevented with heart screenings or the use of an AED device.</p></blockquote>
<p>Simon’s Heart is dedicated to changing the standard of care to screen all kids and make AED devices readily available in all schools and youth facilities. You never know if a seemingly healthy athlete could have a ticking time bomb.</p>
<p>As you continue to follow the NCAA tournament, change your perspective. Learn about the warning signs that lead to sudden cardiac arrest. Understand what an AED device is. Recognize where the closest device might be. Get your hearts checked.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-madness-of-march-2019/">The Madness of March, 2019</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Op Ed &#8211; Don&#8217;t Judge a Book</title>
		<link>/blog/op-ed-dont-judge-a-book/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2014 21:20:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Student Athlete Collapse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sudden Cardiac Death]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=6194</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This past week, many parents in the Greater Philadelphia area learned what I learned almost ten years ago – sudden cardiac arrest isn’t just an adult thing. It takes the lives of thousands of children every year. Two students, an eighth grader from Harrington Middle School in Mount Laurel, and a first grader from Andrew [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/op-ed-dont-judge-a-book/">Op Ed &#8211; Don&#8217;t Judge a Book</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This past week, many parents in the Greater Philadelphia area learned what I learned almost ten years ago – sudden cardiac arrest isn’t just an adult thing. It takes the lives of thousands of children every year.</p>
<p>Two students, an eighth grader from Harrington Middle School in Mount Laurel, and a first grader from Andrew Jackson Elementary in Philadelphia, collapsed and died from cardiac arrest.</p>
<p>In 2005, my son, Simon, died suddenly. He was a baby so most people told me it was SIDS.  Our pediatrician, however, was a bit wiser. She said, “get your hearts checked because babies don’t just die.”  Following her advice, we got tested. My wife, Phyllis, was diagnosed with a heart condition called Long QT Syndrome. It’s an arrhythmia that is linked to 15% of all SIDS deaths.</p>
<p>My heart breaks for these two families. The obvious reason is that there is a gaping void in their life now. It may narrow over time, but it will always be there. There is nothing more painful or unjust than losing a child. We all know that life is unfair, but its not supposed to be this unfair.</p>
<p>The less obvious reason is that I’ve dedicated the last nine years of my life to raising awareness about sudden cardiac arrest in children so that other parents wouldn’t have to take this path. I wanted them to be smarter so they could do a better job of protecting their children. Apparently, I failed. I let these families down.</p>
<p>Now, they’re walking in my shoes wondering how, in the 21<sup>st</sup> century, their child can die from detectable and treatable heart condition. Think about that. It’s not a rare disease. We don’t need billions of dollars to find a cure. We have the technology. We have the treatments. We just need to look. We need to be a little curious, like my pediatrician was nine years ago.</p>
<p>The Journal of American Board of Family Medicine published a study in 2012 showing that 72% of all students that died from SCA reported having symptoms from the underlying heart conditions.  I’ve met students who reported symptoms, like a racing heart or fainting. They were later diagnosed with heart conditions. Prior to their diagnosis, their symptoms were dismissed as drinking too much soda and being dehydrated, respectively. The signs were there. We almost let those kids down. We need to be a little more curious . . . a little wiser.</p>
<p>Sudden cardiac arrest is what happens when the heart stops beating, suddenly and unexpectedly. It is not a heart attack.  That’s what happens when blood can’t get to the heart. The conditions that cause sudden cardiac arrest in children come in two varieties: structural and electrical.</p>
<p>If the heart is too big or the valves are in the wrong place, the heart can’t work properly.  Alternatively, the heart rhythm can get interrupted because of an electrical abnormality.  All of these conditions are mostly genetic. They can be detected and treated.</p>
<p>Here are the warning signs:  (1) fainting or seizures during or immediately after exercise; (2) unexplained shortness of breath; (3) dizziness during exercise; (4) extreme fatigue; (5) a racing heart.  Also, parents should be aware if a family member has died suddenly and unexpectedly before the age of 50.</p>
<p>So, what’s next? The experts will debate the merits of making heart screenings a standard of care, while we continue to provide free eye and ear exams to students in schools. The lawmakers will debate the merits of placing AED devices in schools, even though each is already equipped life saving measures like fire alarms, sprinkler systems and security systems. However, starting tomorrow, we, the parents, can be more diligent and less dismissive about the warning signs of the underlying conditions.</p>
<p>My seemingly healthy baby, who was average height and weight and scored an 8 and 9 on his APGAR tests, had an undetected heart condition.  These two boys, energetic and vibrant students, described as “one of the kids everybody knew,” and “shy, funny and loveable” had undetected heart conditions. The answers may be right in front of us. We just need to look.</p>
<p>As children, we learned not to judge a book by its cover. Remember, we need to look at what’s on the inside. It’s time to realize that this saying applies to our children’s hearts too.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/op-ed-dont-judge-a-book/">Op Ed &#8211; Don&#8217;t Judge a Book</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Wichita State &#8211; Final Four &#038; Sudden Cardiac Arrest</title>
		<link>/blog/wichita-state-final-four-sudden-cardiac-arrest/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 12:59:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Student Athlete Collapse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sudden Cardiac Death]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Final Four]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NCAA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sudden cardiac arrest]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=4608</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Download Release Millions of Americans filled out their brackets and hoped that their team would survive on the Road to the Final Four. However, for some players, survival takes on a whole new meaning.  A recent study published by the American Heart Association shows that 1 out of every 3,100 NCAA Division I male basketball [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/wichita-state-final-four-sudden-cardiac-arrest/">Wichita State &#8211; Final Four &amp; Sudden Cardiac Arrest</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/Wichita-State-Release-4.2.13.pdf">Download Release</a></p>
<p>Millions of Americans filled out their brackets and hoped that their team would survive on the Road to the Final Four. However, for some players, survival takes on a whole new meaning.  A <a href="http://circ.ahajournals.org/content/early/2011/04/05/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.004622.abstract">recent study</a> published by the American Heart Association shows that 1 out of every 3,100 NCAA Division I male basketball players is at risk of dying from sudden cardiac arrest (SCA). <a href="/ways-to-give/simons-club/">Simon’s Fund</a>, a Philadelphia based organization, is trying to reduce that risk providing a free heart screening for over 300 students in an Atlanta suburb on Sunday.</p>
<p><b>Wichita State Has Firsthand Experience with Heart Conditions</b></p>
<p>Guy Alang-Ntang was recruited by the Shockers in 2008. He would have graduated last year, and with a little good fortune, played in the NBA. Instead, Alang-Ntang <a href="http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/news/story?id=2840755">dropped dead</a> of an undetected heart condition during a pick up basketball game months before starting at Wichita State.  Coach Gregg Marshall was there the night he collapsed and died.</p>
<p>Around the same time, Carl Hall, a senior forward for the Shockers, was told that his basketball career was over because he kept fainting during competition &#8212; the primary warning sign of SCA.  He took two years off from basketball, and in 2009, was prescribed medication to control his heart condition.  He made his way to Wichita State in 2011 and on Saturday night, he will lead the Shockers in their first Final Four appearance since 1965.</p>
<p>“Watching Carl Hall play in the Final Four inspires us to continue to raise awareness about the importance of heart screenings for student athletes,” says Darren Sudman, Executive Director of Simon’s Fund, who lost his son Simon to SCA. “The big difference between Alang-Ntang and Hall is that Hall got his heart checked and treated. That’s why he’s here playing.”</p>
<p><b>Local Atlanta Community Shocked by Sudden Death of Two Promising Basketball Players</b></p>
<p>Last year, in a suburb of Atlanta, Buford High School junior, <a href="http://www.ajc.com/news/sports/high-school/buford-high-basketball-player-dies-after-collapsin/nSCxt/">Adam Smith</a>, and Buford Middle School student, <a href="http://www.ajc.com/news/news/buford-player-12-collapses-during-game-and-/nTn45/">Jeremy Nelson</a>, died from SCA. They were both basketball standouts. Both may have been on the road to the Final Four. SCA ended their journeys.</p>
<p>On April 7, 2013, Simon’s Fund, working with the Cardiovascular Group in Lawrenceville, GA, will provide over 300 free heart screenings to students from the Buford and Gwinnett County School Districts.  In its eight- year history, Simon’s Fund has provided free heart screenings to 5,500 students.  One out of every 100 students checked discovers a heart condition.</p>
<p>At the screening, every student completes a medical history, has vital signs checked, and receives an ECG – a painless, non-invasive test that takes a couple of minutes. The ECG will be evaluated by local cardiologists.  Some students will receive an echocardiogram.</p>
<p>“As coaches, we spend so much time preparing our players, because we don’t we don’t to lose a game. We need to focus on sudden cardiac arrest, because losing a student athlete is much worse,” said Phil Martelli, men’s basketball coach of the St. Joseph’s University Hawks and First Vice President of the National Association of Basketball Coaches, which is meeting in Atlanta during the Final Four.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/wichita-state-final-four-sudden-cardiac-arrest/">Wichita State &#8211; Final Four &amp; Sudden Cardiac Arrest</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>HS Soccer Player, Collapses, Dies</title>
		<link>/blog/hs-soccer-player-collapses-dies/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2011 23:47:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Student Athlete Collapse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sudden Cardiac Death]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3003</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Students and staff of a Winnipeg private school are mourning a Grade 11 student athlete who collapsed during a soccer practice Wednesday night.  Grief counsellors met students at St. John&#8217;s-Ravenscourt when they arrived on Thursday morning, hours after learning of the death of Evan Dupuis.  &#8220;We made sure they were attended to,&#8221; said SJR head [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/hs-soccer-player-collapses-dies/">HS Soccer Player, Collapses, Dies</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Students and staff of a Winnipeg private school are mourning a Grade 11 student athlete who collapsed during a soccer practice Wednesday night.  Grief counsellors met students at St. John&#8217;s-Ravenscourt when they arrived on Thursday morning, hours after learning of the death of Evan Dupuis.  &#8220;We made sure they were attended to,&#8221; said SJR head of school Stephen Johnson. &#8220;Every class he was in was a class where people would be looking at an empty chair and thinking about it.&#8221;  On Thursday, the teen&#8217;s teammates gathered and offered a prayer near the field where he fell.</p>
<p>The incident occured at a varsity soccer tryout. As the practice wound down, the team was working on light sprints when the student lost consciousness.  While one parent in the audience &#8212; a doctor &#8212; rushed forward to perform CPR, a student fetched one of SJR&#8217;s two defibrillator machines. The doctor attempted to rescucitate the boy with the defibrillator until paramedics arrived. The teen was rushed to Children&#8217;s Hospital, where he died.  In a letter to parents and students, Johnson described the student as a &#8220;wonderful friend&#8221; with a &#8220;quiet, good nature and kind heart.&#8221;  Johnson praised the coaches, parents and students at the practice for taking quick and decisive steps to try to save the teen&#8217;s life. &#8220;I was very proud with the way they responded to a really shocking event,&#8221; he said, noting SJR students received training in CPR.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/manitoba/story/2011/10/06/wpg-sjr-soccer-death.html">Full story</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/hs-soccer-player-collapses-dies/">HS Soccer Player, Collapses, Dies</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Nine Year Old Dizzy, Drops Dead in School</title>
		<link>/blog/nine-year-old-dizzy-drops-dead-in-school/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[creativemms]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2011 03:26:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Student Athlete Collapse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sudden Cardiac Death]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=2041</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>By Margo Rutledge Kissell, Staff Writer Updated 1:48 AM Friday, September 23, 2011 DAYTON — Two months before 9-year-old Unique Figgers collapsed at Westwood PreK-8 School and died Tuesday, Dayton Public Schools laid off 10 school nurses — one-third of its nursing staff. Among them was the full-time nurse at Westwood, which now has one [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/nine-year-old-dizzy-drops-dead-in-school/">Nine Year Old Dizzy, Drops Dead in School</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Margo Rutledge Kissell, Staff Writer Updated 1:48 AM Friday, September 23, 2011</p>
<p>DAYTON — Two months before 9-year-old Unique Figgers collapsed at Westwood PreK-8 School and died Tuesday, Dayton Public Schools laid off 10 school nurses — one-third of its nursing staff.</p>
<p>Among them was the full-time nurse at Westwood, which now has one nurse splitting her days between the elementary school and Thurgood Marshall High School.  On Tuesday morning, when Unique collapsed after reportedly telling friends she felt dizzy, the school nurse was at Belmont High School as part of a team performing vision screenings.</p>
<p>Though the cause of death still has not been determined as investigators await test results following Wednesday’s autopsy, the girl’s sudden death has put a spotlight on the nursing staff reductions and sparked concern among some who wonder whether having a school nurse on duty that day might have changed the outcome.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.daytondailynews.com/news/dayton-news/9-year-old-girls-death-raises-nurse-staffing-concerns-1258036.html">Full story</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/nine-year-old-dizzy-drops-dead-in-school/">Nine Year Old Dizzy, Drops Dead in School</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Swimmer Dies, My High School</title>
		<link>/blog/swimmer-dies-my-high-school/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2010 00:36:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Student Athlete Collapse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sudden Cardiac Death]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1076</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I graduated from Sycamore High School in 1988.  At that time, life was simple.  Since that time, I lost a son, Sycamore has lost a student swimmer and tens of thousands of other kids have died from sudden cardiac arrest.  My heart goes out to Jose&#8217;s family. CINCINNATI, Ohio, October 27. THE Cincinnati Marlins and Sycamore High School are mourning [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/swimmer-dies-my-high-school/">Swimmer Dies, My High School</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I graduated from Sycamore High School in 1988.  At that time, life was simple.  Since that time, I lost a son, Sycamore has lost a student swimmer and tens of thousands of other kids have died from sudden cardiac arrest.  My heart goes out to Jose&#8217;s family.</p>
<p>CINCINNATI, Ohio, October 27. THE Cincinnati Marlins and Sycamore High School are mourning the loss of Jose Cerda Navarro, who died suddenly Tuesday at a swim practice.</p>
<p>According to a story on Cincinnati&#8217;s Fox TV affiliate&#8217;s website Fox19.com, Cerda collapsed on the pool deck at St. Xavier High School Tuesday after suffering a cardiac event. He was taken to a local hospital, where he was pronounced dead. The cause of death has not yet been disclosed.  Cerda was celebrating his 18th birthday on Tuesday. He was a member of the Sycamore High swimming and water polo teams, and swam for Cincinnati Marlins.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.fox19.com/Global/story.asp?S=13393164">Complete article on Fox19.com</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/swimmer-dies-my-high-school/">Swimmer Dies, My High School</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
