<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Uncategorized Archives -</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/uncategorized/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Protecting Hearts and Saving Lives</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 12:35:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/simons-fav-icon1.png</url>
	<title>Uncategorized Archives -</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>We Need a Country-Sized AED!</title>
		<link>/blog/we-need-a-country-sized-aed/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 19:05:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9310</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We need a country-sized automated external defibrillator (AED) right now. An AED is the only tool that can save someone in cardiac arrest. If needed, it delivers a lifesaving shock. If we hooked one up to this nation, the machine would run its diagnostics (like it always does) and probably make the following statement – [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/we-need-a-country-sized-aed/">We Need a Country-Sized AED!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We need a country-sized automated external defibrillator (AED) right now. An AED is the only tool that can save someone in cardiac arrest. If needed, it delivers a lifesaving shock.</p>
<p>If we hooked one up to this nation, the machine would run its diagnostics (like it always does) and probably make the following statement – “Assessing society . . . assessing society . . . shock advised.”</p>
<p>This week is CPR/AED Awareness Week. <a href="http://www.simonsheart.org/">Simon’s Heart</a>, and others like it, are supposed to capture your attention and educate you about the importance of CPR and AED devices. It’s not up for debate. These two things – a relatively easy hand motion and a $1000 device – dramatically increase the chance of surviving sudden cardiac arrest. Without them, the chance is about 12%, which is a big deal considering sudden cardiac arrest takes the lives of 350,000 adults every year.</p>
<p>But I can’t. That message has to wait. Our country is hurting. Life seems to be out of control. And, if I’m being honest, heart health is a luxury. Wow, bold statement coming from a guy who lost a son to sudden cardiac arrest, has a wife who lives with a heart condition that can result in sudden cardiac arrest, and runs an organization dedicated to preventing sudden cardiac arrest and death in children.</p>
<p>But it is. How can we expect a mother to care about an AED device at school if the walls are crumbling and there aren’t enough textbooks? Will a father of a seemingly healthy daughter take the time to learn CPR if he lost his job and is behind on rent? Is a student athlete really going to tell his coach about his racing heart if he needs that scholarship and his parents don’t have health insurance?</p>
<p>Can we really expect these families to focus on cardiac arrest? <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6324984/">Studies</a> consistently show that the rate of sudden cardiac death is higher, and occurs at younger ages in the black community. This is a very grim statistic . . . unless you are worried about food, shelter or security.</p>
<p>In the United States, <a href="https://www.kidsdata.org/topic/295/infantmortality-race/table#fmt=2749&loc=1&tf=107&ch=7,11,8,10,9,73,1436&sortColumnId=0&sortType=asc">infant mortality</a> is two times higher among blacks than whites. African American children are <a href="https://uncf.org/pages/k-12-disparity-facts-and-stats">less likely</a> to be college-ready, and more likely to be suspended than white children. African Americans are five times more likely to be incarcerated than whites. African Americans are two times more likely to be <a href="https://www.americanprogress.org/issues/economy/reports/2020/02/24/480743/persistence-black-white-unemployment-gap/">unemployed</a> than whites, and two times more likely to <a href="https://www.povertyusa.org/facts">live in poverty</a>. And, let’s not forget where we were three weeks ago – African Americans are <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/may/20/black-americans-death-rate-covid-19-coronavirus">three times</a> more likely to die from COVID-19.</p>
<p>Simon’s Heart cannot achieve its mission, and America cannot fulfill its promise in the face of such disparity and inequality. The tragic and senseless deaths of Ahmaud Arbery, Breonna Taylor and George Floyd are the latest symptoms that our society is very ill.</p>
<p>In medicine, when one function of the body is threatened, other parts of the body respond to protect and heal it. This must be our path too. We must appreciate and understand the factors that bring harm to our fellow citizens. Then, we must work tirelessly to find a cure. Not a bandaid. Not a painkiller. Not a treatment. A cure.</p>
<p>There are very few instances where our body can function without all parts in working order. I don’t know how many times we need to be reminded that society works the same way. Relationships, friendships, workplaces, sports teams, schools and communities all fare better when everyone feels valued and secure.</p>
<p>Simon’s Heart will continue to do its small part to create a more just and equal society by bringing AED devices and heart screenings to underserved communities where kids learn and play. But our focus is narrow, so we’ll look to these organizations for perspective as we work to restore the collective health of this great country.</p>
<p>Respectfully,<br />
Darren Sudman<br />
CEO, Co-Founder<br />
& Simon&#8217;s Dad</p>
<p>&#8220;It is not your responsibility to finish the work [of perfecting the world], but you are not free to desist from it either.&#8221; Pirkei Avot 2:16</p>
<p><strong>Criminal Justice Reform<br />
</strong><a href="https://fight.org/programs/institute-for-community-justice/">Institute for Community Justice</a> (Philly)<br />
<a href="https://www.sentencingproject.org/about-us/">The Sentencing Project</a> (National)</p>
<p><strong>Police Conduct</strong><br />
<a href="https://www.joincampaignzero.org/#vision">Campaign Zero</a> (National)<br />
<a href="https://noblenational.org/about-us/">NOBLE</a> (National)</p>
<p><strong>Education Inequality</strong><br />
<a href="https://www.steppingstonescholars.org/">Stepping Stones </a>(Philly)<br />
<a href="https://edtrust.org/">The Education Trust </a> (National)</p>
<p><strong>Food Insecurity<br />
</strong><a href="https://www.philabundance.org/about">Philadbundance</a> (Philly)<br />
<a href="https://www.nokidhungry.org/">No Kid Hungry</a> (National)</p>
<p><strong>Infant Mortality<br />
</strong><a href="https://birthequity.org/">National Birth Equity Collaborative</a> (National)</p>
<p><strong>Social Justice</strong><br />
<a href="https://blacklivesmatter.com/about/">Black Lives Matter</a> (National)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/juliawuench/2020/06/02/first-listen-then-learn-anti-racism-resources-for-white-people/#1115142e16ee">Forbes Magazine</a> has compiled a list of resources that promote empathy and understanding around the issues of racism and inequality.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/we-need-a-country-sized-aed/">We Need a Country-Sized AED!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Simon&#8217;s Heart Primer</title>
		<link>/blog/a-simons-heart-primer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2015 20:37:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9317</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Thank you for wanting to learn more about Simon&#8217;s Heart. Our organization is approaching its second decade, so there&#8217;s a lot to share. Curious about our impact? We hope that the narrative below provides insight into who we are, why we got started, and what we hope to accomplish. For a quick overview of our [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/a-simons-heart-primer/">A Simon&#8217;s Heart Primer</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thank you for wanting to learn more about Simon&#8217;s Heart. Our organization is approaching its second decade, so there&#8217;s a lot to share. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rmfuKSqIeps">Curious about our impact</a>?</p>
<p>We hope that the narrative below provides insight into who we are, why we got started, and what we hope to accomplish.</p>
<p>For a quick overview of our history, look at <a href="/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/History-of-SIMONS-Heart_V5.pdf">the timeline.</a>  As you learn more about our journey, one thing should stand out &#8211; everything we do is <a href="https://479eg1tq8sc3ni9ow274qh71-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/SIMONS-Heart_The-How-and-Why_FINAL_No-Crops.pdf">rooted in science</a>.</p>
<h3><b><u>The Beginning &#8211; Tragedy and Uncertainty</u></b></h3>
<div>Simon’s Fund (a.k.a Simon’s Heart) began sometime in 2005 following the sudden and unexpected death of Simon Sudman. He was a seemingly healthy three-month old.  He was average for height and weight. He scored 8 and 9 on the APGAR. He smiled for the first time at 47 days. He died in his sleep forty days later. The Sudmans knew they had to do something. They could focus on the unexpected death of infants. They could focus on improving the lives of children who are born to families without resources (since Simon would have been very comfortable). Friends of the family donated $20,000 to support the cause, whatever it would become.</div>
<h3><b><u>Curiosity and Direction</u></b></h3>
<div>The initial hunch was SIDS, but their wise and curious pediatricians told the family to get their hearts checked because “babies just don’t die.” As a result, Phyllis was diagnosed with Long QT Syndrome &#8211; an arrhythmia that has been linked to up to <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5348737/">12% of SIDS deaths</a>  It is also one of a handful of conditions that can cause children, particularly <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29931253/">student athletes</a> to collapse and die. The cause was born &#8211; prevent a family from losing a child to a detectable and treatable heart condition.</div>
<div></div>
<div>There are two ways to approach sudden cardiac arrest and death in children. Prevent the condition before it causes harm (primary prevention) or be prepared to help when the harm occurs (secondary prevention). The board felt that primary prevention was less crowded, more challenging and likely more impactful.</div>
<div></div>
<div>The desire was to raise money and fund another organization that was focused on preventing sudden death in children. In 2005, there were two such groups. After some due diligence, we learned that these groups used to be one &#8211; there was a falling out. We didn’t want to donate our friends’ money to either group.  Hence, Simon’s Fund was born (in 2018, the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HV1MiV7d98E">name was changed to Simon&#8217;s Heart</a>).</div>
<h3><b><u>Our First Program</u></b></h3>
<div>The first fundraiser was held in January 2006 at Normandy Farm. It raised over $100,000. The first program &#8211; a heart screening &#8211; was held at the World Cafe Live.  We partnered with a cardiologist at CHOP.  About eighty kids showed up for a concert and screening. The concept was born.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Why heart screenings? Anecdotally, we know that 1 out of 300 students discover heart conditions at youth heart screenings. <a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Drezner_ECG-Screening-in-NCAA-Athletes_AJC-2016.pdf">Scientifically</a>, we know that a physical exam, medical history and ECG is the most effective way to detect heart conditions. Simon&#8217;s Heart co-funded this research with the NCAA.</div>
<div></div>
<div>The first school based heart screening was held at the Colonial School District. Five students <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A1Y-_H1TlCc">discovered heart conditions</a>.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Over the next few years, Simon&#8217;s Heart and Dr. Vicki Vetter continued to conduct screenings in partnership with schools. The goal of this relationship was to produce research. Simon&#8217;s Heart donated $150,000 to this effort. The research project never got funding and Simon&#8217;s Heart wanted to expand the number of physicians and institutions participating in the effort. This &#8220;exclusive&#8221; relationship came to an end. By 2012, Simon&#8217;s Heart was conducting up to six heart screenings a year and had a network of 40+ cardiologist volunteers. This <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HJLWtIG6hFw">screening model</a> continues to this day.</div>
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Focusing on the Big Kids</strong></span></h3>
<p>Simon was three months old when he died. There was no story. A few months later, Vince Bernardo, a freshman at Shippensburg University, who grew up less than a mile from Simon, died on the football field. <a href="https://shipraiders.com/news/2008/11/18/FB_1118080441.aspx?path=fb">There was a story</a>. This disparity revealed a reality. It is more likely for there to be a discussion about sudden cardiac arrest and death when a big kid dies, particularly if s/he is a student athlete. It is much easier to amplify a conversation than start one. Once we make is safer for the big kids, it&#8217;ll be easier to make it safer for the little kids. Hence, our focus remains on middle and high school-aged students (for now).</p>
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;">The Second Initiative</span></h3>
<div>In 2011, <a href="https://www.npr.org/2011/02/02/133437361/doctors-throw-flags-on-high-school-concussions">NPR ran a story</a> about Zachary Lystedt, a high school football player whose concussion left him paralyzed. The family passed a law in Washington requiring coaches, parents and students to learn about the warning signs. It also required the removal of symptomatic players. With the help of the NFL, within three years, every state adopted a similar law. After studying this law, Simon&#8217;s Heart drafted its own and headed to Harrisburg to meet with lawmakers who had lost a student in their District. Representative Mike Vereb learned about Akhir Frazier. Soon thereafter, a bill was introduced. One year later, <a href="https://www.inquirer.com/philly/news/breaking/20120530_Gov__Corbett_signs_bill_to_protect_student_athletes_from_sudden_death.html">Governor Corbett</a>, signed the Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act (Act 59) into law.</div>
<div></div>
<div>The Act has three prongs: (1) parents must read and sign a form prior to their child playing interscholastic sports; (2) coaches must be trained on the warning signs of sudden cardiac arrest; and (3) coaches must remove players who are symptomatic and they can only return after being cleared by a licensed medical professional. Following the passage, Simon&#8217;s Heart began reaching out to lawmakers and organizations in other states. To date, fourteen states have <a href="/protect-this-heart/advocacy/sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/">enacted similar legislation</a>.</div>
<div></div>
<div>This law opened opportunities to reach coaches and student athletes. The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ws863qgNtgk">Philadelphia Six</a> filmed a PSA, and a licensing agreement with the <a href="https://nfhslearn.com/courses/sudden-cardiac-arrest">National Federation of State High School Associations</a>, made our educational <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aO0KfD52VMk&t=4s">video</a> the primary resource for coach education. It has been used over 1,000,000 times by coaches in all fifty states.</div>
<div></div>
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Changing a Standard of Care</span></h3>
<p>By the time the law was passed, Simon&#8217;s Heart had screened about 5,000 students. Two things were very clear. It was so rewarding to help a family find an undetected heart condition so they could live a healthier and safe life. It was also impossible for Simon&#8217;s Heart to screen every student in Philadelphia, let alone Pennsylvania or the United States. To get every student screened, Simon&#8217;s Heart would need to help change the standard of care. To accomplish this, it would have to help facilitate research.</p>
<p>Simon&#8217;s Heart began work on a digital registry that could be used to streamline the heart screening process and sharing data with researchers. If researchers could avoid having to raise money and gather data, they could analyze and publish more quickly and efficiently. With guidance from companies like DataMed, Amps LLC, ERT and Mortara Instruments, <a href="/protect-this-heart/heartbytes/">HeartBytes was built</a>. Pulse Infoframe developed the data registry and platform architecture. INFINITT NA donated the image software.</p>
<p>The goal is to crowdsource data by working with other screening organizations and provide the de-identified data to researchers, free of charge. To date, the data has been used to publish seven abstracts for national medical conferences.</p>
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;">The Impact of Sports</span></h3>
<p>Athletics creates passion and captures attention. It also increases the risk of sudden cardiac arrest. SCA is the <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22585265/">#1 cause of death</a> of student athletes.  Simon&#8217;s Heart has worked hard to identify space in the world of sport and use it to deliver a lifesaving message.</p>
<p>In 2013, two students collapsed and died in Buford outside of Atlanta. This was also the host city of the Final Four. Simon&#8217;s Heart traveled to Atlanta to conduct a heart screening and bring awareness to the cause. NCAA Division I male basketball players face the greatest risk of sudden cardiac arrest. <a href="https://thephiladelphiacitizen.org/guest-commentary-wheres-the-heart-in-the-final-four/">To this day</a>, Simon&#8217;s Heart continues to conduct a heart screening during the Final Four.</p>
<p>Simon&#8217;s Heart was selected as an Eagles Care partner in 2014. For one year, the organization participated in events and was supported by the Philadephia Eagles. AED Madness was launched in 2016 with St. Joe&#8217;s, Temple, Drexel, LaSalle and Penn. Every year, fans are educated about SCA at a home game and an AED is donated to a local youth facility. In 2017, the Philadelphia Flyers and Simon&#8217;s Heart launched Czech for Hearts which ultimately became the Overtime Challenge.  Through this program, Simon&#8217;s Heart has received over $50,000 and has donated thirty AED devices to local youth facilities.</p>
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Secondary Prevention</strong></span></h3>
<p>After years of focusing on the prevention of sudden cardiac arrest, Simon&#8217;s Heart began to focus on the prevention of sudden cardiac death too. Heart screenings, data gathering and advocating for lifesaving legislation continue, but these initiatives focused specifically on saving lives after cardiac arrest occurs. We created new ways to distribute AED devices and educate students about chest compressions.</p>
<p>The Chain of Survival relay debuted at Simon Says Run and appeared at a variety of locations like Girl Scouts camp and a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hlZY6X6sgFw">Philadelphia Union</a> game.  Students are divided into teams and required to complete three steps in the chain of survival &#8211; 911, CPR and AED. The race takes about five minutes. Saving lives is serious business. Learning how to do it can be fun.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.gotaed.org/">GotAED</a> was launched in 2017 after Simon&#8217;s Heart was unable to fulfill all of the requests for AED donations. The organization was surprised to learn how many groups seeking an AED device would give up when grants were not available (and there aren&#8217;t many grants). In an effort to facilitate the placement of more AEDs, our crowdfunding site was born. Now, within minutes, any youth related organization can start a campaign for a fixed (and really low) price and begin soliciting donations. Upon fulfillment, an AED and cabinet are shipped directly to the facility. To date, fifty AED devices have been sent to venues in 15 states.</p>
<p>The CPR Jukebox debuted at <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ApcovZRWDn8">MusikFest</a> in 2019. It was wildly successful.  To appreciate this statement, you must understand that Simon&#8217;s Heart has always been the loneliest booth at any event. People do not want to contemplate their child&#8217;s mortality or learn about CPR. With a ten foot inflatable, kick balls and a 100+ song playlist, hundreds of children and families picked a song and pushed on a ball. Learning hands-only CPR was a byproduct of having fun. In May 2020, in the midst of the quarantine, Simon&#8217;s Heart hosted a virtual CPR Jukebox Marathon. For 12 hours, 144 students from four countries pushed for ten minutes on a ball. It was hosted by local celebrities and raised $5,000.</p>
<h3><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Investing in the Mission</strong></span></h3>
<p>The first fundraiser was held in January 2006 at Normandy Farm. It raised over $100,000. It would become known as Simon&#8217;s Soiree. Except for three years during the recession, Simon&#8217;s Soiree continues and generates 60% of the organization&#8217;s revenue. During the recession, the event became Simon&#8217;s Day, a day of entertainment and activities for families. It was hosted at the Ambler Theater. Simon Says Run ran from 2014 &#8211; 2017. It was a 5K and family walk. Simon Says Golf was introduced in 2017 and continues to this day. Simon&#8217;s Heart has an annual budget of $500,000.  Through events, partnerships, grants and donations, it will continue checking hearts and saving lives.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/a-simons-heart-primer/">A Simon&#8217;s Heart Primer</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>AHA Report on ECG Screening Drops the Ball</title>
		<link>/blog/aha-panel-issues-one-sided-bias-report/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2014 01:44:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=6457</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Screen Across America is a consortium of organizations that provide youth heart screenings in the United States. The group includes integrated health care systems, hospitals, universities, private medical practices, businesses and foundations. Based on our experiences in screening hundreds of thousands of children, and changing thousands of lives, we believe that youth heart screenings with [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/aha-panel-issues-one-sided-bias-report/">AHA Report on ECG Screening Drops the Ball</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Screen Across America is a consortium of organizations that provide youth heart screenings in the United States. The group includes integrated health care systems, hospitals, universities, private medical practices, businesses and foundations. Based on our experiences in screening hundreds of thousands of children, and changing thousands of lives, we believe that youth heart screenings with electrocardiograms (ECG) are good medicine today.</p>
<p>Thousands of children die from sudden cardiac arrest every year. The American Academy of Pediatrics suggests that this number is 2,000, but we believe it to be higher. In October 2013, the NIH and CDC launched a landmark national registry to track the number of youth sudden deaths because Google and insurance records underestimate the true total.</p>
<p>Sudden cardiac arrest is the #1 medical cause of death of student athletes.</p>
<p>Approximately, one out of every 100 children that get screened discovers a heart condition. These conditions can cause our children to drop dead tomorrow, or cause them significant health problems in their adulthood years.</p>
<p>A significant number of students are diagnosed with hypertension and obesity at our screenings. Early identification of these risk factors and conditions save lives and money.</p>
<p>The cost to perform an ECG at a screening is approximately $25.</p>
<p>In addition, there is some very promising research.</p>
<p>ECG exams are more effective at catching undetected heart conditions. In 2013, 2,471 NCAA athletes received a standard pre-participation sports physical and ECG exam. Seven students were diagnosed with serious heart conditions, yet only of two of them had an abnormal history and/or physical exam (<a href="http://www.amssm.org/News-Release-Article.php?NewsID=67">http://www.amssm.org/News-Release-Article.php?NewsID=67</a>)</p>
<p>Responsible ECG screening criteria drastically reduces the number of false positives. Last year, a group of researchers screened 1,197 students and young adults using the Seattle Criteria. As a result, the false positive rate decreased from 17% to 4% (Br J Sports Med doi: 10.1136/bjsports-2013-092420).</p>
<p>Adding an ECG exam to sports physicals does not create anxiety for students. In 2013, 1,506 high school athletes received sports physicals with an ECG exam. The students reported that the type of screening did not impact their anxiety level. In fact, most students indicated that the ECG was a good addition (J Am Coll Cardiol. 2014; 63(12_S): doi:10.1016/S0735-1097(14)61637-5)</p>
<p>In Italy, where all student athletes receive an ECG exam, the incidence of sudden cardiac arrest in students was reduced by 89%. (J Am Coll Cardiol. 2008 52(24) doi:10.1016/j.jacc.2008.06.053)</p>
<p>We continue to be inspired by the earlier movements who have fought for safer and smarter medical practices. One day, we hope that opponents of youth heart screenings will engage in youth heart screenings to gather and use scientific-based data to form the basis of their objections. When lives are at stake, there is no place for opinion, prejudice or agendas.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/aha-panel-issues-one-sided-bias-report/">AHA Report on ECG Screening Drops the Ball</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dead Man Floating</title>
		<link>/blog/dead-man-floating/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2013 22:10:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=5069</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Last week, I flew from Philadelphia to Nashville to Raleigh to Tampa to Philadelphia. I met with lawmakers about the sudden cardiac arrest prevention act. We found lawmakers in Tennessee and North Carolina to sponsor the bill. We&#8217;re pretty excited. I heard airline attendants on four separate occasions tell us that our seats turn into [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/dead-man-floating/">Dead Man Floating</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last week, I flew from Philadelphia to Nashville to Raleigh to Tampa to Philadelphia. I met with lawmakers about the sudden cardiac arrest prevention act. We found lawmakers in Tennessee and North Carolina to sponsor the bill. We&#8217;re pretty excited.</p>
<p>I heard airline attendants on four separate occasions tell us that our seats turn into a flotation device in the event of a water emergency. That&#8217;s interesting . . . but I&#8217;m not flying over water on these trips, I thought.</p>
<p><a href="http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Virgin-America-Airline.jpg"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-5074" src="https://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Virgin-America-Airline.jpg" alt="Virgin-America-Airline" width="496" height="330" /></a></p>
<p>Then I wondered, how many times do planes crash in the water? The answer must be lots since this instruction is mandatory on EVERY flight. Surprise! According to the <a href="http://aviation.globalincidentmap.com/">Global Incident Map</a>, there were no crashes into water in the US last year (there were no crashes at all, actually).</p>
<p>What other message could the attendants share that could save lives in the midst of a crisis on board? Here&#8217;s a clue. Over the past week, I read three headlines:  <a href="http://www.11alive.com/news/article/299548/40/Delta-employees-save-colleague-after-heart-attack">Delta Employee Saved by AED</a>, <a href="http://india.nydailynews.com/business/404796af7d7985ab24248d368685e343/passenger-dies-of-mid-air-cardiac-arrest">Passenger Dies Mid Air of Cardiac Arrest While Flying</a>, and <a href="http://www.oregonlive.com/health/index.ssf/2013/07/cardiac_arrest_at_29000_feet_y.html">Cardiac Arrest at 29,000 Feet</a>. So, for the week of July 21, the airlines experienced AT LEAST three instances of sudden cardiac arrest.</p>
<p>Could the attendants teach us how to use an AED in those 15 seconds? Yep. Last week, would that instruction have been more useful than the floating seats? Yep. However, that simple instruction could have a much greater societal impact. AEDs are in many public places, so this would actually be knowledge that passengers could take out into the world. They could save lives at sporting events, the mall, in parks and at schools. In my 42 years, I haven&#8217;t seen floating cushions in any of these places.</p>
<p>It seems that the odds of dying on a plane from SCA are significantly higher than crashing into a body of water. So let&#8217;s change that speech and talk to passengers about AED devices. Otherwise, we run the risk of someone dying of sudden cardiac arrest before they hit the water.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/dead-man-floating/">Dead Man Floating</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Student-Athletes Receive Free Heart Screenings</title>
		<link>/blog/student-athletes-receive-free-heart-screenings/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[creativemms]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2011 15:24:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1968</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>KABB Fox San Antonio &#8211; August 14, 2011 One family hopes its heartbreak can prevent others from losing an active teen to sudden cardiac death. It&#8217;s free and it&#8217;s fast.  &#8220;Our goal is to be faster than Starbucks,&#8221; says cardiologist Dr. George Rodgers.  It’s painless and non-invasive &#8212; high-tech heart screenings for hundreds of San [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/student-athletes-receive-free-heart-screenings/">Student-Athletes Receive Free Heart Screenings</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<address>KABB Fox San Antonio &#8211; August 14, 2011</address>
<p>One family hopes its heartbreak can prevent others from losing an active teen to sudden cardiac death.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s free and it&#8217;s fast.  &#8220;Our goal is to be faster than Starbucks,&#8221; says cardiologist Dr. George Rodgers.  It’s painless and non-invasive &#8212; high-tech heart screenings for hundreds of San Antonio student-athletes checking for possibly deadly genetic heart conditions.</p>
<p>&#8220;Anything to prevent another parent to have to go through what we went through,&#8221; says Dore Koontz.</p>
<p>Three years ago, 18-year-old Central Catholic student-athlete August Koontz died suddenly. Strong and fit, August showed no symptoms. But doctors said he died from an inherited disorder &#8212; a thickening of the heart muscle.</p>
<p>&#8220;You worry about drugs, you worry about alcohol, you worry about car wrecks,” says Koontz. “Not once did we ever think of my son dying from natural causes, from a heart condition.&#8221;</p>
<p>These disorders are hard to pick up from a physical examination and don&#8217;t necessarily impair a student&#8217;s athletic abilities.</p>
<p>&#8220;But make them vulnerable to developing very serious rhythm problems when they get that surge of adrenaline when they&#8217;re participating in sports,&#8221; says Dr. Rodgers.</p>
<p>About one out of every 180 students is as at high-risk for sudden cardiac death. But these conditions are very easy to pick up with an electrocardiogram, which traces the heart &#8212; or with an ultrasound of the heart. Thanks to newly founded AugustHeart Foundation, both tools are being used on these students. Both give immediate results.</p>
<p><a href="http://foxsanantonio.com/newsroom/top_stories/videos/vid_7096.shtml">FULL STORY AND VIDEO</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/student-athletes-receive-free-heart-screenings/">Student-Athletes Receive Free Heart Screenings</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hospital to Start Free Heart Screenings for HS Athletes</title>
		<link>/blog/hospital-to-start-free-heart-screenings-for-hs-athletes/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[creativemms]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2011 18:54:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1949</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Miami Children&#8217;s Hospital Program starts soon By Diana Gonzalez &#124;  Friday, Jul 29, 2011 Carolina Richardson just started as a dancer at Florida International University, and she was at Miami Children’s Hospital on Friday getting an EKG as part of her physical for college athletics. Richardson had a disease in early childhood that can [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/hospital-to-start-free-heart-screenings-for-hs-athletes/">Hospital to Start Free Heart Screenings for HS Athletes</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Miami Children&#8217;s Hospital Program starts soon<br />
By Diana Gonzalez |  Friday, Jul 29, 2011</p>
<p>Carolina Richardson just started as a dancer at Florida International University, and she was at Miami Children’s Hospital on Friday getting an EKG as part of her physical for college athletics.</p>
<p>Richardson had a disease in early childhood that can affect the heart, but says she never underwent this testing as a dancer for her high school.</p>
<p>“I had a physical done but not an EKG. Yeah, they never asked me for it.  It wasn’t required,” she said.</p>
<p>Last year, 110 high school athletes across the country died of sudden cardiac arrest, that’s about one every three days. Miami Children’s Hospital believes all high school athletes should have EKG screenings at no cost to the students or their families. And so, it will soon launch a brand new program to make that possible.</p>
<p>One of the hospital’s Health on Wheels trucks will be making the rounds at area high schools.  Also, student athletes who want free EKGs can go to the hospital’s five outpatient centers in Miami-Dade and Broward.</p>
<p>Dr. Anthony Rossi is the medical director for the Cardiac Intensive Care Program at Miami Children’s Hospital.</p>
<p>“The science of trying to figure out who’s at greatest risk hasn’t been perfected yet.  But we do believe athletics triggers some of the fatal problems,” he said.</p>
<p>The American Heart Association does not recommend routine EKGs for all high school athletes. Long Q T Syndrome, a problem with the electrical conduction of the heart, can be detected with this kind of screening. The syndrome affects about 1 in 5000 children, boys more often than girls. It’s more common among African Americans and it is treatable.</p>
<p>“You could have someone for 15 years be completely asymptomatic but have a Long QT, and it’s like a time bomb.  The first time you have an episode can be associated with sudden death,” he said.</p>
<p>While the volunteer cardiologists are targeting athletes, free EKGs will also be available to students who don’t play sports.</p>
<p>“The problem is you’ll screen a lot of patients and you probably won’t find a lot of people who are at risk, but preventing one death in a child who then has the opportunity to live a completely normal life, we think is worth it” Rossi said.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/hospital-to-start-free-heart-screenings-for-hs-athletes/">Hospital to Start Free Heart Screenings for HS Athletes</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Facebook Helps Diagnose Heart Condition</title>
		<link>/blog/facebook-helps-diagnose-heart-condition/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[creativemms]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2011 20:15:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1922</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This is a great story about how raising awareness and leveraging the internet, in this case, facebook, can save a life.  Facebook Saved My Son&#8217;s Life</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/facebook-helps-diagnose-heart-condition/">Facebook Helps Diagnose Heart Condition</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is a great story about how raising awareness and leveraging the internet, in this case, facebook, can save a life.  </em></p>
<p><a href="http://www.slate.com/id/2297933/pagenum/all">Facebook Saved My Son&#8217;s Life</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/facebook-helps-diagnose-heart-condition/">Facebook Helps Diagnose Heart Condition</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>PA State Rep. Vereb introduces Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act</title>
		<link>/blog/pa-state-rep-vereb-introduces-sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[creativemms]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2011 21:37:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1879</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This is very exciting and a very proud moment for us at Simon&#8217;s Fund.  You rarely get a warning sign with Sudden Cardiac Arrest &#8211; but fainting is the # 1 indicator.  If this legislation passes, we will have a protocol in place for handling a child that faints, feels dizzy or has an elevated [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/pa-state-rep-vereb-introduces-sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/">PA State Rep. Vereb introduces Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This is very exciting and a very proud moment for us at Simon&#8217;s Fund.  You rarely get a warning sign with Sudden Cardiac Arrest &#8211; but fainting is the # 1 indicator.  If this legislation passes, we will have a protocol in place for handling a child that faints, feels dizzy or has an elevated heart rate with shortness of breath.  Hopefully this will shift the thought process away from &#8220;you must be dehydrated&#8221; or &#8220;maybe you didn&#8217;t eat enough today&#8221; towards the more appropriate response of &#8220;it may be nothing, but let&#8217;s get you checked out by a cardiologist.&#8221;  We are also seeking parallel legislation in the Senate&#8230;.Please help us by contacting your Senator and/or Representative &#8211; a list can be found here: </em><a href="http://www.legis.state.pa.us/cfdocs/legis/home/findyourlegislator/">http://www.legis.state.pa.us/cfdocs/legis/home/findyourlegislator/</a>.</p>
<p>By MELISSA BROOKS<br />
Times Herald Staff</p>
<p>NORRISTOWN — State Rep. Mike Vereb, R-150th Dist., delivered a bill to the House floor Wednesday that aims to prevent sudden cardiac arrest in student athletes.</p>
<p>The Sudden Cardiac Arrest (SCA) Prevention Act, or House Bill 1610, currently has 40 co-sponsors. The legislation calls for student athletes, who either exhibit signs or symptoms of SCA while participating in their sport or who have exhibited signs or symptoms of SCA prior to or following an athletic activity, to be removed from play until they provide written approval from an appropriate health care professional.</p>
<p>In addition, the SCA Prevention Act will require the health and education departments to educate athletes, parents and coaches on SCA and to provide materials developed by organizations such as Parent Heart Watch and Sudden Arrhythmia Death Syndromes.</p>
<p>“There have been too many news stories of student athletes who have died way before their time as a result of sudden cardiac arrest,” Vereb wrote in an emailed statement.</p>
<p>“As a father of three — all of whom participate in school sports — I know the fear a parent feels when their child is hurt during practice or a game. The safety and well-being of our children needs to be a top priority. My legislation ensures that appropriate measures are taken when a student athlete shows symptoms of distress and will help identify health problems before it is too late.”</p>
<p>Behind the bill is local nonprofit organization Simon’s Fund, founded by husband and wife Darren and Phyllis Sudman, whose seemingly healthy 3-month-old baby boy, Simon, died in January 2005 of sudden cardiac arrest. Since then, Simon’s Fund has provided heart screenings to more than 2,100 children in the Greater Philadelphia area, saving the lives of 20 children.</p>
<p>In August 2010 Akhir Frazier collapsed at the Hank Gathers Recreation Center in North Philly and died four days later. It was later determined Frazier had an inherited heart defect called cardiomyopathy, and that’s what led to his sudden cardiac arrest.</p>
<p>His death prompted Simon’s Fund to set up a free heart screening at Norristown Area High School, where the former basketball standout would have begun his junior year.</p>
<p>Sudman said 227 students received an ECG (electrocardiogram) exam on Oct. 30, 2010, and the Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia cardio team on site at the school recommended 13 students receive further testing. One of them was 13-year-old Kyle McCabe of Norristown, who as a result of the screening learned he has long QT syndrome, the heart rhythm disorder that caused baby Simon’s death.</p>
<p><a href="http://timesherald.com/articles/2011/06/16/news/doc4dfa5d2e571d6583021148.txt?viewmode=fullstory">FULL STORY</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/pa-state-rep-vereb-introduces-sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/">PA State Rep. Vereb introduces Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is it possible that cats receive better health care than our children?</title>
		<link>/blog/is-it-possible-that-cats-receive-better-health-care-than-our-children/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[creativemms]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 21:00:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1861</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I took my cat to the veterinary today to have his teeth cleaned (yeah what of it) and an amazing thing happened while reading the informative pamphlet regarding the dental package.  At the Ardmore Animal Hospital, they complete a physical examination on the morning of the scheduled procedure.  From the pamphlet, &#8220;The physical examination is [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/is-it-possible-that-cats-receive-better-health-care-than-our-children/">Is it possible that cats receive better health care than our children?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I took my cat to the veterinary today to have his teeth cleaned (yeah what of it) and an amazing thing happened while reading the informative pamphlet regarding the dental package.  At the Ardmore Animal Hospital, they complete a physical examination on the morning of the scheduled procedure.  From the pamphlet, &#8220;The physical examination is a comprehensive check of all major body systems.  An electrocardiogram (EKG) will be performed to check for any abnormal heart rhythms.&#8221;</p>
<p>My cat, which was rescued from a shelter three years ago, just had an EKG exam to check for any heart abnormalities.  The American Animal Hospital Association has not complained about false positives, nor about the cost.  Speaking of which, upon receiving my bill I asked the receptionist if she had the ability to break down the charges in greater detail &#8211; specifically could she tell me how much the EKG cost.</p>
<p>$23.00.  I&#8217;ll let that sink in&#8230;.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, our children are still dying from detectable conditions that lead to sudden cardiac arrest.  The media will tragically miss the vast majority of these stories, and will only highlight a select few.  Of those they cover, inevitably they will solicit the input of a physician who will lazily site cost or false positives as reasons against large scale EKG testing.  They will offer these reasons and mention &#8220;lack of data&#8221; as validation.  If you don&#8217;t have data, I&#8217;m not sure how you can discuss &#8220;false positives&#8221; but that&#8217;s a topic for a different rant.</p>
<p>At Simon&#8217;s Fund, we will continue to screen children and collect irrefutable data.  We will continue to develop screening models that are cost effective.  We will continue to provide awareness about sudden cardiac arrest.</p>
<p>In the meantime, if you need an EKG I guess you should take your children to the vet.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/is-it-possible-that-cats-receive-better-health-care-than-our-children/">Is it possible that cats receive better health care than our children?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Student Drowns &#8211; Could Be Heart Related . . .</title>
		<link>/blog/student-drowns-could-be-heart-related/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2010 22:06:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=798</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>COLUMBUS, Ohio (CBS/WBNS) Rico Butler, a Hilliard Davidson High School student and star athlete, drowned Tuesday night while swimming in a Columbus, Ohio quarry. Police recovered the 17-year-old&#8217;s body from a quarry near Dublin and Trabue roads shortly before noon, according to CBS affiliate WBNS. Butler was swimming with several friends when he disappeared beneath [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/student-drowns-could-be-heart-related/">Student Drowns &#8211; Could Be Heart Related . . .</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>COLUMBUS, Ohio (CBS/WBNS)</strong> Rico Butler, a Hilliard Davidson High School student and star athlete, drowned Tuesday night while swimming in a Columbus, Ohio quarry.</p>
<p>Police recovered the 17-year-old&#8217;s body from a quarry near Dublin and Trabue roads shortly before noon, according to CBS affiliate WBNS.</p>
<p>Butler was swimming with several friends when he disappeared beneath the water. One of the teenagers told the station that Butler was playing in the water and joked that he was about to drown. Then, she said, he disappeared.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/student-drowns-could-be-heart-related/">Student Drowns &#8211; Could Be Heart Related . . .</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
