<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>AED Save Archives -</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/aed-save/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Protecting Hearts and Saving Lives</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2021 18:27:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/simons-fav-icon1.png</url>
	<title>AED Save Archives -</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Club saves lives while fundraising during pandemic</title>
		<link>/blog/club-saves-lives-while-fundraising-during-pandemic/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarita Rajpoot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 12:55:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AED Save]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9926</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>WHAT: Colonial Soccer Club is taking steps to protect hearts and place AEDs throughout the Plymouth Meeting, Whitemarsh, and Conshohocken region. The Louis T. Savino, III Foundation and Simon’s Heart collaborated with Colonial Soccer to fund 9 AEDs to 13 soccer fields. AEDs and CPR Education will be provided during the Bill Lapp Soccer Tournament. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/club-saves-lives-while-fundraising-during-pandemic/">Club saves lives while fundraising during pandemic</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>WHAT: Colonial Soccer Club is taking steps to protect hearts and place AEDs throughout the Plymouth Meeting, Whitemarsh, and Conshohocken region. The Louis T. Savino, III Foundation and Simon’s Heart collaborated with Colonial Soccer to fund 9 AEDs to 13 soccer fields. AEDs and CPR Education will be provided during the Bill Lapp Soccer Tournament. Athletes will grab a ball, pick a song, and push to the beat. Surprise, they’re learning CPR! The Club looks to deepen their fundraising efforts to provide 3 more AEDs and further heart safety education in the community before the end of 2021.</p>
<p>WHO: Colonial Soccer Club | Louis T. Savino, III Foundation | Simon’s Heart | 5,000 spectators</p>
<p>WHEN: Saturday October 16th, 2021 | Bill Lapp Soccer Tournament</p>
<p>WHERE: Victory Fields | 201 E Germantown Pike, Colonial Dr, Lafayette Hill, PA</p>
<p>WHY: Sudden Cardiac Arrest isn’t just an adult thing. It is the #1 cause of death of student athletes and takes the lives of thousands of students every year. Colonial Soccer Club partners with The Louis T. Savino, III Foundation and Simon’s Heart to protect<br />
hearts and save lives.</p>
<p>COLONIAL SOCCER CLUB | A note from Brian Cammarota, Health + Safety Coordinator | “It has been a dream of mine to assure that every heart is protected every day on Colonial Soccer Club fields. Thank you to the Louis T. Savino, III Foundation and Simon’s Heart.” <a href="https://www.colonialsoccerclub.org/">www.colonialsoccerclub.org</a></p>
<p>LOUIS T. SAVINO, III FOUNDATION was founded in memory of Louis who died suddenly in 2000 at the age of 15 on a soccer field from an undetected heart condition. An AED could have saved his life. The Foundation is dedicated to increasing awareness of, and preventing, sudden cardiac death (SCD) in youth. <a href="http://www.savinofoundation.org/">www.savinofoundation.org</a></p>
<p>SIMON’S HEART is a 501(c)(3) founded in memory of 3 month old Simon Sudman who died suddenly from an undetected heart condition. The organization is committed to a future in which parents and communities don’t lose children to detectable and treatable heart conditions. <a href="/">www.simonsheart.org</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/club-saves-lives-while-fundraising-during-pandemic/">Club saves lives while fundraising during pandemic</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Jenn and Rob Shockley</title>
		<link>/blog/jenn-and-rob-shockley/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2019 19:52:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AED Save]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9052</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Timing is everything. We met Jenn in 2019. She wasted no time helping us market ideas (her specialty), find sponsors and connect with the youth lacrosse community. We&#8217;ve been completely inspired by her enthusiasm and effort. We are lucky that Robb and she have agreed to serve as co-chairs for Simon&#8217;s Soiree 2020. This year&#8217;s [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/jenn-and-rob-shockley/">Jenn and Rob Shockley</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Timing is everything. We met Jenn in 2019. She wasted no time helping us market ideas (her specialty), find sponsors and connect with the youth lacrosse community. We&#8217;ve been completely inspired by her enthusiasm and effort. We are lucky that Robb and she have agreed to serve as co-chairs for Simon&#8217;s Soiree 2020. This year&#8217;s going to be pretty amazing.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/jenn-and-rob-shockley/">Jenn and Rob Shockley</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Diana and Ducis Rodgers</title>
		<link>/blog/diana-and-ducis-rodgers/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2019 19:38:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AED Save]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9049</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A friend set us up with Ducis Rodgers. He came to one of our heart screenings and then quickly began raising awareness about sudden cardiac arrest and death in student athletes. Then, there was a couple&#8217;s dinner, and now we call Diana and Ducis friends. We&#8217;re so excited they&#8217;re serving as co-chairs for Simon&#8217;s Soiree [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/diana-and-ducis-rodgers/">Diana and Ducis Rodgers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A friend set us up with Ducis Rodgers. He came to one of our heart screenings and then quickly began raising awareness about sudden cardiac arrest and death in student athletes. Then, there was a couple&#8217;s dinner, and now we call Diana and Ducis friends. We&#8217;re so excited they&#8217;re serving as co-chairs for Simon&#8217;s Soiree 2020.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/diana-and-ducis-rodgers/">Diana and Ducis Rodgers</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Testimony &#8211; House Committee on Education and Cultural Affairs (Maine)</title>
		<link>/blog/testimony-house-committee-education-cultural-affairs-maine/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2017 13:53:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AED Save]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.simonsfund.org/?p=7750</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Chairwoman Kornfield and Chairman Langley thank you for allowing me to testify today before the Education and Cultural Affairs Committee in support of LD 1051 – an Act to Prevent Sudden Cardiac Arrest. My name is Darren Sudman. I am the Executive Director and Co-Founder of Simon’s Fund, an organization dedicated to raising awareness about the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/testimony-house-committee-education-cultural-affairs-maine/">Testimony &#8211; House Committee on Education and Cultural Affairs (Maine)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>Chairwoman Kornfield</strong> and <strong>Chairman Langley </strong>thank you for allowing me to testify today before the <strong>Education and Cultural Affairs Committee</strong> in support of <strong>LD 1051 – </strong>an Act to Prevent Sudden Cardiac Arrest.</p>
<p>My name is Darren Sudman. I am the Executive Director and Co-Founder of Simon’s Fund, an organization dedicated to raising awareness about the warning signs and conditions that lead to sudden cardiac arrest and death in children.</p>
<p><strong>Representatives Duchesne, Guerin, Higgins and Hubbell</strong> thank you for introducing this budget neutral, lifesaving legislation. I hope that my testimony today will make a compelling case to enact this bill into law.</p>
<p>Before I begin, I want to extend my thoughts and prayers to <strong>Katie Fugel’s</strong> family. Her passing inspired me to reach out to Representative Duchesne. Katie has brought all of us here together today.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I have walked in the Fugel’s shoes. In 2005, my three-month old son, Simon, didn’t wake up from his nap. Following his death, we were told to get our hearts checked because babies just don’t just die. As a result, my wife, Phyllis, was diagnosed with a heart condition called Long QT Syndrome. It is a potentially-fatal arrhythmia.</p>
<p>Research conducted at the <strong>Mayo Clinic</strong>, revealed that up to 15% of all sudden infant deaths (SIDS) could be attributed to this disease. We also discovered that this condition was one of several that caused students, particularly student athletes, to collapse and die.</p>
<p>We learned that sudden cardiac arrest was not just an adult thing. It takes the lives of thousands of children every year. It is the #1 cause of death of student athletes.</p>
<p>With all of this in mind, we found our purpose. We started Simon’s Fund.</p>
<p>We started providing <strong>free heart screenings</strong> to students. To date, we’ve checked over 14,000 hearts and helped over 100 students discover conditions.</p>
<p>We launched a crowdfunding website, <strong>GotAED</strong>, that is dedicated to getting automated external defibrillators into places where kids learn and play.</p>
<p>We created the first of its kind cardiac registry of seemingly healthy kids called HeartBytes. Data and images are gathered at heart screenings, de-identified, and made available to qualified researchers, free of charge.</p>
<p>And, we got involved in advocacy.</p>
<p>In 2011, I heard a story on the radio about <strong>Zachary Lystedt</strong>, a student athlete from Washington State who got hit in the head during a football game. He came out for three plays. Upon his return, he was hit again which led to his paralysis. This led to the Concussion Safety Legislation movement.</p>
<p>All fifty states, within five years, passed legislation to raise awareness about the threat posed to student athletes by concussions.</p>
<p>In 2012, Maine became the 39<sup>th</sup> state to implement this law. <strong>Chairman Langley, </strong>thank you for sponsoring this bill, and thanks to many of you on this Committee. That law passed by margins of 116 – 3 and 125 – 10, so I am assuming that many of you voted yes to protect student athletes.</p>
<p>LD 1051 is giving you another chance to protect the safety and well being of student athletes. Actually, to save the lives of student athletes.</p>
<p>I started my career as a lawyer. I also really loved the game of Mad Libs. So, when I heard about this law, I changed head to heart and modified the symptoms, to create the Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act.</p>
<p>We introduced it in Pennsylvania in 2011. It became law in in 2012.</p>
<p>It was an awareness bill. It didn’t mandate tests or equipment. It just mandated education. It was budget neutral. The educational materials required under the law were provided to the State for free. Since its passage, we have worked with lawmakers and organizations in ten other states to get similar bills passed: Arkansas, California, Connecticut, Delaware, Indiana, Maryland, New Jersey, Ohio, Pennsylvania, Tennessee and Washington.</p>
<p>I am excited that Maine could be the 12<sup>th</sup>.</p>
<p>The impact of this bill presented itself to me on May 31, the day AFTER it was signed. At that moment, the parents and coaches of approximately 300,000 student athletes were required to know the warning signs of sudden cardiac arrest and how to respond if it happens. Today, this law reaches the coaches and parents of over two million student athletes.</p>
<p>When this bill becomes law in Maine, the information will reach an additional 50,000 student athletes, their coaches and parents.</p>
<p>Why is this important? Why should this knowledge be mandated?</p>
<p>In 2012, a study was published indicating that 72% of students who died of sudden cardiac arrest exhibited at least one symptom before their death. I am providing you with a copy of that study today.</p>
<p>In fact, the number one warning sign of sudden cardiac arrest is fainting, during or immediately following exercise.</p>
<p>Many think that a quick break and swig of Gatorade is the antidote for fainting. This protocol works for exhaustion. However, it can be deadly if there is an underlying heart condition, and unfortunately, there is no way to tell the difference by looking at the student.</p>
<p>So, it is critical for parents and coaches to recognize the warning signs, and it is imperative for the players who do faint, during or immediately after exercise, to be cleared by a licensed medical professional.</p>
<p>Enacting this bill WILL save lives. It WILL NOT require funding, nor will it have any significant effect on the administrative duties of an athletic program or school.</p>
<p>First, parents will need to read and sign a form before their child can participate in sports. Parents in Maine already get forms. Adding one more lifesaving form is reasonable. Furthermore, this form already exists in eleven states. I am providing you with a copy of Connecticut’s form today.</p>
<p>Second, coaches need to be trained about the warning signs. A training video exists and will be made available for free to the coaches in Maine. It was produced by Simon’s Fund, and is distributed by the National Federation of State High School Association. The video comes with a quiz and the quiz results are shared with the school’s athletic director. The video is ten minutes. This is a minimal amount of time to invest when the lives of children are at stake.</p>
<p>Third, students who pass out during or immediately after exercise will need to be cleared by a licensed medical professional before they can return. This provision is the ultimate in objectivity. The football player catches the ball or he doesn’t. The soccer player scores a goal or she doesn’t. The student passes out or he doesn’t. The coach can make this call. In fact, it could be the most important call she makes in her career.</p>
<p>That is why I believe in LD 1051. With the stroke of a pen, coaches and parents will know that sudden cardiac arrest is not just an adult thing. They will know that fainting isn’t normal and in contemplating a response, they will learn about the importance of AED devices and CPR.</p>
<p>The citizens of your state will get to learn from my misfortune. They will get to be smarter than I was twelve years ago. They will get the chance to save the life of a student.</p>
<p>When Simon died, we didn’t have a path forward. We just wanted to prevent another family from losing a child to a detectable and treatable heart condition. LD 1051 will bring us closer to that goal.</p>
<p>Thank you for the opportunity to speak today. I am happy to answer any questions.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/testimony-house-committee-education-cultural-affairs-maine/">Testimony &#8211; House Committee on Education and Cultural Affairs (Maine)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Yeah, But You Don&#8217;t Save Lives</title>
		<link>/blog/yeah-dont-save-lives/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 13:02:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AED Save]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.simonsfund.org/?p=7746</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Funny story. My son died twelve years ago from an undetected heart condition. My husband and I started this foundation to provide free heart screenings for kids. We were thinking that if other parents had the chance to check their kids’ hearts, maybe their kids wouldn’t die from detectable and treatable heart conditions. I felt [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/yeah-dont-save-lives/">Yeah, But You Don&#8217;t Save Lives</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>Funny story. My son died twelve years ago from an undetected heart condition. My husband and I started this <a class="bn-clickable" href="https://www.simonsheart.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;foundation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:1,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://www.simonsheart.org/&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">foundation</a> to provide free heart screenings for kids. We were thinking that if other parents had the chance to check their kids’ hearts, maybe their kids wouldn’t die from detectable and treatable heart conditions.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>I felt good about what we were doing. We screened over 14,000 students and helped over 100 discover heart conditions. We’re part of a robust and passionate <a class="bn-clickable" href="https://www.screenacrossamerica.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;community&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:2,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://www.screenacrossamerica.org/&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">community</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>A couple of months ago, a reporter called. During the interview, she suggested that we had “no evidence that screening adolescents with <a class="bn-clickable" href="http://www.heart.org/HEARTORG/Conditions/HeartAttack/DiagnosingaHeartAttack/Electrocardiogram-ECG-or-EKG_UCM_309050_Article.jsp#.WKc4HTsrKUk" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;electrocardiograms&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:3,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;http://www.heart.org/HEARTORG/Conditions/HeartAttack/DiagnosingaHeartAttack/Electrocardiogram-ECG-or-EKG_UCM_309050_Article.jsp#.WKc4HTsrKUk&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">electrocardiograms</a> prevents deaths.”</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>Stop for a minute. Read the <a class="bn-clickable" href="http://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2017/02/22/516406346/heart-screening-for-teens-may-cause-more-problems-than-it-solves?utm_medium=RSS&utm_campaign=healthcare" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;full article here&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:4,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;http://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2017/02/22/516406346/heart-screening-for-teens-may-cause-more-problems-than-it-solves?utm_medium=RSS&utm_campaign=healthcare&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">full article here</a> for yourself. It was published by <a class="bn-clickable" href="https://www.npr.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;National Public Radio&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:5,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://www.npr.org/&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">National Public Radio</a>. The rest of my post will make more sense.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>I never thought I’d be challenged this way. I thought that helping parents realize that sudden cardiac arrest was not just an adult thing was productive. I believed that making parents, students and coaches aware of the warning signs was meaningful. I assumed that providing free heart screenings, so that others families could find the conditions and avoid the despair and grief that I did not, was worthwhile.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>I did not realize that the value of my efforts would be judged on whether I could prove that I saved a life.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>We never claim to save lives. That is presumptuous. <a class="bn-clickable" href="https://www.simonsheart.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;Our website&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:6,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://www.simonsheart.org/&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">Our website</a> says “lives changed.” But should that fact really matter? As a parent, do you want to take that chance with your child?</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>Talk to the parents of <a class="bn-clickable" href="http://www.simonsheart.org/about-us/simons-club/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;these children&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:7,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;http://www.simonsheart.org/about-us/simons-club/&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">these children</a> who discovered potentially fatal heart conditions at screenings. They’ll tell you, without hesitation, that the ECG saved their child’s life. Or, <a class="bn-clickable" href="https://youtu.be/33dBdRbTsPc?list=PLJp1XkcEsYNcYP-PDe2IjEomaJMIsjsZE" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;watch this&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:8,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://youtu.be/33dBdRbTsPc?list=PLJp1XkcEsYNcYP-PDe2IjEomaJMIsjsZE&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">watch this</a>, and hear directly from the kids. Where were these stories and perspectives in the article?</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>The article only shared Daniel’s story. He attended a screening, was flagged for a serious condition, and was later cleared, but not until his family incurred significant costs and suffered anxiety. This story is horrible. It haunts anyone who provides heart screenings because heart screenings were born out of the desire to spare other parents from unimaginable pain and loss (which are significantly worse than anxiety).</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>It is very misleading to only speak of Daniel, and willfully ignore the brighter futures of Kyle, Drew, Katie, Alaysia, Whitney, Valerie, Melissa, Jake and others. How about my future? Following Simon’s death, I was diagnosed with <a class="bn-clickable" href="http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/157826-overview?pa=PjofP1WqrlFMIEa4Oylf9jaJp3kyR4lSTphuup4G8jGZ1Ao4wNY6L008prkP7zBQkKhMrb9tVKAxwHMq4DPsNA4gMDzaXeeACHEF5jf2slY%3D" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;Long QT Syndrome&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:9,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/157826-overview?pa=PjofP1WqrlFMIEa4Oylf9jaJp3kyR4lSTphuup4G8jGZ1Ao4wNY6L008prkP7zBQkKhMrb9tVKAxwHMq4DPsNA4gMDzaXeeACHEF5jf2slY%3D&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">Long QT Syndrome</a>. Do you think that Simon saved my life? I do.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>Besides, how can we really prove that an ECG screening saves a life? Can we prove that a mammogram saves a life? How about a colonoscopy? We can prove they lead to diagnoses (<a class="bn-clickable" href="https://www.cancer.gov/types/breast/hp/breast-screening-pdq" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;sometimes false ones&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:10,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://www.cancer.gov/types/breast/hp/breast-screening-pdq&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">sometimes false ones</a>). But how can we prove they save lives?</p>
</div>
<div class="inline-newsletter inline-newsletter--valencia"></div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>I’m not a doctor. I didn’t even care that much for science back in school. But this is what I’m thinking . . .</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>Let’s find ten kids with heart conditions. We’ll have to detect the conditions at a community screening with an ECG or my experiment won’t work. We won’t refer her to a clinic for more testing or treatment. We’ll just wait. Every year, we’ll check back to see if she or the others are still alive. After twenty years, we’ll write a killer research paper and cite the percentage of kids who died but could have been saved with treatment (and since we used 10, the math will be super easy to figure out).</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>I am not suggesting that heart screenings are perfect &#8211; far from it. There are real problems that have to be addressed. But, here’s the truth. The “problem-causing” screening organizations are the ones demanding answers and driving the science.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>The <a class="bn-clickable" href="http://www.cardiology.org/projects_athletic_14_3136203759.pdf" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;Seattle Criteria&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:11,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;http://www.cardiology.org/projects_athletic_14_3136203759.pdf&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">Seattle Criteria</a>, which has dramatically driven down the false positive rate in student athlete heart screenings, evolved out of the screening community. The <a class="bn-clickable" href="http://www.onlinejacc.org/content/69/8/1057" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;updated criteria&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:12,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;http://www.onlinejacc.org/content/69/8/1057&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">updated criteria</a> were released this week in the Journal of American College of Cardiology.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>The impact that anxiety has on students who attend heart screenings was <a class="bn-clickable" href="https://iths.pure.elsevier.com/en/publications/the-psychological-impact-of-cardiovascular-screening-in-young-ath-2" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;studied&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:13,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://iths.pure.elsevier.com/en/publications/the-psychological-impact-of-cardiovascular-screening-in-young-ath-2&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">studied</a> by the screening community. The emotional impact is very low.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>Evaluating whether an ECG improves the chance of detecting heart conditions during a standard physical exam was funded and <a class="bn-clickable" href="http://www.simonsheart.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Drezner_ECG-Screening-in-NCAA-Athletes_AJC-2016.pdf" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;studied&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:14,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;http://www.simonsheart.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Drezner_ECG-Screening-in-NCAA-Athletes_AJC-2016.pdf&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">studied</a> by the screening community. I know . . . we still can’t prove that the conditions would have killed those thirteen NCAA athletes (ten of whom only found their conditions after getting an ECG).</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>Interestingly, in an effort to cast doubt on screenings, the article quoted three doctors involved in a two-year-old NIH <a class="bn-clickable" href="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/news/spotlight/fact-sheet/frequently-asked-questions-about-sudden-death-young-case-registry" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;registry&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:15,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/news/spotlight/fact-sheet/frequently-asked-questions-about-sudden-death-young-case-registry&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">registry</a> that tracks sudden death kids; an effort by the <a class="bn-clickable" href="http://cardiac-safety.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;Cardiac Safety Research Consortium&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:16,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;http://cardiac-safety.org/&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">Cardiac Safety Research Consortium</a> to standardize the screening process; and a four year screening pilot program in Texas. All three of these initiatives were driven and/or funded by the <a class="bn-clickable" href="https://www.parentheartwatch.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;screening community&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:17,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://www.parentheartwatch.org/&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">screening community</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>The article goes to great lengths to expose all of the alleged harms of ECG screenings, yet fails to explore the reality surrounding kids who die, or are saved with an <a class="bn-clickable" href="https://www.gotaed.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;automated external defibrillator&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:18,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://www.gotaed.org/&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">automated external defibrillator</a> (AED). When a student drops dead, we are horrified. When a student is saved with an AED, we are relieved. But, in both scenarios, the students were failed by the medical system. They had wellness exams. The had sports physicals. Their families were consistently assured that their child was fine. Is that acceptable or should we acknowledge that the status quo is flawed and can be fatal?</p>
</div>
<div class="advertisement in_line_ad_unit treated">
<div id="adsDiv3" class="adtech-adspot ad-in_line_ad_unit"><em>Charities Push for More Data and Better Heart Screenings</em>. This could have been the title of the article. It would have conveyed the uncertainty around screenings. At the same time, it would have honored the lives of our children and the sacrifices we have made to protect them. Not our children. Our children are dead. Your children.</div>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true"></div>
<div class="content-list-component bn-content-list-text text" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;}}" data-beacon-parsed="true">
<p>Instead, this article suggested that we are part of the problem. Honestly, after losing my son, that’s one burden I never thought I’d have to bear.</p>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/yeah-dont-save-lives/">Yeah, But You Don&#8217;t Save Lives</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Heart of Mike Pence</title>
		<link>/blog/heart-mike-pence/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2016 18:37:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AED Save]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.simonsfund.org/?p=7623</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Published previously in Huffington Post It’s official. Governor Mike Pence of Indiana is Trump’s pick for Veep (great show, by the way). Most people are “meeting” him for the first time. I “met” him in March 2014, when he became the fourth Governor to sign the Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act (SCAPA). This Act was introduced [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/heart-mike-pence/">The Heart of Mike Pence</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Published previously in Huffington Post</em></p>
<p>It’s official. Governor Mike Pence of Indiana is <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2016/07/14/politics/donald-trump-vice-presidential-choice/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:2}}">Trump’s pick</a> for Veep (great show, by the way). Most people are “meeting” him for the first time. I “met” him in March 2014, when he became the fourth Governor to sign the Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act (SCAPA). This Act was introduced by <a href="http://thestatehousefile.com/coaches-required-monitor-students-cardiac-arrest-symptoms-bill-passed-senate/15328/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:3}}">Representative Ron Bacon</a> and educates coaches, parents and players about the risks and warning signs of sudden cardiac arrest.</p>
<p>It is estimated that <a href="http://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2013/08/06/injuries-athletes-kids-sports/2612429/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:4}}">1.35 million</a> students visit emergency rooms for serious sports injuries every year. The overwhelming majority of these injuries are strains, sprains, fractures, contusions (bruises) and abrasions (scrapes). Fortunately, the prognosis for these types of injuries is very good.</p>
<p>That is not the case for students who experience cardiac arrest. The likely outcome is death. In fact, the survival rate is less than <a href="http://www.ems1.com/cardiac-arrest/articles/2255015-Report-U-S-out-of-hospital-cardiac-arrest-survival-rates-unacceptably-low/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:5}}">six percent</a>. That rate can <a href="https://www.heart.org/idc/groups/heart-public/@wcm/@adv/documents/downloadable/ucm_301646.pdf" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:6}}">be improved</a> with the availability of an automated external defibrillator (AED) and cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR), but its still pretty poor.</p>
<p>As parents, when a child goes down and is writhing in pain, we know that something is wrong. If there is not an <a href="http://www.nata.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:7}}">athletic trainer</a> on site to assess the situation (which there should be), we will take the child to an emergency room (hence the 1.35 million visits mentioned above). Time is usually not of the essence for these cases.</p>
<p>However, unless you’ve lost a child like I have, or know someone who has, you probably think that sudden cardiac arrest is just an adult thing. It’s not. Sudden cardiac arrest is the <a href="https://www.ncaa.org/sites/default/files/Cardiac_SA_Web10102011.pdf" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:8}}">number one</a> cause of death of student athletes. It takes the lives of <a href="https://www.aap.org/en-us/about-the-aap/aap-press-room/pages/Understanding-Pediatric-Sudden-Cardiac-Arrest.aspx?nfstatus=401&nftoken=00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000&nfstatusdescription=ERROR:+No+local+token" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:9}}">thousands</a> of students every year.</p>
<p>It doesn’t have to be this way. A study showed that <a href="http://www.jabfm.org/content/25/4/408.full" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:10}}">seventy-two percent </a>of families who lost a child to cardiac arrest reported that there were warning signs. This conclusion was further corroborated by another <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/news/sudden-cardiac-arrest-may-have-warning-signs-after-all/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:11}}">recent study</a>.</p>
<p>So, in children, what are the warning signs of sudden cardiac arrest?</p>
<ul>
<li>Fainting or seizure during or after exercise</li>
<li>unexplained shortness of breath</li>
<li>dizziness</li>
<li>extreme fatigue</li>
<li>racing heart</li>
<li>sudden and unexplained death of a family member under 50</li>
</ul>
<p>This is why the SCAPA is such a great tool.</p>
<ul>
<li>Parents must read and sign a form acknowledging the risks and warnings signs associated with sudden cardiac arrest</li>
<li>Coaches must take an online training course to learn about the warning signs</li>
<li>Coaches must remove players who exhibit symptoms and those players cannot return until cleared by a licensed medical professional.</li>
</ul>
<p>The legislation is budget neutral, meaning that it does not create a cost for the state to implement (other than the cost of printing some forms). As a result, the parents of over two million student athletes have become informed about the risks and warning signs, and two hundred thousand coaches have been educated by the free video produced by <a href="https://www.simonsheart.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:12}}">Simon’s Fund</a> and promoted by the <a href="https://nfhslearn.com/courses/61032/sudden-cardiac-arrest." target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:13}}">National Federation of State High Schools Association</a>.</p>
<p>The SCAPA been passed in <a href="/legislation-by-state/">nine states</a>, and adopted by athletic associations in two other states. We were fortunate to collaborate with some amazing organizations on this effort:<a href="http://www.andysmilesforever.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:15}}">Andy Smiles Forever Foundation</a>, <a href="http://www.epsavealife.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:16}}">Eric Paredes Save a Life Foundation</a>, <a href="http://givingheartsahand.org/)" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:17}}">Giving Hearts a Hand</a>, <a href="http://www.heartinthegame.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:18}}">Heart in the Game</a>, <a href="http://nickoftimefoundation.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:19}}">Nick of Time Foundation</a>, <a href="http://www.playforchase.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:20}}">Play for Chase</a>, and <a href="http://whoweplayfor.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:21}}">Who We Play For</a>.</p>
<p>We’re going to hear a lot more about Governor Pence in the coming months. My hope is that, with your help, we’ll also hear a lot more about preventing sudden cardiac arrest among our children.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/heart-mike-pence/">The Heart of Mike Pence</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mother&#8217;s Day &#8211; Post Mortem</title>
		<link>/blog/mothers-day-post-mortem/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2016 15:34:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AED Save]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.simonsfund.org/?p=7533</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Published in the Huffington Post Another Mother’s Day is in the books. It is my 44th. For thirty-one years, the day was dedicated to honoring my mother. In my 32nd year, we welcomed Sally, our first child. Whoa did Mother’s Day change! It became so much more special and relevant because I finally knew what [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/mothers-day-post-mortem/">Mother&#8217;s Day &#8211; Post Mortem</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Published in the Huffington Post</p>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Another Mother’s Day is in the books. It is my 44th. For thirty-one years, the day was dedicated to honoring my mother.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>In my 32nd year, we welcomed Sally, our first child. Whoa did Mother’s Day change! It became so much more special and relevant because I finally knew what it meant to be a mother. With that first sleepless night and diaper change, appreciation for my mother went through the roof.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>In my 34th year, it changed again. Simon was born. Ninety-six days later he died. He was a seemingly health three-month old. However, he had an unknown heart condition. After he died, I was diagnosed with the same condition.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Now, eleven years later, I still have a hard time articulating what his death did to my Mother’s Day. I don’t know how to approach it. I have two beautiful kids, and my mom lives fifteen minutes down the road. There is so much to celebrate and appreciate. But&#8230;</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Most girls have thought about becoming a mother. From what I’ve read, the majority of women who experience it claim that it is the most challenging and rewarding part of life. It is a role for which we are completely unprepared. Somehow, we manage.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>As I struggle to process my emotions for yet another Mother’s Day season, I want to share some quotes about motherhood. Some are profound. Others are endearing. You’ll recognize a few of the names. You know, the celebrities. It’s fun to see how famous people view motherhood.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>However, pay closer attention to the quotes from the other women. These are women I got to know after Simon died through a group called <a href="http://www.parentheartwatch.org/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:0}}">Parent Heart Watch</a>. Like me, they lost children to unknown heart conditions and founded organizations to spare other families from tragedy.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Like me, they struggle to make sense of this holiday, and well, a world where you can lose your child to a detectable and treatable heart condition.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Motherhood is tough. If you just want a wonderful little creature to love, you can get a puppy.<br />
<a href="http://www.brainyquote.com/quotes/quotes/b/barbarawal596036.html" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:1}}">Barbara Walters</a></p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Motherhood has completely changed me. It’s just about like the most completely humbling experience that I’ve ever had. I think that it puts you in your place because it really forces you to address the issues that you claim to believe in and if you can’t stand up to those principles when you’re raising a child, forget it.<br />
<a href="http://www.brainyquote.com/quotes/quotes/d/dianekeato429714.html" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:2}}">Diane Keaton</a></p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>The natural state of motherhood is unselfishness. When you become a mother, you are no longer the center of your own universe. You relinquish that position to your children.<br />
<a href="http://www.brainyquote.com/quotes/quotes/j/jessicalan364785.html" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:3}}">Jessica Lange</a></p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>I never imagined the range and depth of feelings that motherhood would introduce into my life. I’ve gone from one extreme of incredible pride, an abundance of love and immeasurable joy&#8230;to the unthinkable edge of despair and knock-the-wind-out-of-you total devastation after losing my precious 19 year old daughter without warning. At the best moments before my tragic loss, I remember having the feeling that my heart would burst with love and joy. And now, it’s as though my heart has been completely shattered and I’m not sure if the pieces can ever be reassembled.<a href="http://www.peytonwalker.org/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:4}}"><br />
Julie Walker, The Peyton Walker Foundation</a></p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Each of my children carry a piece of my heart but it broke into more pieces than it was made of, when my son died.<br />
<a href="http://nickoftimefoundation.org/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:5}}">Darla Varrenti, Nick of Time Foundation</a></p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Being a mother: There is no greater gift, nor bigger heartache.<br />
<a href="http://ryanlopynski.org/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:6}}">Jeremy Lopynski, Ryan Lopynski Big Heart Foundation</a></p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Motherhood is a life-long promise from you to your child. You promise to protect and nurture and care for your child, to help them grow to adulthood. Sadly, despite your very best efforts, tragedy can wipe that out in a moment, and you’re left shouldering the pain of a failed promise.<br />
<a href="http://heartsmartekg.org/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:7}}">Mary Beth Schewitz, Max Schewitz Foundation</a></p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Motherhood is the greatest gift and I’m thankful God chose me. Motherhood has brought me unconditional love, hope, joy, sorrow, and laughter. Motherhood is pure beauty.<br />
<a href="http://www.runforsarah.com/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:8}}">Laura Friend, Run for Sarah</a></p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>I guess these sayings are really true. You don’t know what you got until it’s gone. To understand, walk in another (wo)man’s shoes.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Motherhood is something that we dream about and imagine. We know there will be laughter and celebrations. We know there will be tears and heartbreak, but we think it’ll be the “my boyfriend broke up with me” or the “I failed a test” kind.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>I didn’t know how to change a diaper. I didn’t know all of the different kinds of formula available for reflux. I didn’t know how to install a car seat. I didn’t know how to bury a child. I’ve learned all of these things on the fly. I’ve faked it.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>There is one thing I do know. Our children don’t come with a timeline or expiration date. Their roads and destinies are unknown. I was prepared to do whatever it took to get Simon to his destination. Instead, he gave his life for me, so that I could discover my heart condition and reach my destination, whatever that may be. I’m not sure that is how motherhood is supposed to work.</p>
</div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/mothers-day-post-mortem/">Mother&#8217;s Day &#8211; Post Mortem</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The $600,000 Vacation</title>
		<link>/blog/the-600000-vacation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 15:33:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AED Save]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.simonsfund.org/?p=7532</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Published in the Huffington Post This vacation was out of control. Their room was $5,900 a night. The helicopter ride cost $36,347. They spent more than $1,000 a day on drugs. It was like nothing I’d ever heard of before. Last summer, my friends took their family to Virginia. They rented a nice house with [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-600000-vacation/">The $600,000 Vacation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Published in the Huffington Post</p>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>This vacation was out of control. Their room was $5,900 a night. The helicopter ride cost $36,347. They spent more than $1,000 a day on drugs. It was like nothing I’d ever heard of before.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Last summer, my friends took their family to Virginia. They rented a nice house with a pool &#8211; a prerequisite for three kids under the age of ten. One beautiful day hanging out around the pool, they turned around and found one of their children at the bottom of it . . . unconscious.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>For twenty-six minutes, they performed <a href="http://www.redcross.org/get-help/prepare-for-emergencies/be-red-cross-ready/hands-only-cpr" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:0}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">CPR</a> and waited for the paramedics to arrive. For twenty-six minutes, he didn’t breath and his heart didn’t pump. When the first responders arrived, they shocked his heart with an <a href="http://www.chw.org/childrens-and-the-community/resources-for-schools/cardiac-arrest-project-adam/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:1}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">AED</a> device.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Why was it on this family vacation, swimming in that pool, a nine year old went into sudden cardiac arrest? What caused it? Could it have been prevented? Could the near drowning been avoided?</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Sudden cardiac arrest may be sudden, as the name suggests, in which case, there is little that can be done to prevent it. However, <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/news/sudden-cardiac-arrest-may-have-warning-signs-after-all/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:2}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">some studies</a> suggest that the majority of children who experience sudden cardiac arrest have at least one warning sign. Sudden cardiac arrest is caused by an underlying heart condition. Most of these conditions can be detected with an <a href="http://www.webmd.com/heart-disease/electrocardiogram" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:3}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">electrocardiogram (EKG)</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>What began as an idyllic family vacation turned into a nightmare. Every day was touch and go. According to the <a href="http://www.phillymag.com/citified/2016/04/19/cardiact-arrest-philadelphia-fire-department/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:4}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">statistics</a> on sudden cardiac arrest, drownings and resuscitation, Timmy had absolutely no chance of survival.</p>
<p>Timmy was in a coma for six days. He spent fourteen days in intensive care. He didn’t eat for eight days. During his stay, he was diagnosed with a heart condition called <a href="http://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/long-qt-syndrome/basics/definition/con-20025388" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:5}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">Long QT Syndrome</a>, a potentially-fatal arrhythmia that disrupts the heartbeat. Before his discharge, he received an <a href="http://www.heart.org/HEARTORG/Conditions/Arrhythmia/PreventionTreatmentofArrhythmia/Implantable-Cardioverter-Defibrillator-ICD_UCM_448478_Article.jsp#.VxpKSZMrLjA" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:6}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">implantable cardioverter-defibrillator (ICD)</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>In 2005, my son, Simon, died from this condition. Following his death, I was diagnosed with the same condition. It is responsible for up to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EnTsnfoJoNU" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:7}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">15% of all SIDS deaths</a>. It is one of a handful of conditions that makes cardiac arrest the leading cause of death of student athletes.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Like me, Timmy’s family didn’t know about their son’s heart condition because children don’t get EKG exams. The <a href="http://news.heart.org/ecgs-wont-save-more-young-people-experts-say/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:8}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">American Heart Association</a> and <a href="http://www.acc.org/latest-in-cardiology/articles/2014/09/15/14/24/acc-aha-release-recommendations-for-congenital-and-genetic-heart-disease-screenings-in-youth" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:9}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">American College of Cardiology</a>, the two organizations that dictate which tests are offered in the world of heart health, decided three decades ago that asking students twelve questions about their hearts and family history was good enough. Timmy is nine. He’s had that exam and was asked those questions at least three times. In fact, it is safe to assume that most children who collapse and die from sudden cardiac arrest have passed this AHA/ACC exam. In the medical world, that is called a false negative.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>One of the major arguments against screening kids’ hearts is the cost. For a minute, put aside the fact that a very small group of physicians from these two organizations are claiming that your child is not worth the cost of the exam. Instead, let’s looks at Timmy’s experience and explore the economics.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Timmy’s eighteen-day cardiac arrest episode cost $596,806. Put another way, it cost a over a half a million dollars to save the life of one nine year old.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Alternatively, Timmy could have gotten a $25 EKG exam before his vacation, at which point he could have discovered his heart condition, gone on a beta blocker, which costs about $5 per month, and enjoyed his Virginia family vacation. What sounds more appealing to you?</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Proponents of heart screenings suggest that the cost can be as low as $15. The opponents of heart screenings suggest that it is as high as $263. Let’s ignore both sides of the argument since they each have their own biases, and look at some medical institutions that are actually providing this service.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p><a href="https://www.peacehealth.org/southwest/services/heart/Pages/young-champions" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:10}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">Peace Health</a> charges $50 for a youth cardiac screening. <a href="http://www.beaumont.edu/heart/screenings-tests/student-healthy-heart-check/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:11}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">Beaumont Hospital</a> has offered the screening for as low as $10 per student. By way of reference, Italy, who mandated heart screenings for all children puts the cost at around $60 per child. By the way, Italy reduced the incidents of sudden cardiac arrest by <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23370230" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:12}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">89%</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Since Providence seems to have found a sustainable and scalable way to screen our youth, let’s use their number.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Take Timmy’s medical bills of $597,000 and divide them by the cost of one youth heart screening ($50). The result is 11,940. In other words, for the amount of money used to save one Timmy from sudden cardiac arrest, we could have screened 11,940 students at these two institutions.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>This doesn’t solve our problem, though. There are more than 11,940 students in this country. So, let’s start with the highest-risk population &#8211; student athletes. We do this all the time in medicine. It is a way to protect the most vulnerable and learn in the process.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>There are <a href="http://www.nfhs.org/ParticipationStatics/PDF/2014-15_Participation_Survey_Results.pdf" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:13}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">eight million</a> student athletes in the United States. To screen this population (at $50 per athlete), we would need $400 million. That seems like a whole lot of money . . . . until you think about Timmy.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Every year in this country, almost <a href="http://www.scienceworldreport.com/articles/9193/20130901/400-000-deaths-due-cardiac-death-each-year.htm" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:14}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">400,000 people</a> die from sudden cardiac arrest. This is more than breast cancer, lung cancer and AIDS combined. Isn’t it likely that out of that number, 670 would be kids like Timmy? If so, we just spent $400,000,000. The truth is, we spend way more than that because nationally, we only save about <a href="http://www.phillymag.com/citified/2016/04/19/cardiact-arrest-philadelphia-fire-department/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:15}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">11% of people</a> who experience sudden cardiac arrest. That means we are trying to save way more than 400,000 people a year and spending much more money.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Shouldn’t we opt for the alternative? Shouldn’t we screen our children to get a baseline of their heart; discover conditions that could be life-threatening in the short term; discover conditions that could be life shortening in the long term; or prevent cardiovascular disease? Doesn’t it behoove us to know as much about our hearts as early as possible? It is the #1 cause of death, remember?</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Timmy checked back into the hospital a few weeks ago. He stayed there for sixteen days. Two surgeries later, he got a new ICD. This “vacation” cost hundreds of thousands of dollars. This puts Timmy’s experience closer to $1,000,000. We could have screened a few more kids, probably.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>My son was worth everything to me. He saved my life. I discovered my heart condition because we didn’t discover his. Four years ago, at one of our screenings, <a href="https://www.simonsheart.org/blog/story/whitney-jones/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:16}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">Whitney Jones</a> discovered that she had Long QT Syndrome. Soon thereafter, her mother, Rayna, was diagnosed with it too. No one had to die. That’s how it should work.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>I can’t change my story or the ending, but if we get smarter about prevention and the way that we spend our money, I may be able to help change yours. Assuming, you think it’s worth it.</p>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-600000-vacation/">The $600,000 Vacation</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>No Sh#* Sherlock</title>
		<link>/blog/no-st-sherlock/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2016 15:30:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AED Save]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.simonsfund.org/?p=7531</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Published in the Huffington Post No sh*#, Sherlock. How fun is this phrase? C’mon, you’ve used at least once in your life. You know . . . the answer or outcome is so completely obvious that you sit in awe of someone doesn’t know it. I remember it being popular in middle and junior high [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/no-st-sherlock/">No Sh#* Sherlock</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Published in the Huffington Post</p>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>No sh*#, Sherlock. How fun is this phrase? C’mon, you’ve used at least once in your life. You know . . . the answer or outcome is so completely obvious that you sit in awe of someone doesn’t know it.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>I remember it being popular in middle and junior high school. Now that I am a mother, I am reminded why &#8211; kids do the darndest things!</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Courtesy of <a href="https://www.reddit.com/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:0}}">Reddit</a>, here are few examples:</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>“I put a stethoscope in my dog’s ears while he was sleeping and screamed into it. I had to get stitches on my neck and the bite marks narrowly missed my eye.”</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Really? You didn’t see that coming?</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>“I wanted to see if my bike would stop if I put a stick in the spokes. It did.”</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>No . . . a wheel would never stop if you jam a wedge in it . . . .</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>“I made a Lego “cake”, put it in the oven, and switched it on.”</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Of course! Everyone knows that plastic is made for baking.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Are you chuckling, shaking your head in disbelief, or recalling your own shameful story? They are all amusing. No one got hurt. So despite the lack of sense or judgment, we can laugh it off and forgive. Kids will be kids.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>However, this can’t be the case in medicine. We can’t miss the obvious because the consequences can be tragic.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>I read a story this week about a sixteen-year old girl named <a href="http://www.buzzfeed.com/leticiamiranda/girl-died-in-detention-cell-from-irregular-heartbeat-not-phy" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:1}}">Gynna McMillen</a>. She died in her sleep. The autopsy, through genetic testing, revealed that she had a heart condition called <a href="http://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/long-qt-syndrome/basics/definition/con-20025388" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:2}}">Long QT Syndrome</a>. This is an electrical defect. It causes an irregular heartbeat (arrhythmia) that can lead to cardiac arrest.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>No one at the Lincoln Village Juvenile Treatment and Detention Center knew about her heart condition.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>They should have.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>You see, two years earlier, Gynna’s father died unexpectedly in his sleep. This is the no sh@#, Sherlock moment.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>It is well documented that the sudden and unexpected death of a family member under the age of fifty raises a red flag. The <a href="https://www.aap.org/en-us/professional-resources/practice-support/Documents/Preparticipation-Physical-Exam-Form.pdf" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:3}}">Preparticipation Physical Evaluation</a>asks this specific question: “Has any family member or relative died of heart problems or had an unexpected or unexplained sudden death before age 50 (including drowning, unexplained car accident, or sudden infant death syndrome)?”</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>This document, and question, were drafted by five leading medical associations &#8211; the American Academy of Family Physicians (<a href="http://www.aafp.org/home.html" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:4}}">AAFP</a>), the American Academy of Pediatrics (<a href="https://www.aap.org/en-us/Pages/Default.aspx" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:5}}">AAP</a>), the American Medical Society for Sports Medicine (<a href="http://www.amssm.org/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:6}}">AMSSM</a>), the American Orthopaedic Society for Sports Medicine (<a href="https://www.sportsmed.org/aossmimis" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:7}}">AOSSM</a>), and the American Osteopathic Academy of Sports Medicine (<a href="http://www.aoasm.org/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:8}}">AOASM</a>). The document is used in a majority of states across this country when evaluating student athletes, and the question is part of many wellness checks.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Why didn’t anyone check Gynna McMillen’s heart after her father died suddenly and unexpectedly in his sleep? It is likely that <a href="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/qt/diagnosis" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:9}}">an electrocardiogram</a> would have revealed her Long QT Syndrome.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Didn’t all of the family physicians and pediatricians know this warning sign? Isn’t it so completely obvious that had to be the next step?</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>In 2005, my three-month old son died in his sleep. The initial prognosis was sudden infant death syndrome (<a href="http://kidshealth.org/en/parents/sids.html" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:10}}">SIDS</a>). However, my pediatrician was wiser than most and told me to get my heart checked because “babies don’t just die.” As a result, I was diagnosed Long QT Syndrome, just like Gynna.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Apparently, my pediatrician knew the standard. She knew the warning sign. She may have even known about the research that shows up to <a href="http://circ.ahajournals.org/content/115/3/294.full" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:11}}">15% </a>of all SIDS deaths is attributed to Long QT Syndrome.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Simon saved my life. I truly believe that.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Gynna’s dad tried to save her. Like Simon, he left a big clue. Unfortunately, Gynna needed Sherlock Holmes that day because her medical community failed her. Now, she is gone.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>It shouldn’t be this way. We need to do better. We can’t afford to miss the obvious.</p>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/no-st-sherlock/">No Sh#* Sherlock</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Do You Believe in Destiny?</title>
		<link>/blog/do-you-believe-in-destiny/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 15:26:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AED Save]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.simonsfund.org/?p=7529</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Published in the Huffington Post. Do you believe in destiny or are you one of those “that’s just a coincidence” kind of people? Let’s say you’ve been dying to go to a concert and your friend calls at the last minute to invite you. Destiny or coincidence? What if you go to a conference out [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/do-you-believe-in-destiny/">Do You Believe in Destiny?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Published in the Huffington Post.</p>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Do you believe in destiny or are you one of those “that’s just a coincidence” kind of people? Let’s say you’ve been dying to go to a concert and your friend calls at the last minute to invite you. Destiny or coincidence? What if you go to a conference out of town and find yourself sitting next to someone from a company that you’ve been trying to connect with forever? Destiny or coincidence?</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>I’m on the fence about this subject. Since Simon’s death, it is hard for me to make sense of things like this. Because, for me to believe in destiny, I have to accept that my son died for a reason. That’s a tall order.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>Simon was born on October 21, 2004. He was a seemingly healthy baby. He died in his sleep on January 24, 2005. Following his death, our family got their hearts checked and I discovered a heart condition that is attributed to up to <a href="http://cardiovascres.oxfordjournals.org/content/67/3/388" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:0}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">15% of SIDS deaths</a>. It is called <a href="http://my.clevelandclinic.org/services/heart/disorders/arrhythmia/long-qt-syndrome" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:1}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">Long QT Syndrome</a> (LQTS). In his memory, we established Simon’s Fund to raise awareness about sudden cardiac arrest and death in children.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>On the other hand, since his passing, some things have happened that are very difficult to explain. It is impossible for me to write them off as mere coincidence.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>You be the judge.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p><strong>The Third Angel Day</strong>. We call it his angel day &#8211; the day that Simon died. In 2007, Melissa Fair attended Simon’s Fund’s very first heart screening. She discovered two structural conditions that required open heart surgery. Her surgery took place on January 24, 2008. Out of all of the days to schedule a surgery, why did it happen on Simon’s third angel day? It is always a brutally difficult day. However, knowing that Melissa’s life was changed for the better makes it bearable.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p><strong>The Other Simon</strong>. I don’t know too many kids named Simon. I like that. It’s unique. Maybe even a little old school. In 2011, a local family reached out to us. Their son was getting ready to become a bar mitzvah and was looking for a community service project. We never had a student organize a screening for us, but it seemed like a pretty cool concept. He rallied more than 300 students to attend. He worked with <a href="http://www.fox29.com/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:2}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">FOX29</a> to get his EKG exam <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=us7Ee7y86BY" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:3}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">on the air</a> to educate the public. He created a new model for our organization that has led to many more screenings and projects spearheaded by students. Of course, his name was Simon.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p><strong>The Seventh Birthday</strong>. Drew Harrington played a lot of basketball. He used to complain to his mother that his heart beat felt strange at times. His mom attributed it to all of the caffeinated beverages he consumed. In 2012, Drew was one of the students who attended “The Other Simon’s” heart screening. Drew discovered a heart condition called <a href="http://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/wolff-parkinson-white/basics/definition/con-20043508" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:4}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wolff Parkinson White Syndrome</a>, an arrhythmia. On October 21, 2012, he had a procedure to correct the problem. This would have been Simon’s seventh birthday. It is so hard to be joyous on Simon’s birthday. It is a day when I should be throwing parties, taking photos and helping him open gifts. However, Drew has given us something to celebrate.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p><strong>The Ninth Birthday</strong>. Our ongoing ritual was to escape on Simon’s birthday. We just wanted to be alone. I didn’t want to deal with the conversations or glances that come with a birthday after your child has passed. Simon’s Fund was finalizing its <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aO0KfD52VMk" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:5}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">educational video</a> on sudden cardiac arrest for coaches pursuant to the passage of the <a href="/legislation-by-state/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:6}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act</a>. We received amazing news.<a href="https://twitter.com/JimmyRobertsNBC?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Eauthor" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:7}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jimmy Roberts</a> of NBC Sports agreed to narrate the video. There was a caveat &#8211; Jimmy was only available to record in studio on October 21. The video is now being used by state governments and the <a href="http://www.nfhs.org/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:8}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Federation of State High School Associations</a> to educate millions of coaches around the country.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p><strong>The Eleventh Birthday</strong>. Sudden death is a good way to decide a hockey game, not lose a teammate. Sudden cardiac arrest is the <a href="http://www.screenacrossamerica.org/about-us/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:9}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">#1 cause of death</a> of student athletes. This year, Simon’s Fund launched A Czech for Hearts with the<a href="http://flyers.nhl.com/" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:10}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">Philadelphia Flyers</a> and <a href="http://espn.go.com/nhl/player/_/id/3781/jakub-voracek" target="_hplink" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:11}}" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jakub Voracek</a> to bring awareness to the cause. Every time the Flyers win in overtime, Jakub donates $1,000 to Simon’s Fund for free heart screenings. The season began on October 8. On October 21, the Flyers won their first game of the season . . . and it was in sudden death. Happy Birthday, Simon.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p><strong>Just This Week</strong>. On Monday night (November 23), my husband and I went to the Flyers game and meet Jakub Voracek. We were excited to thank him for helping us launch such a meaningful awareness campaign. The Flyers got off to a quick 2 &#8211; 0 lead. In the third period, the Carolina Hurricanes scored two. The game was tied at the end of regulation. Twenty-four seconds into sudden death, the Flyers scored. Simon’s Fund received another $1,000 from Jakub. To date, the Flyers have won seven games. Three have been decided in sudden death.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>There is a very old cliché &#8211; everything happens for a reason. Literally, this is true. It rains because the clouds fill up with water. A dog chases a ball when we throw it. However, it is not always the reason that is so important. It is the purpose.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>I still can’t answer the question &#8211; is it destiny or coincidence. I also don’t want to admit that there was a reason for his death. Selfishly, I have a thousand reasons for him to be with me today. However, I can see the purpose.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>His death revealed true friendships. It brought amazing people into my life (some listed above). It widened my eyes to the generosity of and goodness in others. It brought awareness to millions of people. It may have even saved a few lives.</p>
</div>
<div class="content-list-component mt-paragraph text">
<p>During this holiday season, I hope that you find gratitude and purpose in your life. Happy Holidays.</p>
</div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/do-you-believe-in-destiny/">Do You Believe in Destiny?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
