<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>A Parent&#039;s Story Archives -</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/a-parents-story/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Protecting Hearts and Saving Lives</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 17:13:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/simons-fav-icon1.png</url>
	<title>A Parent&#039;s Story Archives -</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>My Perspective Changed Forever</title>
		<link>/blog/my-perspective-changed-forever/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Simon's Heart]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 17:09:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[A Parent's Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Life After SCA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SIDS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9184</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I remember like it was yesterday. Phyllis and I had to escape from life. We had just passed the first anniversary of Simon&#8217;s death. We took Sally to the beach. It was so hard to be around people with babies. It was even harder to hear about &#8220;problems.&#8221; I&#8217;m really sorry your contractor didn&#8217;t show up. It&#8217;s just [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/my-perspective-changed-forever/">My Perspective Changed Forever</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I remember like it was yesterday. Phyllis and I had to escape from life. We had just passed the first anniversary of Simon&#8217;s death. We took Sally to the beach.</p>
<p>It was so hard to be around people with babies. It was even harder to hear about &#8220;problems.&#8221; I&#8217;m really sorry your contractor didn&#8217;t show up. It&#8217;s just awful that you had to work all weekend. We couldn&#8217;t deal with all of this. Let&#8217;s say that we needed some social distancing.</p>
<p>Bitterness and resentment are best friends with tragedy and adversity. This is especially true when life shatters your expectations. I knew how life was <em>supposed</em> to work. I grow up. I start a family. I have kids. I watch them grow up and raise their family. Then I pass on. But, that&#8217;s not my life. I was being singled out.</p>
<h4><span style="color: #fc0505;">Something happened on the beach that day and it went something like this.</span></h4>
<p>What if that is not the way life is supposed to work. Sure, it happens that way for most people I know, but that is because they are blessed and fortunate. What happens if examine the lives of the 6.6 billion people around the world? Does life really work out that way? Probably not.</p>
<p>Do I really get to expect my son to reach a certain age? What happens if I reset my expectations to zero days? Can I convince myself to be grateful for the 96 days I had?</p>
<p>Last week, someone on the news suggested that social distancing is not in place to prevent me from catching COVID-19. It is preventing me from infecting someone else. I need to assume that I am infected. Hmmm. Perspective.</p>
<p>As we shelter in place, search for a new normal, and face varying levels of adversity, I hope that you and your family can find a healthy perspective to get you through these challenging times. This too shall pass.</p>
<p><span style="color: #fc080c;">&#8211;<em>Darren Sudman,</em> <em>CEO, Co-Founder and Simon&#8217;s Dad</em></span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/my-perspective-changed-forever/">My Perspective Changed Forever</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Being a Part of Something Bigger</title>
		<link>/blog/being-a-part-of-something-bigger/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2014 22:18:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[A Parent's Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nonprofits]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=5826</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I am on my way home from the 9th Annual Parent Heart Watch Conference. I sit on the Board and Simon&#8217;s Fund was a sponsor. It is a great organization that brings families and organizations together. Here are some thoughts that I shared with the attendees. Simon’s Fund is really happy to join the likes [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/being-a-part-of-something-bigger/">Being a Part of Something Bigger</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am on my way home from the 9th Annual <a href="http://www.parentheartwatch.org/">Parent Heart Watch Conference</a>. I sit on the Board and Simon&#8217;s Fund was a sponsor. It is a great organization that brings families and organizations together. Here are some thoughts that I shared with the attendees.</p>
<p>Simon’s Fund is really happy to join the likes of the Acomporas and sponsor this Conference because it is something very special. We all have something in common &#8211; our lives have been touched by sudden cardiac arrest. However, we are all in this room together because we want to do something about it.</p>
<p>As we saw in the Members&#8217; Rock Presentation this morning, many of us are doing great things in our hometown, but at a place like this, we figure out how to do it bigger and better. We make new discoveries. We find new friends. We talk about best practices. We connect the dots. Really, the possibilities of what we can accomplish are endless.</p>
<p>Let me share a few examples. This past year, with the help of the Nick of Time Foundation, we launched a new website called Screen Across America. It identifies over forty organizations across the country who regularly provide youth heart screenings.</p>
<p>It shows the world that heart screenings aren’t just the pet projects of grieving parents, but that they are part of a national movement.  This concept would not have been developed without our involvement in Parent Heart Watch.</p>
<p>Two years ago, we passed the Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act in Pennsylvania. It has already been introduced in six other states, and is expected to be introduced in six more by the end of 2014.  We have worked with many of you in this room on this legislation. This success would not have happened without our involvement in Parent Heart Watch.</p>
<p>I want to take a second and give a shout out to one of these groups because they blow me way.  There are eight students here this weekend from Florida. In 2007, they lost their high school teammate and friend, Rafe. In response, they formed Who We Play For. It is six years later and they are all in college now. They are meeting at 7 AM on Tuesday mornings, going to Orlando to help Martha with heart screenings, traveling to Tallahassee to meet with lawmakers, and placing AEDs around their community. You guys are inspiring. You are also showing up all of us old people.</p>
<p>I hope that this is a very meaningful conference for all of you. I hope that it helps you heal and inspires you to go home to do great things. I also hope that it makes you a believer in the power of Parent Heart Watch, so that as we continue our personal journeys, we will also be thinking about how we can support each other and this great organization.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/being-a-part-of-something-bigger/">Being a Part of Something Bigger</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Simon&#8217;s Club Member of the Week &#8211; Jake Berman</title>
		<link>/blog/simons-fund-student-of-the-week-jake-berman/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2013 10:00:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[A Parent's Story]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=5430</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When doctors told Margie Gardner her daughter’s heart arrhythmia was not hereditary, she was relieved; at least, she needn’t worry about her older child Jake. Still when she heard about Simon’s Fund’s free heart screening at Plymouth Whitemarsh High School in 2007, she decided to have Jake tested. She remains stunned by the irony of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/simons-fund-student-of-the-week-jake-berman/">Simon&#8217;s Club Member of the Week &#8211; Jake Berman</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Jake-Web.png"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-5431" src="https://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Jake-Web.png" alt="Jake Web" width="249" height="355" /></a></p>
<p>When doctors told Margie Gardner her daughter’s heart arrhythmia was not hereditary, she was relieved; at least, she needn’t worry about her older child Jake. Still when she heard about Simon’s Fund’s free heart screening at Plymouth Whitemarsh High School in 2007, she decided to have Jake tested. She remains stunned by the irony of Jake’s diagnosis that day with Wolff Parkinson White (WPW), an extra electrical pathway in the heart which can cause a very rapid heartbeat.</p>
<p>During spring break that year, Jake underwent cardiac ablation to repair his heart at A.I. DuPont Hospital for Children. After taking six weeks off to recuperate, Jake went right back to his busy life, which includes marching band, hiking and rock climbing.</p>
<p>Seven years after Jake’s diagnosis, his mother reflects, “Jake’s surgery was simple, but his condition could have killed him. We feel very lucky that Simon’s Fund exists and helped us ensure Jake’s safety. We only wish that we had known about Jake’s heart condition when he were an infant and taken care of it then.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/simons-fund-student-of-the-week-jake-berman/">Simon&#8217;s Club Member of the Week &#8211; Jake Berman</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Simon&#8217;s Club Member of the Week &#8211; Alaysia Keeley</title>
		<link>/blog/simons-fund-student-of-the-week-alaysia-keeley/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2013 10:00:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[A Parent's Story]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=5427</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>October 30, 2010 was a crazy day in the Keeley house. Both of single mom Beth’s kids had soccer games and the family had promised to attend a birthday party. As a result, Alaysia Keeley almost didn’t make it to Norristown High School to get her heart screened. Luckily, a voice in Beth’s head told [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/simons-fund-student-of-the-week-alaysia-keeley/">Simon&#8217;s Club Member of the Week &#8211; Alaysia Keeley</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Alaysia-Web.png"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-5428" src="https://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/Alaysia-Web.png" alt="Alaysia Web" width="307" height="398" /></a></p>
<p>October 30, 2010 was a crazy day in the Keeley house. Both of single mom Beth’s kids had soccer games and the family had promised to attend a birthday party. As a result, Alaysia Keeley almost didn’t make it to Norristown High School to get her heart screened. Luckily, a voice in Beth’s head told her to keep the appointment. That voice may have saved the East Norriton middle schooler’s life.</p>
<p>Alaysia’s EKG suggested Long QT Syndrome, the same heart condition that took Simon Sudman’s life. A stress test and genetic testing at Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia confirmed it. The most common electrical heart condition, Long QT Syndrome can cause a fast, chaotic heartbeat, and lead to sudden cardiac arrest.</p>
<p>For Alaysia, a three-season athlete with dreams of playing in the WNBA, the diagnosis was life altering. She was immediately placed on medication with the warning that she might need a pacemaker or implanted defibrillator. Her doctor also limited her physical activity.</p>
<p>Today Beth Keeley struggles between protecting her daughter’s health and allowing her to live a normal life. The two worked closely with Alaysia’s doctor to find a compromise about basketball. The result: as long as there is an AED on site, Alaysia is allowed to play for two minutes every other quarter. She must sit down if she begins to feel sluggish. Alaysia’s school has asked Beth to attend all of her daughter’s games, requiring her to regularly leave her job at CVS for hours at a time. She brings her own AED.</p>
<p>“It’s the worst as a parent. I don’t want her to feel different, but I’m afraid. What if I let her play and something happens. How will I live with myself?” wonders Beth Keeley.</p>
<p>This year, as she signed Alaysia’s health forms for school sports, Beth was excited to see the information sheet about sudden cardiac arrest, required by Pennsylvania’s Sudden Cardiac Arrest Awareness Act. Beth and Alaysia were part of the contingent from Simon’s Fund which travelled to Harrisburg to lobby for the law &#8212; a law this mom hopes will raise awareness among coaches of the warning signs of sudden cardiac arrest in their athletes.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/simons-fund-student-of-the-week-alaysia-keeley/">Simon&#8217;s Club Member of the Week &#8211; Alaysia Keeley</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Simon&#8217;s Club Member of the Week &#8211; Katie Asper</title>
		<link>/blog/simons-fund-student-of-the-week-katie-asper/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2013 10:00:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[A Parent's Story]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=5437</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Karen Asper, a nurse affiliated with Abington Hospital, volunteered to work at Simon’s Fund’s free heart screening at Upper Dublin high school on September 23rd, 2012. As the day wore on, Karen learned that space had opened up at the ‘sold out’ screening and she went home to pick up her children to be screened. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/simons-fund-student-of-the-week-katie-asper/">Simon&#8217;s Club Member of the Week &#8211; Katie Asper</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/Camera-shop-1-e1381771893574.jpeg"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-5545" src="https://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/Camera-shop-1-198x300.jpeg" alt="Camera shop 1" width="198" height="300" /></a></p>
<p>Karen Asper, a nurse affiliated with Abington Hospital, volunteered to work at Simon’s Fund’s free heart screening at Upper Dublin high school on September 23<sup>rd</sup>, 2012. As the day wore on, Karen learned that space had opened up at the ‘sold out’ screening and she went home to pick up her children to be screened. Like most parents who bring their children to screenings, Karen expected to be in and out. Like 1% of these parents – or 1 in 100 – Karen was stunned when she learned that her daughter had a heart condition.</p>
<p>The EKG had shown that daughter Katie, 14, had Wolff Parkinson White Syndrome (WPW), a disorder that can run in families. Although Katie had never complained of any symptoms, such as dizziness or a racing heart, during a stress test, when her heart was stressed to a rate of 190, the Wolff Parkinson White still showed up on the monitors. This indicated that the condition could put Katie in danger. Ironically, at the time, some of Karen’s days were being spent working in Abington’s cardiac stress lab giving stress tests.</p>
<p>People with WPW have an extra electrical circuit in their heart, which can cause their heart rate to go too high. The gravity of a person’s WPW depends on which pathway is affected by the aberrant circuit. Katie’s doctors could not determine which pathway was impacted without performing invasive electrophysiological tests. Her mother found this untenable, “I was having a hard time intervening with an invasive procedure when Katie was not symptomatic,” she explains.</p>
<p>The uncertainty was taking its toll on Katie, causing her to visit the nurse more at school and feel apprehensive. Karen found herself regularly quizzing the cardiologists in her stress test lab, until finally she got the advice that spurred her to action. Dr. Andy Fireman advised her to stop thinking like a nurse and instead think like a mom about how she would feel if something happened to Katie. His advice, combined with Katie’s upcoming mission to Belize, where she wouldn’t have access to advanced medical care, finally made the decision easy.</p>
<p>Almost nine months to the day after her initial heart screening, Katie underwent the testing and a cardiac ablation at Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia. Her family was told after the procedure that they had made the right choice; had the doctor have known in advance which pathway was aberrant, ablation to remedy it would definitely have been recommended. An EKG and echocardiogram shortly thereafter showed no sign of WPW.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/simons-fund-student-of-the-week-katie-asper/">Simon&#8217;s Club Member of the Week &#8211; Katie Asper</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Whitney Jones &#8211; Simon&#8217;s Club Member of Week</title>
		<link>/blog/whitney-jones-simons-club-member-of-week/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2013 10:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[A Parent's Story]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=5491</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Any mother would gladly lay down her life for her child, which makes both the Jones’ and Sudman’s stories heartbreakingly ironic. Phyllis Sudman has long credited her child, Simon, with saving her life. Following his death, the family was instructed to get their hearts checked. Through this process, Phyllis was diagnosed with Long QT Syndrome, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/whitney-jones-simons-club-member-of-week/">Whitney Jones &#8211; Simon&#8217;s Club Member of Week</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/Camera-shop-24-copy.jpg"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-5492" src="https://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/Camera-shop-24-copy.jpg" alt="Camera shop 24 copy" width="383" height="254" /></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Any mother would gladly lay down her life for her child, which makes both the Jones’ and Sudman’s stories heartbreakingly ironic. Phyllis Sudman has long credited her child, Simon, with saving her life. Following his death, the family was instructed to get their hearts checked. Through this process, Phyllis was diagnosed with Long QT Syndrome, and a reason for Simon’s death was found. The Jones family credits the Sudmans and Simons Fund with saving both mom Rayna’s and daughter Whitney’s lives.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">In May 2012, Whitney’s cheerleading coach signed her entire team up for Simon’s Fund’s free heart screening at Downingtown West High School. Before the screening, neither Whitney, a competitive cheerleader, nor Rayna, a former runner and swimmer, knew much about sudden cardiac arrest among students. They certainly had not heard of Long QT Syndrome, a hereditary heart condition particularly dangerous for athletes. Within a month, both would be diagnosed with the condition that killed Simon Sudman.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">“We really admire how the Sudmans have given back to so many others by organizing Simon&#8217;s Fund to help others avoid the same tragedy faced by their family. For the rest of our lives, we will be thankful for their mission to help others. It is hard to find the words to express our heartfelt appreciation for what they have done for our family,” says Rayna Jones.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Rayna remembers sitting at the screening waiting … and waiting, as her daughter’s friends were being sent home, until the cardiologist came out and asked to speak with her privately. They’d found an anomaly on Whitney’s EKG and wanted to do an echocardiogram on site. The findings were not conclusive, but suggested Long QT Syndrome.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Getting a final diagnosis took the family almost a year of additional testing, because Whitney’s results were borderline. One test was particularly memorable. Whitney underwent a stress test at the Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia. Her heart reacted intensely to the test, and for the first time, the family became frightened. Yet the diagnosis was still not definitive, so the doctors suggested genetic testing. That’s where the Jones finally got their answers. Both Whitney and Rayna had the hereditary heart condition; Rayna’s was much more severe than her daughter’s.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The Joneses are grateful that their insurance covered this testing, allowing them to finally get the answer they needed.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Whitney is lucky; her sport of choice centers around a two and a half minute routine. Sports like soccer or basketball with sustained activity could prove too dangerous. Still Whitney’s doctor requires that an AED be available on the field whenever she practices or competes. Rayna is allowed to walk for exercise, as long as she stays hydrated.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">“Whitney is such a special girl with a sunny, winning spirit” says her mother. “Although this diagnosis has been a heartbreaking experience for us, we are not going to let it rob us of a full life. We are focused on managing Whitney’s Long QT through medication, hydration, nutrition and avoiding the potential triggers. In the future, we hope to help others through our story and we will be life long supporters of Simon&#8217;s Fund to help others benefit from the testing that helped our family.”</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/whitney-jones-simons-club-member-of-week/">Whitney Jones &#8211; Simon&#8217;s Club Member of Week</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>$60 Saved a Life &#8211; Just Ask Mom &#038; Dad</title>
		<link>/blog/60-saved-a-life-just-ask-mom-dad/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2012 23:37:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[A Parent's Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3320</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>It was the best $60 that Scott and Sarah Lepke ever spent. &#160; In November 2010, the Lepkes opted to pay the extra money for an optional athletic heart screening for their son, Matt. The ultrasound test, through Transmed Inc.&#8217;s Screening America program, was offered by the Beresford School District. The Lepkes&#8217; decision was more [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/60-saved-a-life-just-ask-mom-dad/">$60 Saved a Life &#8211; Just Ask Mom &amp; Dad</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It was the best $60 that Scott and Sarah Lepke ever spent.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In November 2010, the Lepkes opted to pay the extra money for an optional athletic heart screening for their son, Matt. The ultrasound test, through Transmed Inc.&#8217;s Screening America program, was offered by the Beresford School District. The Lepkes&#8217; decision was more about supporting the sports program at the school, where Scott was the high school principal at the time, than it was about any concern for their son&#8217;s health.</p>
<p>&#8220;We never, ever thought that there was a problem with him. He&#8217;d been an athlete his whole life,&#8221; said Sarah of her 12-year-old son.</p>
<p>But the ultrasound revealed a life-threatening defect in Matt&#8217;s heart &#8211; a large hole between his left and right atrium that had been there since birth. So large, in fact, that it went undetected during routine physicals that might have caught smaller, noisier heart murmurs.</p>
<p>&#8220;That&#8217;s the thing with murmurs &#8211; the bigger they are, the less likely you are to catch them,&#8221; said Scott, who has been superintendent of the Custer School District since July. &#8220;His was so big, that it wasn&#8217;t making a noise.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="http://rapidcityjournal.com/lifestyles/parents-credit-optional-athletic-heart-screening-for-saving-son-s/article_cbbee8e4-3891-11e1-9584-001871e3ce6c.html">Full story</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/60-saved-a-life-just-ask-mom-dad/">$60 Saved a Life &#8211; Just Ask Mom &amp; Dad</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
