<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Past Events Archives -</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/past-events/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Protecting Hearts and Saving Lives</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 05:51:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/simons-fav-icon1.png</url>
	<title>Past Events Archives -</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Central Bucks South (October 20, 2013)</title>
		<link>/blog/central-bucks-south-october-20-2013/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2013 15:34:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Past Events]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=5813</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This was one of those very special screenings. Two years ago, Caroline Gallagher died from sudden cardiac arrest. The students started a 5K in her memory. This screening was held the same day as the 5K. We worked closely with the Gallagher and Jacobsen families. We also couldn&#8217;t have done it without the tremendous support [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/central-bucks-south-october-20-2013/">Central Bucks South (October 20, 2013)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This was one of those very special screenings. Two years ago, Caroline Gallagher died from sudden cardiac arrest. The students started a 5K in her memory. This screening was held the same day as the 5K. We worked closely with the Gallagher and Jacobsen families. We also couldn&#8217;t have done it without the tremendous support of Maria Reitano, a vice principal at the school.  We screened 296 students.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/central-bucks-south-october-20-2013/">Central Bucks South (October 20, 2013)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Bill Signing &#8211; Our Remarks</title>
		<link>/blog/the-bill-signing-our-remarks/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2012 11:24:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Legislation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Past Events]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3628</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I need to begin by saying thank you to Jennaphr Frederick, Josh Weisman, Brian Kadunc and Representative Mike Vereb.  The universe brought all of us together on April 14, 2011, and as a result, we are here today making a huge difference in the lives students. Representative Vereb, a big thanks to you (and your [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-bill-signing-our-remarks/">The Bill Signing &#8211; Our Remarks</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I need to begin by saying thank you to Jennaphr Frederick, Josh Weisman, Brian Kadunc and Representative Mike Vereb.  The universe brought all of us together on April 14, 2011, and as a result, we are here today making a huge difference in the lives students.</p>
<p>Representative Vereb, a big thanks to you (and your staff) for your tireless efforts.  We did not realize the champion we were getting that day we met in your office.  Governor Corbett, thank you for your leadership and support on this issue. With your pen stroke here today, you will save the lives of children.</p>
<p>A good friend of ours always says that we are members of a club that no one wants to join.  Phyllis and I became members of that club on January 24, 2005, when our three month old son, Simon, died.  There are other club members here today – the Rodgers Family, the Silva Family and the Frazier family.  It was Akhir Frazier’s story that brought me to Representative Vereb’s office.</p>
<p>Like in all clubs, the members get to decide what they want to get out of it.  Our choice was simple.  We wanted to make sure that we were the last members of this club.  We don’t want you to join. We want your kids to be safer.  This bill is a manifestation of our choice.</p>
<p>We believe that there are three approaches to tackling sudden cardiac arrest and death in children. These approaches are not mutually exclusive.  They work together, in concert.</p>
<p>The first approach is DETECTION.  We need to discover these conditions before they hurt our children.  Simon’s Fund works with schools and organizations to provide free heart screenings.  To date, we’ve checked almost 4,000 hearts and helped at least 38 students discover potentially life threatening heart conditions.  Some of those students are sitting here today.</p>
<p>This weekend, we’ll be at the Liacouris Center with the Athlete Health Organization to provide free sports physicals for over 1,000 high school students in Philly.   Every student will receive an ECG exam.</p>
<p>The second approach is REACTION; how do we respond when a child collapses.  By having AED devices spread throughout our communities, and a population that knows how to perform CPR, we will save lives when sudden cardiac arrest strikes.</p>
<p>The third approach is EDUCATION. The Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act accomplishes this.  Representative Mike Vereb summed it up best &#8211; he said that sudden cardiac arrest is now a household term.  Parents will now be AWARE that sudden cardiac arrest kills at least 2,000 students every year and they’ll guard against it.</p>
<p>Coaches will now be AWARE that fainting is not acceptable and Gatorade is not the remedy.  As a State, we will take these symptoms seriously and do a better job of protecting our children.</p>
<p>This is a tremendous step forward in our quest to save young lives.  We are so proud to be a part of it.</p>
<p>I’d like to close on a personal note.  Phyllis and I cherish this moment.  Simon would have been in first grade this year, positioned nicely in between our daughter, Sally and our son, Jaden.   We are so happy that they are here with us today.</p>
<p>We’re never going to get to go to Simon’s soccer games, choir concerts or graduations. Our moments with him are limited. This bill signing is one of those moments.  This is our ceremony for him.</p>
<p>Finally, I want to share a phrase from one of our favorite songs.</p>
<p>You&#8217;ll be with me; Like a handprint on my heart. And now whatever way our stories end; I know you have re-written mine</p>
<p>This legislation will be the handprint of Simon and Representative Mike Vereb on the hearts of children throughout Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-bill-signing-our-remarks/">The Bill Signing &#8211; Our Remarks</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Party From the Heart</title>
		<link>/blog/a-party-from-the-heart/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Apr 2012 00:32:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Past Events]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3588</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Last night, an organization of twenty-five women, threw a party for Simon&#8217;s Fund.  They&#8217;ve been having fundraisers for nonprofit organizations for 25 years. Over 200 people gathered to bid on great auction items, eat and drink and watch a fashion show presented by Neiman Marcus.  We are so grateful.  Here is the speech that Phyllis [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/a-party-from-the-heart/">A Party From the Heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Last night, an organization of twenty-five women, threw a party for Simon&#8217;s Fund.  They&#8217;ve been having fundraisers for nonprofit organizations for 25 years. Over 200 people gathered to bid on great auction items, eat and drink and watch a fashion show presented by Neiman Marcus.  We are so grateful.  Here is the speech that Phyllis shared.</em></p>
<p>When your child dies, you feel alone.  No one can comprehend the grief.  Few know what to say.  And then one day, you start to encounter random acts of kindness from strangers that would never have come your way.</p>
<p>The sixty-something man that came to our house to lead a shiva minyan – his first time, ever.  The woman who created our ad book for the very first Simon’s Soiree. The student with a heart condition that reached out to volunteer after reading about Simon’s Fund in the paper. The company that donated medical equipment from a cold call.</p>
<p>Then, there’s the story about a bunch of women who just want to help.  For 25 years, From the Heart has been raising money for local nonprofits.  They’ve channeled their time, energy and money toward helping women in need, people living with disease or disability, and children.  Their network has raised over $1,000,000.</p>
<p>We are so humbled and honored to be this year’s beneficiary.  Thankfully, most of you in this room will never know what it feels like to lose a child.  However, we hope that everyone in this room will one day feel what it is like to be honored by a group of woman with big hearts.  It fills your heart.  It soothes your soul.</p>
<p>Thank you so much for honoring our son, Simon, tonight.  He would have been seven years old and finishing first grade.  Thanks for recognizing the efforts and accomplishments of Simon’s Fund.  Thanks for helping us raise awareness.  Thanks for helping us raise money so that we can continue to check hearts and save lives.</p>
<p>We’ve prepared a brief video to share with you tonight, but want to take a moment to introduce you to three special groups of people.</p>
<p>First, will all of the people that have attended a Simon’s Fund event in the past please stand up.  These are the people that have funded the heart screenings that have checked almost 4,000 children.  Thanks from the bottom of our heart.</p>
<p>Second, will the Simon’s Fund board members and Jill Deeves please stand up.  This dedicated group has helped position Simon’s Fund so that it can impact the lives of children through heart screenings, cookie drives, medical partnership and advocacy efforts.</p>
<p>Finally, our third group.  This is a very special group.  Alaysia Keeley, Drew Harrington and Melissa Fair. They are three of the 36 children that have discovered heart conditions at our heart screenings.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/a-party-from-the-heart/">A Party From the Heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Full Circle of Simon&#8217;s Day</title>
		<link>/blog/the-full-circle-of-simons-day/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2012 13:18:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Past Events]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3560</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The very first Simon&#8217;s Day was held at the World Cafe Live on Simon&#8217;s first birthday (October 21, 2006).  At that event, 80 friends (adults and kids) listened to the music of Erin Flynn.  We also had a mini-heart screening.  We came together to remember Simon.  A few years later, Simon&#8217;s Day became our annual [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-full-circle-of-simons-day/">The Full Circle of Simon&#8217;s Day</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The very first Simon&#8217;s Day was held at the World Cafe Live on Simon&#8217;s first birthday (October 21, 2006).  At that event, 80 friends (adults and kids) listened to the music of Erin Flynn.  We also had a mini-heart screening.  We came together to remember Simon.  A few years later, Simon&#8217;s Day became our annual fundraiser.  We invited families, not just adults, to help us raise money to check hearts and save lives.</p>
<p>On March 13, 2012, we came full circle.  We abandoned the fundraising component, and gathered families for an entertainment lalapalooza for kids, just because.  We wanted to celebrate together.  We wanted to remember Simon together.  We wanted to raise awareness together.</p>
<p>At Simon&#8217;s Day, over 300 people gathered at the Ambler Theater to be entrained by the Great Holtzie (comedian), John Pizzi (ventriloquist) and Scott Alexander (magician). They danced with the Phillie Phanatic, who also got an ECG exam.  The entered a heart art contest, got airbrush tattoos, decorated heart cookies and ate lots and lots of food.  They watched basketball and concerts on the big screens.  They met students that discovered heart conditions at Simon&#8217;s Fund heart screenings.</p>
<p>We&#8217;re lucky that we can take moment to just celebrate with families that benefit from our mission.  Of course, we need to raise money to continue our good work, but for that day . . . Simon&#8217;s Day . . . we just smiled.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-full-circle-of-simons-day/">The Full Circle of Simon&#8217;s Day</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Great Friend to Kids Award</title>
		<link>/blog/great-friend-to-kids-award/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2010 03:22:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Past Events]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1020</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Tonight, Simon&#8217;s Fund received the Great Friend to Kids Award presented by Please Touch Museum.  It was a very special evening.  Our remarks are below . . . We are so honored to receive this award tonight and to be in the company of so many other great organizations. We want to thank Please Touch [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/great-friend-to-kids-award/">Great Friend to Kids Award</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tonight, Simon&#8217;s Fund received the Great Friend to Kids Award presented by Please Touch Museum.  It was a very special evening.  Our remarks are below . . .</p>
<p>We are so honored to receive this award tonight and to be in the company of so many other great organizations.</p>
<p>We want to thank Please Touch Museum for having an award like this and for choosing us to receive it this year. By recognizing us, you have done so much to raise awareness for our cause and we really appreciate that.</p>
<p>We want to thank our friends, family, board members, medical advisory board, volunteers and supporters. They have been the driving force behind Simon’s Fund and the reason that we are here tonight.</p>
<p>We want to give a special thanks to Hallee Adelman – for what she’s done for us and what she does for Please Touch Museum.</p>
<p>We want to thank the Cardiac Team at Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia and the Pediatric Team at Abington Memorial Hospital.  They have given us channels to direct our energy and make differences in the lives of children.</p>
<p>Since Simon died almost six years ago, thousands of children have died from sudden cardiac arrest.  Since we were nominated for this award, we’ve read articles about nine student athletes that dropped dead &#8211; Devonte Bundley, Akhir Frazier, Reggie Garrett, Jesus Cruz, Jospin Milandu, Patrick Dinsmore, Jorden T. Pond, Dillon Menard, Larsan Korvili.</p>
<p>We still have lots of hearts to check.  We still have lots of work to do.   We know that 1 or 2 out of every 100 children have a potentially fatal heart condition.  It is cheap to check a child’s heart – about $50.  We think that checking hearts should be a standard of care, like eye exams, hearing exams and dental exams.</p>
<p>On a very personal note, Simon’s sixth birthday is two weeks from tonight.  We won’t be having a party.  We know that we will never be able to attend an assembly, concert, game, event or ceremony for Simon.  So, thank you for giving us the next best thing here tonight – this award to honor his memory.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/great-friend-to-kids-award/">Great Friend to Kids Award</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sex and the City II for Simon&#8217;s Fund</title>
		<link>/blog/sex-and-the-city-ii-for-simons-fund/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2010 02:00:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Past Events]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=880</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>When we purchased Simon’s Fund Sex and the City II package offered at Simon&#8217;s Day, we were confident of two things. First, the money was going to an amazing cause, one that is dear to our hearts, and will be spent to help safeguard the lives of children in our region. Second, we will have [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/sex-and-the-city-ii-for-simons-fund/">Sex and the City II for Simon&#8217;s Fund</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/Suzy.jpg"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-881" title="Suzy Goldstein at the World Premiere" src="https://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/Suzy.jpg" alt="Suzy Goldstein at the World Premiere" width="289" height="468" /></a>When we purchased Simon’s Fund Sex and the City II package offered at Simon&#8217;s Day, we were confident of two things. First, the money was going to an amazing cause, one that is dear to our hearts, and will be spent to help safeguard the lives of children in our region. Second, we will have a great time celebrating Jill’s special birthday together. What we were not prepared for was what an unbelievable experience we were about to have!</p>
<p>After checking in to the Ritz Carlton on Central Park South for two nights to a club room overlooking the park, we were chauffeured by the hotel to the premiere. We were ecstatic to find that our seats were up front, at the center of all the excitement. We were surrounded by A-list celebrities (Donald and Melania Trump, Jerry and Jessica Seinfeld, and Gayle King to name a few), with everyone decked out for New York City’s premiere of the year!</p>
<p>After the movie was introduced by its producers and by Sarah Jessica Parker, we were shuttled in movie themed double-decker bus to the after-party.  The party was magnificent, an outdoor Moroccan themed party, with delicious food, and, of course, the best Cosmopolitans we have ever tasted.  We were right in the center of all of the excitement, with opportunities to speak at length to many celebrities.  We took every opportunity to discuss Simon’s Fund and felt extremely proud to promote the cause.  The experience far exceeded both of our expectations. The entire evening was unforgettable and only outshined by the knowledge that our enjoyment helped to support a wonderful, amazing cause.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/sex-and-the-city-ii-for-simons-fund/">Sex and the City II for Simon&#8217;s Fund</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Simon&#8217;s Day &#8211; Fun &#038; Fundraising</title>
		<link>/blog/simons-day-fun-fundraising/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2010 21:26:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Past Events]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=766</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>On May 2, the Ambler Theater was transformed into a family celebration.  Kids laughed at the Great Holtzie, danced to Alex and the Kaleidoscope Band and were mesmerized by Michael Bonacci&#8217;s magic.  We even spotted a few parents hiding out in the theaters watching classic Looney Toons and Sports Bloopers. Fun was a key ingredient of the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/simons-day-fun-fundraising/">Simon&#8217;s Day &#8211; Fun &#038; Fundraising</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-family: Trebuchet MS,Helvetica;">On May 2, the Ambler Theater was transformed into a family celebration.  Kids laughed at the Great Holtzie, danced to Alex and the Kaleidoscope Band and were mesmerized by Michael Bonacci&#8217;s magic.  We even spotted a few parents hiding out in the theaters watching classic Looney Toons and Sports Bloopers.</span></p>
<p>Fun was a key ingredient of the day, but so was saving more lives.  To that end, we raised over $80,000.  At Simon&#8217;s Fund, we convert dollars raised into lives saved.  It costs $50 for us to screen a child&#8217;s heart.  For every 100 children we screen, one will discover a potentially fatal heart defect.  As a result of Simon&#8217;s Day, we can screen 1,600 more children and save sixteen more lives.</p>
<p>Five years ago, we tried to turn our tragedy into hope.  Now, five years later, it&#8217;s a reality.  Thanks to everyone for their generosity, and for helping us to save one child&#8217;s life . . . and then another by raising awareness about conditions that lead to sudden cardiac arrest and death.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/simons-day-fun-fundraising/">Simon&#8217;s Day &#8211; Fun &#038; Fundraising</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
