<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>SIDS Archives -</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/sids/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Protecting Hearts and Saving Lives</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 17:13:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/simons-fav-icon1.png</url>
	<title>SIDS Archives -</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>My Perspective Changed Forever</title>
		<link>/blog/my-perspective-changed-forever/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Simon's Heart]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 17:09:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[A Parent's Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Life After SCA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SIDS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9184</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I remember like it was yesterday. Phyllis and I had to escape from life. We had just passed the first anniversary of Simon&#8217;s death. We took Sally to the beach. It was so hard to be around people with babies. It was even harder to hear about &#8220;problems.&#8221; I&#8217;m really sorry your contractor didn&#8217;t show up. It&#8217;s just [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/my-perspective-changed-forever/">My Perspective Changed Forever</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I remember like it was yesterday. Phyllis and I had to escape from life. We had just passed the first anniversary of Simon&#8217;s death. We took Sally to the beach.</p>
<p>It was so hard to be around people with babies. It was even harder to hear about &#8220;problems.&#8221; I&#8217;m really sorry your contractor didn&#8217;t show up. It&#8217;s just awful that you had to work all weekend. We couldn&#8217;t deal with all of this. Let&#8217;s say that we needed some social distancing.</p>
<p>Bitterness and resentment are best friends with tragedy and adversity. This is especially true when life shatters your expectations. I knew how life was <em>supposed</em> to work. I grow up. I start a family. I have kids. I watch them grow up and raise their family. Then I pass on. But, that&#8217;s not my life. I was being singled out.</p>
<h4><span style="color: #fc0505;">Something happened on the beach that day and it went something like this.</span></h4>
<p>What if that is not the way life is supposed to work. Sure, it happens that way for most people I know, but that is because they are blessed and fortunate. What happens if examine the lives of the 6.6 billion people around the world? Does life really work out that way? Probably not.</p>
<p>Do I really get to expect my son to reach a certain age? What happens if I reset my expectations to zero days? Can I convince myself to be grateful for the 96 days I had?</p>
<p>Last week, someone on the news suggested that social distancing is not in place to prevent me from catching COVID-19. It is preventing me from infecting someone else. I need to assume that I am infected. Hmmm. Perspective.</p>
<p>As we shelter in place, search for a new normal, and face varying levels of adversity, I hope that you and your family can find a healthy perspective to get you through these challenging times. This too shall pass.</p>
<p><span style="color: #fc080c;">&#8211;<em>Darren Sudman,</em> <em>CEO, Co-Founder and Simon&#8217;s Dad</em></span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/my-perspective-changed-forever/">My Perspective Changed Forever</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rethinking SIDS: Many Deaths No Longer A Mystery</title>
		<link>/blog/rethinking-sids-many-deaths-no-longer-a-mystery/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[creativemms]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2011 19:28:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[SIDS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=1907</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The coroner said that Simon died of SIDS.  However, that answer was not good enough for us because it doesn&#8217;t really mean anything.  I&#8217;m glad that other people are starting to dig deeper into SIDS .  However, I&#8217;m very disappointed that this article only talks about back to sleep campaigns.  There is a Mayo Clinic [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/rethinking-sids-many-deaths-no-longer-a-mystery/">Rethinking SIDS: Many Deaths No Longer A Mystery</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The coroner said that Simon died of SIDS.  However, that answer was not good enough for us because it doesn&#8217;t really mean anything.  I&#8217;m glad that other people are starting to dig deeper into SIDS .  However, I&#8217;m very disappointed that this article only talks about back to sleep campaigns.  There is a Mayo Clinic study that shows that Long QT Syndrome is responsible for up to 15% of SIDS deaths.  Why aren&#8217;t we talking about that?  </em></p>
<p>The thought of a baby dying suddenly and unexpectedly is one that keeps parents awake at night, fearing the worst. For years, little was known about sudden infant death syndrome, or SIDS. Babies would die in their sleep, and it was presumed that little could be done to prevent those deaths.</p>
<p>Today in the U.S., more than 2,000 babies die of SIDS every year, according to government figures.</p>
<p>But the mystery surrounding SIDS is not what it once was. Many SIDS deaths are now believed to be accidents caused by unsafe sleep practices. And some are questioning whether the term SIDS remains relevant at all.</p>
<p><strong>SIDS: A &#8216;Diagnosis Of Exclusion&#8217;</strong></p>
<p>In Wayne County, Mich., 50 to 60 infants die suddenly and unexpectedly each year, most of them in Detroit.</p>
<p>For the past 11 years, the task of investigating those cases has fallen to Pat Tackitt, a pediatric mortality investigator for the Wayne County Medical Examiner&#8217;s Office.</p>
<p>When an infant dies, law enforcement will contact her. She&#8217;ll head out immediately to the family&#8217;s home, spending anywhere from one to five hours talking with the family, using a doll to help parents re-enact what happened.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.npr.org/2011/07/15/137859024/rethinking-sids-many-deaths-no-longer-a-mystery">Full Story</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/rethinking-sids-many-deaths-no-longer-a-mystery/">Rethinking SIDS: Many Deaths No Longer A Mystery</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Misleading &#8211; Autopsy Show SIDS</title>
		<link>/blog/misleading-autopsy-show-sids/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2010 21:51:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[SIDS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsfund.org/?p=792</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>An autopsy cannot show SIDS.  An autopsy can only rule out other things.  This is irresponsible reporting, or worse, an irresponsible finding. A report from the Hamilton County Medical Examiner&#8217;s office says that 9-month-old Ryder Brown died of &#8220;Sudden Infant Death Syndrome,&#8221; commonly known as SIDS. The child was found dead in an East Brainerd [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/misleading-autopsy-show-sids/">Misleading &#8211; Autopsy Show SIDS</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>An autopsy cannot show SIDS.  An autopsy can only rule out other things.  This is irresponsible reporting, or worse, an irresponsible finding.</p>
<p>A report from the Hamilton County Medical Examiner&#8217;s office says that 9-month-old Ryder Brown died of &#8220;Sudden Infant Death Syndrome,&#8221; commonly known as SIDS.</p>
<p>The child was found dead in an East Brainerd apartment May 12.</p>
<p>The report says all toxicology tests were negative, there were no outward signs of trauma, physical abuse or injury by drugs or alcohol and the child had no known medical history.</p>
<p>The babysitter, Julie Jack, was charged with aggravated child neglect after she left the child in the care of another person who police say was unfit to care for a child. That person has not been charged. Jennifer Bruce, the child&#8217;s mother, told NewsChannel 9 &#8220;He was the one that was completely incoherent and messed up on all kinds of pills.&#8221;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/misleading-autopsy-show-sids/">Misleading &#8211; Autopsy Show SIDS</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
