<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>&#8211; Simon&#039;s Heart</title>
	<atom:link href="/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Protecting Hearts and Saving Lives</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2021 18:29:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/simons-fav-icon1.png</url>
	<title>&#8211; Simon&#039;s Heart</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Philadelphia Phillies</title>
		<link>/blog/philadelphia-phillies/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarita Rajpoot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 13:09:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9930</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Simon’s Heart is the proud recipient of a $20,000 grant from Phillies Charities, Inc. Grants were provided in part from the support of Phillies fans who participated in the team’s auctions, raffles and memorabilia events held this past baseball season. Upon learning of the grant, Simon’s Heart Executive Director Jenn Parrado said, “The support of [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/philadelphia-phillies/">Philadelphia Phillies</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Simon’s Heart is the proud recipient of a $20,000 grant from Phillies Charities, Inc. Grants were provided in part from the support of Phillies fans who participated in the team’s auctions, raffles and memorabilia events held this past baseball season. Upon learning of the grant, Simon’s Heart Executive Director Jenn Parrado said, “The support of the Philadelphia Phillies means the world to Simon’s Heart because sudden cardiac arrest is the #1 cause of death in youth athletes. We are grateful to share our mission and save lives!”</p>
<p>The generous grant will be used to provide free heart screenings, AEDs where children learn and play, and CPR Education in communities so that young hearts are protected long into the future. “These remarkable organizations continuously step up to the plate to be there for those who need it most,” said Phillies Charities, Inc. President John Weber. “Thanks to our fans, we are able to help ensure that the much-needed services of our community heroes can continue to make a difference all year long.”</p>
<p>About Simon’s Heart:<br />
SIMON’S HEART is a 501(c)(3) founded in memory of 3-month-old Simon Sudman who died suddenly from an undetected heart condition. The organization is committed to a future in which parents and communities don’t lose children to detectable and treatable heart conditions.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/philadelphia-phillies/">Philadelphia Phillies</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Club saves lives while fundraising during pandemic</title>
		<link>/blog/club-saves-lives-while-fundraising-during-pandemic/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarita Rajpoot]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 12:55:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[AED Save]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9926</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>WHAT: Colonial Soccer Club is taking steps to protect hearts and place AEDs throughout the Plymouth Meeting, Whitemarsh, and Conshohocken region. The Louis T. Savino, III Foundation and Simon’s Heart collaborated with Colonial Soccer to fund 9 AEDs to 13 soccer fields. AEDs and CPR Education will be provided during the Bill Lapp Soccer Tournament. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/club-saves-lives-while-fundraising-during-pandemic/">Club saves lives while fundraising during pandemic</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>WHAT: Colonial Soccer Club is taking steps to protect hearts and place AEDs throughout the Plymouth Meeting, Whitemarsh, and Conshohocken region. The Louis T. Savino, III Foundation and Simon’s Heart collaborated with Colonial Soccer to fund 9 AEDs to 13 soccer fields. AEDs and CPR Education will be provided during the Bill Lapp Soccer Tournament. Athletes will grab a ball, pick a song, and push to the beat. Surprise, they’re learning CPR! The Club looks to deepen their fundraising efforts to provide 3 more AEDs and further heart safety education in the community before the end of 2021.</p>
<p>WHO: Colonial Soccer Club | Louis T. Savino, III Foundation | Simon’s Heart | 5,000 spectators</p>
<p>WHEN: Saturday October 16th, 2021 | Bill Lapp Soccer Tournament</p>
<p>WHERE: Victory Fields | 201 E Germantown Pike, Colonial Dr, Lafayette Hill, PA</p>
<p>WHY: Sudden Cardiac Arrest isn’t just an adult thing. It is the #1 cause of death of student athletes and takes the lives of thousands of students every year. Colonial Soccer Club partners with The Louis T. Savino, III Foundation and Simon’s Heart to protect<br />
hearts and save lives.</p>
<p>COLONIAL SOCCER CLUB | A note from Brian Cammarota, Health + Safety Coordinator | “It has been a dream of mine to assure that every heart is protected every day on Colonial Soccer Club fields. Thank you to the Louis T. Savino, III Foundation and Simon’s Heart.” <a href="https://www.colonialsoccerclub.org/">www.colonialsoccerclub.org</a></p>
<p>LOUIS T. SAVINO, III FOUNDATION was founded in memory of Louis who died suddenly in 2000 at the age of 15 on a soccer field from an undetected heart condition. An AED could have saved his life. The Foundation is dedicated to increasing awareness of, and preventing, sudden cardiac death (SCD) in youth. <a href="http://www.savinofoundation.org/">www.savinofoundation.org</a></p>
<p>SIMON’S HEART is a 501(c)(3) founded in memory of 3 month old Simon Sudman who died suddenly from an undetected heart condition. The organization is committed to a future in which parents and communities don’t lose children to detectable and treatable heart conditions. <a href="/">www.simonsheart.org</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/club-saves-lives-while-fundraising-during-pandemic/">Club saves lives while fundraising during pandemic</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Welcome, Dominic Folino, to Simon’s Heart!</title>
		<link>/blog/welcome-dominic-folino-to-simons-heart/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jenn Parrado]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2021 07:05:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9845</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>With all eyes on our children as they return to school, it’s more important than ever to continue advocating to protect hearts. For 17 years we have advocated for coaches, athletes, and families to receive education about the signs of Sudden Cardiac Arrest (SCA). In 2012, Simon’s Heart advocacy efforts led Pennsylvania to become the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/welcome-dominic-folino-to-simons-heart/">Welcome, Dominic Folino, to Simon’s Heart!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With all eyes on our children as they return to school, it’s more important than ever to continue advocating to protect hearts. For 17 years we have advocated for coaches, athletes, and families to receive education about the signs of Sudden Cardiac Arrest (SCA). In 2012, Simon’s Heart advocacy efforts led </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Pennsylvania to become the first state in the country to protect students from sudden cardiac arrest. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Since then, fifteen states have followed suit and adopted new legislation to protect hearts.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I’m pleased to share that this month, Dominic Folino has joined our </span><a href="/leadership/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">board of directors</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> as the Director of Advocacy where he’ll spearhead our efforts to expand the <a href="/sudden-cardiac-arrest-prevention-act/">SCA Prevention Act</a> to all 50 states. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dom is the President of Spectrum Strategies where his focus is on government affairs, business development, strategic planning, and blockchain education and solutions for various organizations. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Formerly, Dominic was the Vice President of External Affairs at FS Investments. He helped manage the firm&#8217;s political, lobbying, charitable, and community initiatives, including FS&#8217;s political action committee and its charitable affiliate, The FS Foundation.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Before joining FS Investments, Dominic served as the Executive Director of Volunteer Medical Services Corps of Lower Merion and Narberth. He began his career in politics working for various campaigns in Philadelphia and the surrounding area. Dominic also served as Chief of Staff to a member of the Pennsylvania House of Representatives. Service to the community has always been important to Dominic. He helped start the FS Foundation and currently serves as the advisory board co-chair for Volunteer Medical Services Corp of Lower Merion and Narberth and is a board member of the Police Athletic League.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dominic is a graduate of La Salle University. He also completed the Accelerated Management Program at the Yale School of Management and is currently pursuing an MBA at Villanova University.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Thank you, Dom, for protecting hearts and saving lives with us.</span></p>
<p><span class="il">Jenn</span> Parrado | Executive Director</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/welcome-dominic-folino-to-simons-heart/">Welcome, Dominic Folino, to Simon’s Heart!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Covid-19 and the Heart</title>
		<link>/blog/covid-19-and-the-heart/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jenn Parrado]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2021 14:39:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Medical]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9795</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic is due to a severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and was first reported in late 2019. This virus has had a massive global impact resulting in the deaths of millions of people. COVID-19 has a broad range of clinical presentations from completely asymptomatic to affecting every organ system [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/covid-19-and-the-heart/">Covid-19 and the Heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic is due to a severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and was first reported in late 2019. This virus has had a massive global impact resulting in the deaths of millions of people. COVID-19 has a broad range of clinical presentations from completely asymptomatic to affecting every organ system of the body.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Based on data collected during the pandemic, we know that individuals with cardiovascular disease are at increased risk of death or severe illness from COVID-19. The virus is dangerous not only to those with preexisting heart disease, but to those with no preexisting medical conditions at all.</span></p>
<h2><b>COVID-19 can damage the heart muscle in many ways</b></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The virus can either directly damage the heart itself, or it can cause secondary damage due to the inflammatory response caused by the virus affecting other organs in the body. Generally, this secondary damage to the heart is due to increased demands on the heart combined with limited oxygen availability to the heart. In order for the heart to pump blood effectively, it needs to be supplied with enough oxygen.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When the heart is not supplied with the amount of oxygen it needs to perform the work that is required of it, damage to the heart muscle occurs. This oxygen supply and demand mismatch is what leads to the various types of heart attacks.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Additionally, damage can result from inflammation in the heart due to an inappropriate immune system response to the infection. It has become increasingly clear that this inflammatory immune response to the infection is responsible for some of the devastating consequences of the COVID-19 infection.</span></p>
<h2><strong>What tests can be used to detect heart muscle damage?</strong></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There have been many studies looking at blood tests and imaging studies to detect damage to the heart caused by COVID-19. Though the field of evidence is still growing, it is well known that individuals who become severely ill with COVID-19, or who have to be hospitalized, are at a relatively high risk of having damage to the heart.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Blood levels of troponin, a heart muscle enzyme, can be used to detect damage to the heart muscle. In addition to blood test, ultrasound imaging of the heart or computed tomography or magnetic resonance imaging of the heart can be used to detect the inflammation or damage caused by the infection.</span></p>
<h2><b>How does a virus affect the heart?</b></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are multiple possible ways that viral infections such as influenza or COVID-19 can affect the heart. One of the most common forms of heart muscle damage from viral infections is myocarditis, or inflammation of the heart muscle. This has been well described in individuals who have viral infections such as COVID-19 and the symptoms that occur are variable.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Some individuals are asymptomatic, while others become severely ill and require hospitalization. In addition to direct viral infection and damage to the heart, cardiac damage from COVID-19 and other viral infections can be due to the systemic inflammation that often occurs.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Specifically for COVID-19, based on the risk of heart muscle damage from symptomatic infection, it has been recommended that those individuals who develop severe symptoms such as chest pain or shortness of breath be evaluated for cardiac risk stratification to determine whether any damage has occurred, and to ensure that it is safe to resume regular activity.</span></p>
<h2><b>What symptoms might I have if COVID-19 has affected my heart?</b></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Symptoms can range in severity from none at all to severe chest pain and shortness of breath. For individuals who are having shortness of breath, chest pain, or signs of low oxygen levels, it is important to seek medical attention so a physician can provide supportive care and determine if additional therapies are needed.</span></p>
<h2><strong>When should I see a doctor to make sure my heart is healthy after COVID-19, and when can I return to exercise?</strong></h2>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You should see a doctor for a cardiac evaluation if you had moderate to severe COVID-19, are age 65 or older, or experienced any cardiovascular symptoms. It recommended that individuals quarantine for a 10-day period after initial diagnosis of infection.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For athletes, even if asymptomatic, it is recommended to abstain from exercise for 10 days before gradual supervised resumption.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For those who had moderate to severe symptoms, those with pre-existing cardiovascular conditions, those with prolonged symptoms (&gt;10 days), and those older than 65, it is reasonable to undergo cardiovascular risk stratification to ensure it is safe to resume exercise.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If cardiac involvement is diagnosed during the post COVID-19 infection period, then return to physical activity should be delayed until determined to be safe from a physician.</span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/covid-19-and-the-heart/">Covid-19 and the Heart</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Next Chapter &#8211; A New Leader</title>
		<link>/blog/the-next-chapter-a-new-leader/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 12:08:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9416</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Today marks another milestone in my journey since the loss of Simon. I step down as Executive Director of Simon’s Heart and welcome Jennifer Parrado with open arms. Jenn comes to us from the Leukemia &#038; Lymphoma Society where she served as the Regional Advancement Director. She has spent the last ten years raising awareness, advocating, and fundraising [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-next-chapter-a-new-leader/">The Next Chapter &#8211; A New Leader</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today marks another milestone in my journey since the loss of Simon. I step down as Executive Director of Simon’s Heart and welcome Jennifer Parrado with open arms.</p>
<p>Jenn comes to us from the Leukemia & Lymphoma Society where she served as the Regional Advancement Director. She has spent the last ten years raising awareness, advocating, and fundraising for some amazing causes. So, she’s qualified. More importantly, she is smart, considerate, passionate, humble and witty. She possesses the qualities we value.</p>
<p>It was June 2012, right after the Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act was signed into law. Simon’s Heart and Representative Mike Vereb made Pennsylvania the first state to pass legislation to protect student athletes <u>from</u> sudden cardiac arrest.  The law requires coaches, parents and students to learn about the risks and warning signs of sudden cardiac arrest. Athletes who are symptomatic must be removed from play and cannot return until cleared by a licensed medical professional.</p>
<p>As we celebrated this major accomplishment, the board asked me a question. If you can host heart screenings and pass a law as a part-time volunteer, what can we accomplish if you do this full time? I had major reservations about making a career out of my loss. I’ll never forget the advice my friend and business partner gave me. Imagine yourself five years from now. Our business and Simon’s Heart are both doing great. Which one makes you more excited and proud?  That’s where you should work. I am so blessed to have wise friends.</p>
<p>The Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act has become law in fourteen states. Every year, two million student athletes across the country, along with their parents and coaches, learn about sudden cardiac arrest. Over one million coaches have been educated by our training video. We have provided heart screenings for 18,000 + students. Data from our registry has been used to publish seven abstracts and two manuscripts. We partnered with the NCAA to fund research. We introduced a new way to teach kids about CPR using music and balls. We placed hundreds of AED devices in youth-related facilities through partnerships with sports teams and our crowdfunding site. We provide educational materials to youth organizations around the country to educate their students.</p>
<p>I am so proud of this organization &#8211; family, co-workers, supporters and partners &#8211; for all of these accomplishments. In the face of unimaginable tragedy, we responded with innovative programs that protect hearts and save lives. It’s hard to believe it’s been fifteen years. I can still feel the energy and urgency that existed when we began.</p>
<p>How do I know I’m making the right decision to step down? I don’t. But, I try to imagine Simon’s Heart five years from now. It’s bigger and better. It has impacted more families and helped change a standard of care. Jenn and Jill are running the show (with others too, hopefully). All of you are rallying behind them. I am contributing as a co-founder and board member.</p>
<p>This vision makes me the most proud and excited. It reveals an impactful, sustainable and lifesaving organization.</p>
<p>Jenn and Jill, my family and the board of directors can’t wait to see the places you’ll go. We’ll be right beside you.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-next-chapter-a-new-leader/">The Next Chapter &#8211; A New Leader</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is Cardiac Arrest Contagious?</title>
		<link>/blog/is-cardiac-arrest-contagious/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 16:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9403</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Sudden cardiac arrest is what happens when the heart stops beating suddenly and unexpectedly. It is the leading cause of death of adults in this country. However, it is not just an adult thing. It is linked to 10% of SIDS deaths; is the leading cause of death of student athletes; and takes the lives of thousands [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/is-cardiac-arrest-contagious/">Is Cardiac Arrest Contagious?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sudden cardiac arrest is what happens when the heart stops beating suddenly and unexpectedly. It is the leading cause of death of adults in this country. However, it is not just an adult thing. It is linked to 10% of SIDS deaths; is the leading cause of death of student athletes; and takes the lives of thousands of children every year.</p>
<p>Is it contagious?</p>
<p>Last week, two stories broke about the risk of sudden cardiac arrest in athletes. <a href="https://default.salsalabs.org/T7b4e93da-f726-4210-8658-d766c99c2d60/7215b599-ddb2-485e-bbac-830cd681e0da" target="_top" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cameron Smith</a>, a twenty-four year old linebacker with the Minnesota Vikings, discovered a heart condition (bicuspid aortic valve) after being diagnosed with COVID-19. Biscupid aortic valve is a condition where the aortic valve has two leaflets instead of three. The aortic valve regulates blood flow from heart to the aorta. This is a structural heart condition and is usually inherited.</p>
<p>Then, the <a href="https://default.salsalabs.org/Tea5fc6e9-4348-46c4-8761-209c7c9ca843/7215b599-ddb2-485e-bbac-830cd681e0da" target="_top" rel="noopener noreferrer">Big Ten reported</a> at least ten players were diagnosed with myocarditis after testing positive for COVID-19. Myocarditis is an inflammation of the heart muscle (called myocardium) that limits the heart&#8217;s ability to pump blood. This condition is also structural, but it is acquired. It is caused by things like a virus or a drug interaction.</p>
<p>&#8220;We know that COVID-19 can attack the heart, said David Shipon, a cardiologist at Jefferson University Hospital and Chief Medical Officer of Simon&#8217;s Heart. &#8220;Typically, the worse the symptoms are from COVID, the greater the likelihood that the heart will become inflamed. But, all physically active individuals who are diagnosed with COVID should get their hearts screened because we are still learning about the effects of this virus.&#8221;</p>
<p>These stories amplify our message &#8211; testing and screening are so important. It is not enough for us to assume that Cameron&#8217;s heart was healthy for the first two decades of his life. He and all of his high school classmates should have been screened. He is an elite athlete. He won a state championship in high school, played at USC for four years, and was drafted by the NFL. Should he have to wait for a pandemic to find something so significant?</p>
<p>The case of the Big Ten players underscores the importance of screening for a different reason. It is not enough to report positive tests, hospitalizations and fatalities of COVID-19. We need to understand how this virus is compromising the hearts and other parts of our children. Over <a href="https://default.salsalabs.org/T39fefe37-5b25-41b0-83cd-e8f24d98b515/7215b599-ddb2-485e-bbac-830cd681e0da" target="_top" rel="noopener noreferrer">300,000</a> children have tested positive for coronavirus, and while the mortality rate is very low today, how many of these children will suffer from heart failure or cardiac arrest in the future? We won&#8217;t know unless we screen and conduct research.</p>
<p>Sudden cardiac arrest is not contagious, although viruses like COVID-19 that can cause myocarditis are. Whether the conditions are inherited or acquired, we can prevent sudden cardiac arrest through screening and research. Our children don&#8217;t have to die from detectable and treatable heart conditions.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/is-cardiac-arrest-contagious/">Is Cardiac Arrest Contagious?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>We Need a Country-Sized AED!</title>
		<link>/blog/we-need-a-country-sized-aed/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 19:05:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9310</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We need a country-sized automated external defibrillator (AED) right now. An AED is the only tool that can save someone in cardiac arrest. If needed, it delivers a lifesaving shock. If we hooked one up to this nation, the machine would run its diagnostics (like it always does) and probably make the following statement – [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/we-need-a-country-sized-aed/">We Need a Country-Sized AED!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We need a country-sized automated external defibrillator (AED) right now. An AED is the only tool that can save someone in cardiac arrest. If needed, it delivers a lifesaving shock.</p>
<p>If we hooked one up to this nation, the machine would run its diagnostics (like it always does) and probably make the following statement – “Assessing society . . . assessing society . . . shock advised.”</p>
<p>This week is CPR/AED Awareness Week. <a href="http://www.simonsheart.org/">Simon’s Heart</a>, and others like it, are supposed to capture your attention and educate you about the importance of CPR and AED devices. It’s not up for debate. These two things – a relatively easy hand motion and a $1000 device – dramatically increase the chance of surviving sudden cardiac arrest. Without them, the chance is about 12%, which is a big deal considering sudden cardiac arrest takes the lives of 350,000 adults every year.</p>
<p>But I can’t. That message has to wait. Our country is hurting. Life seems to be out of control. And, if I’m being honest, heart health is a luxury. Wow, bold statement coming from a guy who lost a son to sudden cardiac arrest, has a wife who lives with a heart condition that can result in sudden cardiac arrest, and runs an organization dedicated to preventing sudden cardiac arrest and death in children.</p>
<p>But it is. How can we expect a mother to care about an AED device at school if the walls are crumbling and there aren’t enough textbooks? Will a father of a seemingly healthy daughter take the time to learn CPR if he lost his job and is behind on rent? Is a student athlete really going to tell his coach about his racing heart if he needs that scholarship and his parents don’t have health insurance?</p>
<p>Can we really expect these families to focus on cardiac arrest? <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6324984/">Studies</a> consistently show that the rate of sudden cardiac death is higher, and occurs at younger ages in the black community. This is a very grim statistic . . . unless you are worried about food, shelter or security.</p>
<p>In the United States, <a href="https://www.kidsdata.org/topic/295/infantmortality-race/table#fmt=2749&loc=1&tf=107&ch=7,11,8,10,9,73,1436&sortColumnId=0&sortType=asc">infant mortality</a> is two times higher among blacks than whites. African American children are <a href="https://uncf.org/pages/k-12-disparity-facts-and-stats">less likely</a> to be college-ready, and more likely to be suspended than white children. African Americans are five times more likely to be incarcerated than whites. African Americans are two times more likely to be <a href="https://www.americanprogress.org/issues/economy/reports/2020/02/24/480743/persistence-black-white-unemployment-gap/">unemployed</a> than whites, and two times more likely to <a href="https://www.povertyusa.org/facts">live in poverty</a>. And, let’s not forget where we were three weeks ago – African Americans are <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/may/20/black-americans-death-rate-covid-19-coronavirus">three times</a> more likely to die from COVID-19.</p>
<p>Simon’s Heart cannot achieve its mission, and America cannot fulfill its promise in the face of such disparity and inequality. The tragic and senseless deaths of Ahmaud Arbery, Breonna Taylor and George Floyd are the latest symptoms that our society is very ill.</p>
<p>In medicine, when one function of the body is threatened, other parts of the body respond to protect and heal it. This must be our path too. We must appreciate and understand the factors that bring harm to our fellow citizens. Then, we must work tirelessly to find a cure. Not a bandaid. Not a painkiller. Not a treatment. A cure.</p>
<p>There are very few instances where our body can function without all parts in working order. I don’t know how many times we need to be reminded that society works the same way. Relationships, friendships, workplaces, sports teams, schools and communities all fare better when everyone feels valued and secure.</p>
<p>Simon’s Heart will continue to do its small part to create a more just and equal society by bringing AED devices and heart screenings to underserved communities where kids learn and play. But our focus is narrow, so we’ll look to these organizations for perspective as we work to restore the collective health of this great country.</p>
<p>Respectfully,<br />
Darren Sudman<br />
CEO, Co-Founder<br />
& Simon&#8217;s Dad</p>
<p>&#8220;It is not your responsibility to finish the work [of perfecting the world], but you are not free to desist from it either.&#8221; Pirkei Avot 2:16</p>
<p><strong>Criminal Justice Reform<br />
</strong><a href="https://fight.org/programs/institute-for-community-justice/">Institute for Community Justice</a> (Philly)<br />
<a href="https://www.sentencingproject.org/about-us/">The Sentencing Project</a> (National)</p>
<p><strong>Police Conduct</strong><br />
<a href="https://www.joincampaignzero.org/#vision">Campaign Zero</a> (National)<br />
<a href="https://noblenational.org/about-us/">NOBLE</a> (National)</p>
<p><strong>Education Inequality</strong><br />
<a href="https://www.steppingstonescholars.org/">Stepping Stones </a>(Philly)<br />
<a href="https://edtrust.org/">The Education Trust </a> (National)</p>
<p><strong>Food Insecurity<br />
</strong><a href="https://www.philabundance.org/about">Philadbundance</a> (Philly)<br />
<a href="https://www.nokidhungry.org/">No Kid Hungry</a> (National)</p>
<p><strong>Infant Mortality<br />
</strong><a href="https://birthequity.org/">National Birth Equity Collaborative</a> (National)</p>
<p><strong>Social Justice</strong><br />
<a href="https://blacklivesmatter.com/about/">Black Lives Matter</a> (National)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/juliawuench/2020/06/02/first-listen-then-learn-anti-racism-resources-for-white-people/#1115142e16ee">Forbes Magazine</a> has compiled a list of resources that promote empathy and understanding around the issues of racism and inequality.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/we-need-a-country-sized-aed/">We Need a Country-Sized AED!</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Simon&#8217;s Heart Begins Executive Search</title>
		<link>/blog/executive-search/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 17:13:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Simon's Heart News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9266</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Today, Darren Sudman, announced that he will stepping down from the day to day operations at Simon&#8217;s Heart this year. Darren and his wife, Phyllis, co-founded the organization fifteen years ago following the sudden and unexpected death of their son, Simon. Over the last eight years, Darren has served as the Executive Director of Simon’s [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/executive-search/">Simon&#8217;s Heart Begins Executive Search</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today, Darren Sudman, announced that he will stepping down from the day to day operations at Simon&#8217;s Heart this year. Darren and his wife, Phyllis, co-founded the organization fifteen years ago following the sudden and unexpected death of their son, Simon. Over the last eight years, Darren has served as the Executive Director of Simon’s Heart and he will continue his work into the Fall to ensure a smooth and successful leadership transition.</p>
<p>As a result, Simon’s Heart is commencing a search for its next inspiring leader and the process will be led by board members, Rayna Jones and Ken Fair. The successful candidate will be curious, passionate and inspiring. S/he will be eager to expand on the programs that have been protecting the lives of children, which include youth heart screenings, a national cardiac registry, a crowdfunding site for AED devices, and a hands-only CPR activation.</p>
<p>“It&#8217;s time for a change,&#8221; said Darren Sudman.  &#8220;After Simon died, there was no obvious path forward. We decided to lean in and use our tragedy to prevent other families from losing children to detectable and treatable heart conditions. The time is right for me to take a step back, exhale and invite another innovative and passionate leader to protect hearts and save lives. I’m excited to see where this leads, and I look forward to serving on the board and being a co-founder. Simon will always be my son and this will always be my cause.&#8221;</p>
<p>“We will miss Darren&#8217;s leadership and passion in day-to-day operations, but we are also excited for the Sudman family,&#8221; said Eldwin Thay, Board Chair.  &#8220;They have sacrificed so much and have shared their grief so publicly to build an organization that educates and engages students and parents about sudden cardiac arrest and death. Simon&#8217;s Heart is in a really good place and we are excited to welcome a new leader to continue our great work in the community.&#8221;</p>
<p>Qualified candidates can find application <a href="/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/ED-Job-Description-Final.pdf">information here.</a></p>
<p>To recommend a candidate, please send an email to <a href="mailto:career@simonsheart.org">career@simonsheart.org</a>.</p>
<p>Darren shares more insight into his decision to step back in this <a href="https://youtu.be/JL8tEWNeKGg">brief video</a>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/executive-search/">Simon&#8217;s Heart Begins Executive Search</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>My Perspective Changed Forever</title>
		<link>/blog/my-perspective-changed-forever/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Simon's Heart]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 17:09:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[A Parent's Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Life After SCA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SIDS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9184</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I remember like it was yesterday. Phyllis and I had to escape from life. We had just passed the first anniversary of Simon&#8217;s death. We took Sally to the beach. It was so hard to be around people with babies. It was even harder to hear about &#8220;problems.&#8221; I&#8217;m really sorry your contractor didn&#8217;t show up. It&#8217;s just [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/my-perspective-changed-forever/">My Perspective Changed Forever</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I remember like it was yesterday. Phyllis and I had to escape from life. We had just passed the first anniversary of Simon&#8217;s death. We took Sally to the beach.</p>
<p>It was so hard to be around people with babies. It was even harder to hear about &#8220;problems.&#8221; I&#8217;m really sorry your contractor didn&#8217;t show up. It&#8217;s just awful that you had to work all weekend. We couldn&#8217;t deal with all of this. Let&#8217;s say that we needed some social distancing.</p>
<p>Bitterness and resentment are best friends with tragedy and adversity. This is especially true when life shatters your expectations. I knew how life was <em>supposed</em> to work. I grow up. I start a family. I have kids. I watch them grow up and raise their family. Then I pass on. But, that&#8217;s not my life. I was being singled out.</p>
<h4><span style="color: #fc0505;">Something happened on the beach that day and it went something like this.</span></h4>
<p>What if that is not the way life is supposed to work. Sure, it happens that way for most people I know, but that is because they are blessed and fortunate. What happens if examine the lives of the 6.6 billion people around the world? Does life really work out that way? Probably not.</p>
<p>Do I really get to expect my son to reach a certain age? What happens if I reset my expectations to zero days? Can I convince myself to be grateful for the 96 days I had?</p>
<p>Last week, someone on the news suggested that social distancing is not in place to prevent me from catching COVID-19. It is preventing me from infecting someone else. I need to assume that I am infected. Hmmm. Perspective.</p>
<p>As we shelter in place, search for a new normal, and face varying levels of adversity, I hope that you and your family can find a healthy perspective to get you through these challenging times. This too shall pass.</p>
<p><span style="color: #fc080c;">&#8211;<em>Darren Sudman,</em> <em>CEO, Co-Founder and Simon&#8217;s Dad</em></span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/my-perspective-changed-forever/">My Perspective Changed Forever</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Please Help Our Restaurants</title>
		<link>/blog/restaurants-that-save-lives/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Simon's Heart]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 20:27:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=9150</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This year, we raised $65,000 at Simon&#8217;s Soiree from the silent auction. A good portion of these proceeds came through the generosity of the dining industry. They donated gift cards and dining experiences. Many took part in our Heart Month campaign to sell wine totes.  They stepped in when we asked for help protecting hearts [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/restaurants-that-save-lives/">Please Help Our Restaurants</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This year, we raised $65,000 at Simon&#8217;s Soiree from the silent auction. A good portion of these proceeds came through the generosity of the dining industry. They donated gift cards and dining experiences. Many took part in our Heart Month campaign to sell <a href="https://secure.simonsfund.org/wine-bag">wine totes</a>.  They stepped in when we asked for help protecting hearts and save lives. Today, they need our help to stay open.</p>
<p>Please support these establishments that remain open for take-out or delivery. We are all in this together.</p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.333belrose.com/"><span style="color: #0000ff;">333 B</span></a><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.333belrose.com/">elrose Bar & Grill</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="http://alicephilly.com/">Alice</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.alicart.com/restaurants">Alicart Restaurants</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://philadelphia.amadarestaurant.com/">Amada</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="http://arpeggiobyob.com/">Arpeggio</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="http://arugulacoldpoint.com/">Arugula Ristorante</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://atthetablebyob.com/">At The Table BYOB</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="http://www.auroragracechocolates.com/">Aurora Grace</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="http://www.azieonmain.com/">Azie</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.barclaycaterers.com/">Barclay Caterers</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="http://benandirvs.com/">Ben & Irv&#8217;s</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://bridgetssteak.com/">Bridget&#8217;s</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.cadencerestaurant.com/">Cadence</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="http://caffeabbracci.com/">Cafe Abbracci</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="http://www.cantinafeliz.com/">Cantina Feliz</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.thecapitalgrille.com/locations/pa/philadelphia/philadelphia/8013">Capital Grill</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://ristorantecastello.com/">Castello&#8217;s</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://cerdorestaurant.com/">Cerdo-Pieri Restaraunt Group</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://christophersaneighborhoodplace.com/">Christopher&#8217;s</a><br />
</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.cornerstonewayne.com/">Cornerstone</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="http://www.dettera.com/">Dettera Restaurant & Wine Bar</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.docksoysterhouse.com/">Dock&#8217;s Oyster House</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.elegancecafe.com/">Elegance Cafe</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.flemingssteakhouse.com/locations/pa/radnor">Fleming&#8217;s</a>, Radnor</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.foxrc.com/restaurant-finder/">Fox’s Restaurant Group</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://fromtheboot.com/ambler-location/">From The Boot</a>, Ambler</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="http://www.infinitycaterers.com/">Infinity Caterers</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.julesthincrust.com/">Jules Thin Crust</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://lovecitybrewing.com/">Love City Brewing Company</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="http://www.moonstruckrestaurant.com/">Moonstruck Restaurant</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.noburestaurants.com/miami/home/">NoBu</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.nothingbundtcakes.com/bakery/pa/king-of-prussia">Nothing Bundt Cakes</a>, King of Prussia</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.patskingofsteaks.com/">Pat’s</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.pepperoncinirestaurant.com/">Pepperonicini Restaurant</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://ripplewoodbar.com/">Ripplewood Whiskey & Craft</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.rouge98.com/">Rouge</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.slyfoxbeer.com/">Sly Fox Brewing Co.</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.allmenus.com/pa/lafayette-hill/288606-sorrentos/menu/">Sorrento&#8217;s</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://starr-restaurants.com/">Starr Restaurants</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.steveandcookies.com/">Steve and Cookies</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.sweetgreen.com/">Sweetgreen</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="http://www.taqueriafeliz.com/">Taqueria Feliz</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.thebercy.com/">The Bercy</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://bluebellinn.com/">The Blue Bell Inn</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://locations.thecheesecakefactory.com/pa/king-of-prussia-46.html">The Cheesecake Factory</a>, King of Prussia</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://farmandfisherman.com/">The Farm & Fisherman</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="http://www.silverspoonwayne.com/">The SILVERSPOON</a>, Wayne</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://victorcafe.com/">The Victor Cafe</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.trattoriacarina.com/">Trattoria Carina</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://tredicibm.com/">Tredici</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.triaphilly.com/location/tria-rittenhouse/">Tria Rittenhouse</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.truefoodkitchen.com/">True Food Kitchen</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://www.twentymanning.com/">Twenty Manning</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="https://urbanfarmerphiladelphia.com/">Urban Farmer</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a style="color: #0000ff;" href="http://urbanvillagebrewing.com/">Urban Village Brewing Company</a></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/restaurants-that-save-lives/">Please Help Our Restaurants</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
