<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Heart Screening Archives -</title>
	<atom:link href="/blog/category/heart-screening/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Protecting Hearts and Saving Lives</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 06:31:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/simons-fav-icon1.png</url>
	<title>Heart Screening Archives -</title>
	<link></link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>What is a Standard of Care?</title>
		<link>/blog/screening-show-us-your/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2019 11:28:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cancer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[heart]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mammogram]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8832</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the past century, we’ve seen extraordinary advances in medicine and technology. The ways we detect, diagnose, and treat disease have changed the course of humankind. Among these changes is the method by which we screen for disease in a seemingly healthy population. It’s called preventative medicine. There is a wide variety of routine screenings [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/screening-show-us-your/">What is a Standard of Care?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the past century, we’ve seen extraordinary advances in medicine and technology. The ways we detect, diagnose, and treat disease have changed the course of humankind. Among these changes is the method by which we screen for disease in a seemingly healthy population. It’s called preventative medicine.</p>
<p>There is a wide variety of routine screenings to help detect and reduce the risk of disease. They are based on factors like age, sex, and family history. Some of the most common are mammograms, colonoscopy, Pap smear, PSA (prostate cancer), and blood glucose. At birth, we screen for genetic disorders and in schools we assess vision and hearing. Today, these tests are routine – part of our standard of care. However, at their inception, their effectiveness and utility were called into question.</p>
<p>The road to standardization was full of research. There were false positives, false negatives, bad techniques and large sums of money spent. However, the results proved the benefits of early detection and intervention. The process is pretty typical when purusing a new standard of care. Costs and mistakes are high in the beginning as we seek to define and understand the unknown. Over time, as our experience and exposure increases, the costs and mistakes subside. We settle into an affordable and effective outcome.</p>
<p>The United States Army was one of the first to implement health screenings (1940). It utlitized mental health screenings in the application process. A standardized pencil and paper test identified at risk men seeking military service. This initiative established the criteria for developing and vetting screening programs.</p>
<p>Screening programs would need to answer the following questions: (1) Does early treatment improve prognosis; (2) how valid and repeatable is the screening test; and (3) among those with a positive screening, how many of them are true cases? And, there would need to be an effective way to treat the disease. Screenings needed to prove their specificity and sensitivity. Be <u>sensitive</u> enough to detect the condition almost every time, and <u>specific</u> enough to find the condition being sought.</p>
<p>The first breast cancer screening emerged in the 1930s. Dr. Stafford Warren used direct radiographic exposure. This method was successful in identifying malignant and benign breast cancer that were found during an exam, but the technique was not very successful when seeking out less advanced breast cancers that were not detectable during an exam. This was a major flaw. Hence, research and evolution.</p>
<p>Contrast injections were next. This technique improved the outcomes but they caused inflammation, and the images were not clear. Thirty years later, radiologists Gershen-Cohen and Egan discovered a low-contrast technique that could detect unsuspected cancers not discovered during the examination. This became the first reproducible technique for breast cancer screening, but it didn’t stop there. Advancements like film-screen mammography and digital mammography continued to improve the safety, accuracy and outcomes.</p>
<p>Our ability to detect and treat breast cancer has evolved. We experimented using the best, yet flawed, methods known at the time. We learned from our failures to arrive where we are today. This progression took nearly 70 years. We saw countless clinical trials, huge sums of money spent, bad side effects and lots of mistakes.</p>
<p>Critics of early breast cancer screenings questioned whether screenings could change the course of the disease a manner significant enough to warrant the poking, proding and spending. There was no real evidence that an individual&#8217;s life would be improved. There was no data showing that the quality and design of the screening had an acceptable sensitivity and specificity to improve outcomes. We did not know how breast cancer looked in different populations. One doctor even proclaimed, “if I can’t feel it on examination, it’s not there.”</p>
<p>As clinical data emerged, these concerns waned. Through trial and error, we simply got smarter. Incidence and mortality rates declined, vital statistics improved, and people shared testimonials of how screening changed their life’s trajectory.</p>
<p>What would life be like today if the critics prevailed? How many friends or family members would you have lost to breast cancer? Would feeling for lumps been sufficient or did they benefit from some improved method of detection?</p>
<p>Medicine is interesting. Every disease and condition requires a unique treatment. Actually, each patient may require a unique treatment. Despite this, the path to discovering treatments is very similar. Idea. Try it out on lots of people. Analyze the results. Repeat. It’s expensive in the beginning. Mistakes are made while we learn. Hopefully, it gets cheaper and more effective.</p>
<p>Sudden Cardiac Arrest is the leading cause of death of adults in the United States. However, it is not just an adult thing. It is the #1 cause of death of student athletes and takes the lives of thousands of children every year. Today, the standard of care is the equivalent of “it’s not there unless I can feel it.” Parents answer a few questions about heart conditions in the family, and a doctor listens to the child’s heart. So, it’s more like “it’s not there unless I can hear it”</p>
<p>Heart screenings using electrocardiograms (ECG) and echocardiograms (echo) have been shown to improve our ability to detect abnormalities. In an evaluation of NCAA student athletes, 72% of heart conditions were found only after the use of the ECG. They were missed by feeling and listening. Additionally, the false positive rate (someone thinks you have a problem only to find out you do not) are quite low at 3.4 percent.</p>
<p>In 1930, in an effort to save lives, we accepted injections of highly toxic materials in the bodies of our mothers and sisters. That was the beginning of a long and uncertain road that has saved countless lives. Today, critics of heart screenings are not willing to accept the placement of stickers or a little gel on a student’s chest. It is too expensive. We don’t know what heart conditions look like in different pediatric popluations. We don’t know if detecting conditions will save lives. Sound familiar?</p>
<p>There is only one path forward. Idea. Try it out on lots of people. Analyze the results. Repeat. It’s expensive in the beginning. Mistakes are made while we learn. We get smarter. Fortunately, the research and future look promising.</p>
<p>A special thanks to our research fellow, Chris Koilor, for educating us about the history of screenings.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/screening-show-us-your/">What is a Standard of Care?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Madness of March, 2019</title>
		<link>/blog/the-madness-of-march-2019/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Simon's Heart]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 18:02:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Student Athlete Collapse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sudden Cardiac Death]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AED]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Final Four]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[March Madness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NCAA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sudden cardiac arrest]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8758</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The competition throughout the NCAA basketball season is always high but as soon as March rolls around it changes dramatically. March Madness. Teams are no longer just competing against other teams, but they are competing for spots, wins, and championships. Brackets start forming, bets are on the table and the conversations start. Conversations about upsets, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-madness-of-march-2019/">The Madness of March, 2019</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The competition throughout the NCAA basketball season is always high but as soon as March rolls around it changes dramatically. March Madness. Teams are no longer just competing against other teams, but they are competing for spots, wins, and championships. Brackets start forming, bets are on the table and the conversations start. Conversations about upsets, final four and championships but never heart conditions, AED devices or sudden cardiac arrest.</p>
<p>When you sit and watch the games, your main focus is that game. You aren’t thinking about injuries, the what-ifs or even heart issues. I know Shaquille O’Neal does. His 19-year-old son, <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/sports/ncaab/2018/09/28/uclas-shareef-oneal-to-miss-season-with-heart-ailment/37975417/">Shareef</a> was diagnosed with a heart condition at the end of last year.</p>
<blockquote><p>Sudden cardiac arrest is the number one cause of death of student-athletes. In fact, every three days a young athlete in the US collapses and dies due to an undetected heart condition.</p></blockquote>
<p>People typically don’t pay attention to the statistics unless it&#8217;s newsworthy and they read about it on their sports app. NCAA basketball players have a 1 in 3,000 chance of experiencing a sudden cardiac arrest event. In this NCAA tournament alone, there are three players and two coaches that have dealt with a heart-related issue. That is about 8%.</p>
<p>Minnesota a No. 10 seed will play today at 12:15 pm against No. 7 seed Louisville in the first round of the NCAA tournament. Did you know that Jarvis Johnson, a four-star prospect out of high school, recruited by ISU, was never able to suit up for Minnesota? Why? A heart condition called hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. He was never cleared to play competitively and his career as a basketball player was cut short. As a sixth man, he is watching and cheering on his teammates from the sidelines.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.toledoblade.com/sports/ohio-state/2019/02/13/once-an-unheralded-recruit-Andre-Wesson-rises-up-for-Ohio-State/stories/20190213011">Andre Wesson</a> from Ohio State is a prized defender. There was a good chance that Ohio State wouldn’t have been at the No. 11 seed if it wasn’t for his skills, attitude, and progression this season. It is a big surprise to learn that Wesson had a slow start last season due to a heart issue that was discovered by the Ohio State’s team doctors.</p>
<p>Making it this far in the NCAA tournament felt like an impossibility to <a href="http://theacc.com/news/2019/3/13/mens-basketball-virginia-techs-ty-outlaw-named-bradley-award-winner.aspx">Ty Outlaw</a> at Virginia Tech in 2015 when he was diagnosed with a heart condition. A heart condition that threatened to end his Hokies career. Outlaw was having difficulties recovering after drills during the preseason. Virginia Tech knew about a septal defect that Outlaw was born with that caused murmurs along with his high blood pressure. His struggles continued when he learned about his diagnosis of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. That was enough to shut him down in the 2015-2016 season. Now Outlaw has the reputation as being one of the top 3-point shooters in the ACC. Pretty impressive for someone with a heart condition.</p>
<p>No. 2 Michigan and No. 15 Montana will be facing off today at 9:20 pm. Who would have thought that both coaches have dealt with heart issues? Michigan <a href="http://www.espn.com/mens-college-basketball/story/_/id/24796749/john-beilein-michigan-reflects-offseason-heart-surgery">Coach John Beilein</a> had a double bypass heart operation. <a href="http://406mtsports.com/college/frontier-conference/university-of-providence/providence-men-s-basketball-coach-steve-keller-on-the-mend/article_96d8b9ea-5bd4-521c-9e90-b8791313107c.html">Montana Coach Steve Keller</a> endured a heart attack just a few months ago.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the players above have happy endings. They might not be able to follow their dreams to play in the tournament or even the NBA but their life wasn’t cut short. In this month alone there were six teens that lost their lives from an undiagnosed heart condition or sudden cardiac arrest. <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/health/pennsylvania-teen-13-dies-after-sudden-cardiac-arrest-school-says">Daron Lewis Godbee</a>, 13; <a href="https://www.phillyvoice.com/newville-teen-big-spring-pennsylvania-basketball-heart-attack/">Jonathan “JT” Kuhn</a>, 16; <a href="https://www.ktbs.com/news/caddo-parish-schools-mourns-the-loss-of-domanique-jones/article_34c9d6f6-3aeb-11e9-90af-8355eee1db59.html">Domanique Jones</a>, 18; <a href="https://www.fredericksburg.com/news/local/fredericksburg/jmhs-mourns-death-of-student-who-collapsed-during-gym-class/article_2e3a087c-c281-5383-bbc3-718fd03a8e29.html">Anonymous student</a>, 16; <a href="https://nypost.com/2019/03/07/high-school-football-player-dies-after-passing-out-in-weight-room/">Jermaine Falcaer</a>, 16; and Scott Krulcik, 22.</p>
<blockquote><p>These deaths could have been prevented with heart screenings or the use of an AED device.</p></blockquote>
<p>Simon’s Heart is dedicated to changing the standard of care to screen all kids and make AED devices readily available in all schools and youth facilities. You never know if a seemingly healthy athlete could have a ticking time bomb.</p>
<p>As you continue to follow the NCAA tournament, change your perspective. Learn about the warning signs that lead to sudden cardiac arrest. Understand what an AED device is. Recognize where the closest device might be. Get your hearts checked.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-madness-of-march-2019/">The Madness of March, 2019</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>No Drugs! Death, Maybe</title>
		<link>/blog/no-drugs-death-maybe/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 18:44:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cardiac arrest]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NCAA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[steroids]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8710</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>How many student athletes die from steroid use? That was the first thought to cross my mind after hearing that Clemson players, Dexler Lawrence, Zach Giella and Braden Galloway, were suspended from the BCS Championship Playoff. Despite having filed an appeal last week, they won’t be on the field tonight in the Championship Game. I [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/no-drugs-death-maybe/">No Drugs! Death, Maybe</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>How many student athletes die from steroid use? That was the first thought to cross my mind after hearing that Clemson players, Dexler Lawrence, Zach Giella and Braden Galloway, <a href="https://www.cbssports.com/college-football/news/clemson-dl-dexter-lawrence-two-other-suspended-players-wont-play-vs-alabama/">were suspended</a> from the BCS Championship Playoff. Despite having filed an appeal last week, they won’t be on the field tonight in the Championship Game.</p>
<p>I don’t believe that death is the only consequence. Steroids are unhealthy, and using them is considered cheating. However, when steroid use is viewed against the backdrop of sudden cardiac arrest and death in sport, it really makes me wonder about our priorities.</p>
<p>The NCAA set forth its policy on steroid use in the <a href="http://www.ncaa.org/sport-science-institute/ncaa-drug-testing-program">NCAA Drug Testing Program</a>. The policy identifies drugs that are “potentially harmful to the health and safety of the student-athlete.” The rationale for the policy seems to reflect a “dedication to the ideal of fair and equitable intercollegiate competition at their championships and postseason bowl games.</p>
<p>So, we’ve accepted the reality that our student athletes can be randomly tested for drugs during the season. Before the “big” game, that testing should be mandatory. We have also accepted that these tests are reliable enough to warrant suspension from “big” games, even if there’s a chance we’re wrong. In the case of the Clemson players, there are <a href="https://www.usada.org/growing-evidence-ostarine-athlete-risk/">thirty-six supplements</a> that contain the banned substance of ostarine. This is a very different approach than we’re taking to sudden cardiac arrest and death.</p>
<p>Four years ago, <a href="mailto:https://www.wsj.com/articles/ncaa-doctor-backs-off-recommending-heart-tests-for-athletes-1429291801">Brian Hainline</a>, the Chief Medical Officer of the NCAA, suggested that all high risk athletes, namely basketball and football players, be required to undergo a cardiac exam before taking the field or court. <a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/Drezner_ECG-Screening-in-NCAA-Athletes_AJC-2016.pdf">Research</a> supports this position and shows that heart screenings are far more effective at detecting heart conditions in NCAA athletes.</p>
<p>The backlash was brutal and the idea was quickly scrapped.</p>
<p>All or nothing shouldn’t be the only choice when setting policy for the health and safety of student athletes. It’s not for steroids.</p>
<p>Last year, the news media reported the deaths of nine student athletes from suspected sudden cardiac arrest. Yet, no student athlete was randomly tested for heart conditions this season, and none of the players from Notre Dame, Oklahoma, Clemson and Alabama were required to get a heart screening before the BCS Championship Playoffs. Some schools do provide heart screenings for their student athletes. This year, <a href="https://www.mcall.com/sports/college/psu/mc-spt-penn-state-football-nana-asiedu-20180627-story.html">Penn State football</a> discovered career-ending conditions in two of its players.</p>
<p>If steroids pose a significant health risk for our student athletes, I welcome testing. If steroid use threatens the integrity of sport, let’s prevent and punish its use. But, is this about health or cheating? If it’s about health, let’s apply the same or stricter standards to testing for heart conditions. I think that we can all agree that losing a game because of cheating sucks, but losing a player is tragic.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/no-drugs-death-maybe/">No Drugs! Death, Maybe</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Curiosity and Heart Screenings</title>
		<link>/blog/curiosity-and-heart-screenings/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2018 11:21:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8554</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This article appeared in Medpage Today. Are physicians in Europe more curious than physicians in the United States? I get that impression after reading headlines from the recent study about soccer players and heart screenings in England: &#8220;Screening fails to predict most heart deaths in young soccer players&#8221; (Reuters) &#8220;More young footballers dying of heart problems than thought, FA study finds&#8221; [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/curiosity-and-heart-screenings/">Curiosity and Heart Screenings</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This article appeared in Medpage Today.</em></p>
<p>Are physicians in Europe more curious than physicians in the United States? I get that impression after reading headlines from the <a href="https://www.medpagetoday.com/cardiology/arrhythmias/74483" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recent study about soccer players and heart screenings</a> in England:</p>
<ul>
<li>&#8220;Screening <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-health-soccer-cardiac-screening/screening-fails-to-predict-most-heart-deaths-in-young-soccer-players-idUSKBN1KT2M8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fails to predict most heart deaths</a> in young soccer players&#8221; (<em>Reuters</em>)</li>
<li>&#8220;More young <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/science/2018/aug/08/more-young-footballers-dying-of-heart-problems-than-thought-fa-study-finds" target="_blank" rel="noopener">footballers dying of heart problems</a> than thought, FA study finds&#8221; (<em>The Guardian</em>)</li>
</ul>
<p>In fact, many local reactions to this study, and the heart screening studies before it, have become very predictable. They are quick to raise doubts and cast judgments, like &#8220;screening fails to predict most heart deaths.&#8221; As a parent, patient, and advocate, I find these reactions to be very &#8230; curious.</p>
<p>Curiosity has played a tremendous role in my life. My son died 13 years ago. Everyone assumed it was sudden infant death syndrome (SIDS). However, our pediatrician was curious. She said, &#8220;Get your hearts checked, because babies just don&#8217;t die.&#8221; As a result, Phyllis, Simon&#8217;s mom, was diagnosed with Long QT syndrome. Long QT has been linked to up to 15% of all SIDS deaths and is one of several conditions that lead to sudden cardiac arrest in children.</p>
<p>If we&#8217;re open to it, this study raises some great questions and reveals some areas for improvement. Here are a few that jumped out at me:</p>
<ul>
<li>The status quo does not work. The physical and survey missed 93% of the heart conditions that can lead to sudden death and 67% of other heart conditions. In other words, there were hundreds of false negatives (of the 11,168 young athletes screened). Can the ECG and/or echo help us screen better and decrease the number of false negatives?</li>
<li>The leading cause of death of adults in this country is cardiac arrest. The screening found a total of 267 heart conditions. Some were more serious than others. Won&#8217;t detecting these conditions early in life lead to better quality of life and lower healthcare costs?</li>
<li>Despite detecting 267 heart conditions, the screening failed to detect six. Some conditions take time to develop. Why? Could screening help us better understand when and why these heart conditions develop?</li>
<li>No one knows the real cost of screenings. The healthcare system is broken and pricing is erratic. Heart screenings are new. Today, we order lots of tests to learn the difference between abnormal and normal variance. Won&#8217;t the frequency and cost of additional tests decrease over time as we get smarter?</li>
<li>Six young athletes died after their conditions went undetected. Two others died after ignoring their doctor&#8217;s advice. Forty were treated and have not died. How many deaths may have been prevented from this screening? Could a second screening at a later date have prevented the six deaths? Is there a best time to screen?</li>
<li>There are two ways to prevent sudden cardiac death – detection and preparation. Screening helps to identify the conditions. CPR and automated external defibrillator (AED) devices reduce sudden death. We&#8217;re never asked to choose smoke detectors <em>or</em> fire extinguishers, so why should we have to choose between ECG and AED?</li>
</ul>
<p>I&#8217;m biased. My son died from an undetected heart condition. My organization, Simon&#8217;s Heart, has helped students discover heart conditions. Parents have thanked me for saving their child&#8217;s life. But, even I don&#8217;t reach a conclusion from this study. I remain curious. How many students really die from undetected heart conditions? How many kids saved with an AED device were cleared during a wellness check or sports physical? What is the best way to screen kids to prevent sudden cardiac arrest? I hope that you&#8217;ll remain curious too.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/curiosity-and-heart-screenings/">Curiosity and Heart Screenings</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>An Apple a Day</title>
		<link>/blog/an-apple-a-day/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2018 11:18:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=8552</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>An apple a day keeps the doctor away. I heard this as a kid, and now as a parent, I always look for healthy advice and habits to pass on to my kids. This week, the apple became even more important in the prevention of disease. Apple announced that its Series 4 Watch includes an [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/an-apple-a-day/">An Apple a Day</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>An apple a day keeps the doctor away. I heard this as a kid, and now as a parent, I always look for healthy advice and habits to pass on to my kids. This week, the apple became even more important in the prevention of disease. Apple announced that its Series 4 Watch includes an electrocardiogram (EKG or ECG).</p>
<p>The ECG was invented in the late 1800s. It’s the machine that displays the squiggly lines, and <u>always</u> flatlines in TV dramas. It is used to detect abnormal heart rhythms and diagnose electrical conditions and heart attacks. It is also a good indicator for certain structural conditions. It is a very useful piece of equipment, but not all ECGs are created equal.</p>
<p>Most ECGs found in a doctor’s office or hospital have 12 leads. They are typically the size of a desktop computer and include ten wires and electrodes (stickers) that connect to the patient’s chest, arms and legs. The machine evaluates the rhythm, conduction and contour of the heart as it monitors the heart’s activity across the body.</p>
<p>The Apple Watch is a one lead ECG so it monitors the heart rhythm from one spot on the body. Its portability makes it great for capturing isolated events and offering insight into potential issues, like aFib in adults. This technology shows lots of promise, but it does not collect enough detail to diagnose heart conditions . . . yet.</p>
<p>Why does this matter? Sudden cardiac arrest is the leading cause of death of adults in the United States. It is the #1 cause of death of student athletes and takes the lives of thousands of children every year. Thirteen years ago, my son became one of those statistics so we created a <a href="https://www.simonsheart.org/">heart screening program</a> for students. Let me offer this real life scenario to illustrate my point.</p>
<p>Drew is thirteen. He complains that his heart races. It is hard to know what this really means because Drew is the only one who feels his symptoms. Does Drew consume too much caffeine? Is he an anxious kid? Does he have a heart condition?</p>
<p>Drew comes to our screening. After getting an ECG (12 lead), he is diagnosed with Wolff Parkinson White Syndrome &#8211; an electrical condition. It is possible that the new Apple Watch would have recorded his racing heart. This would’ve provided his parents and doctor with clues about his complaints. It could have led to further testing, the 12 lead ECG, to diagnose his condition. In other words, the watch could have taken the ambiguity out of Drew’s description.</p>
<p>After our screening, Drew underwent a medical procedure called an ablation. The surgery took place on my son’s birthday. Coincidence? Now, he is completely fine and doing well.</p>
<p>We should celebrate this new advancement for what it is. It brings affordable medical technology into our homes. It empowers consumers with valuable information. It raises awareness about heart health. It will give our children insight into how hard their heart works every day. It will help them understand how their heart behaves in certain situations. There’s no doubt that this will lead to a better quality of life.</p>
<p>In the meantime, get your child’s heart screened. <a href="https://www.screenacrossamerica.org/">Check out</a> one of these organizations. It could save their life.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/an-apple-a-day/">An Apple a Day</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Now Spit</title>
		<link>/blog/now-spit/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 15:05:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.simonsfund.org/?p=7712</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Previously posted in Huffington Post on December 13, 2016 I went to the dentist for my six month check up last week. I didn’t want to be there. Are you surprised? I hate all of the poking and scraping. It was also the day before my daughter’s 14th birthday. I had stuff to do, and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/now-spit/">Now Spit</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Previously posted in <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/now-spit_us_584f5a0de4b0151082221e5e">Huffington Post</a> on December 13, 2016</p>
<p>I went to the dentist for my six month check up last week. I didn’t want to be there. Are you surprised? I hate all of the poking and scraping. It was also the day before my daughter’s 14th birthday. I had stuff to do, and places to be. I didn’t have time for this.</p>
<p>So, to keep my mind off of the scraping and poking, I started to wonder what would happen if I just left. Seriously, who needs this? What could possibly go wrong?</p>
<p>I stayed put, but afterwards, I did a little research. The <a href="https://www.dentalhealth.org/blog/blogdetails/96" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:2,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://www.dentalhealth.org/blog/blogdetails/96&quot;}}">Oral Health Foundation</a> claims that the mouth is one of the dirtiest parts of the body, so maybe there is some merit to getting it professionally cleaned. Poor oral hygiene can lead to heart disease, stroke, rheumatoid arthritis and lung conditions.</p>
<p>But wait. The <a href="http://www.heart.org/HEARTORG/HealthyLiving/Dental-Health-and-Heart-Health_UCM_459358_Article.jsp#" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:3,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;http://www.heart.org/HEARTORG/HealthyLiving/Dental-Health-and-Heart-Health_UCM_459358_Article.jsp#&quot;}}">American Heart Association</a> contends that there is not enough research to conclude that good oral hygiene prevents heart disease or strokes. So, should I stay or should I go?</p>
<p>Taking off probably won’t kill me, but, it could make my life a little more challenging for things like chewing food.</p>
<p>Experts recommend that we take <a href="http://www.wsj.com/articles/how-many-bites-do-you-take-a-day-try-for-100-1407798123%20" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:4,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;http://www.wsj.com/articles/how-many-bites-do-you-take-a-day-try-for-100-1407798123%20&quot;}}">100 bites per day</a> (or chews). Most of us don’t do that. Who has time to chew that much? If we did, we would chew 36,500 per year. As the <a href="https://www.google.com/publicdata/explore?ds=d5bncppjof8f9_&met_y=sp_dyn_le00_in&idim=country:USA:CAN:GBR&hl=en&dl=en%20" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:5,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://www.google.com/publicdata/explore?ds=d5bncppjof8f9_&met_y=sp_dyn_le00_in&idim=country:USA:CAN:GBR&hl=en&dl=en%20&quot;}}">average life expectancy</a> in the U.S. is seventy-nine, our lifetime chew average would be around 2.88 million.</p>
<p>That seems like a lot for something where the consequences are not grave. Not the chewing; all of the maintenance and cleaning.</p>
<p>We are supposed to go the dentist when we get <a href="https://www.google.com/webhp?sourceid=chrome-instant&ion=1&espv=2&ie=UTF-8#q=when%20should%20children%20visit%20dentist%20for%20first%20time" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:6,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://www.google.com/webhp?sourceid=chrome-instant&ion=1&espv=2&ie=UTF-8#q=when%20should%20children%20visit%20dentist%20for%20first%20time&quot;}}">our first tooth</a>. So, if we start at age 1 and live to seventy-nine, we will spend 78 hours sitting in a dentist’s chair – just for hygiene visits! That doesn’t even count all of the brushing and flossing we do at home. OK, <a href="http://www.usnews.com/news/articles/2016-05-02/how-many-americans-floss-their-teeth." target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:7,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;http://www.usnews.com/news/articles/2016-05-02/how-many-americans-floss-their-teeth.&quot;}}">nobody really flosses</a>.</p>
<p>I am pro dentist and pro good oral hygiene. I even floss. I’m just struck by the emphasis that we place on good oral hygiene compared to let’s say . . . heart health.</p>
<p>That’s really what was bothering me in the chair. Realizing that my kids get a thorough oral exam twice a year, but they will never be offered a thorough heart exam. For the heart, they will get evaluated only if they complain of symptoms. That usually happens much later in life, and then the damage has already be done.</p>
<p>Why do we practice prevention in oral hygiene but not in cardiac care? We don’t wait for tooth pain to visit a dentist. However, we require pain or discomfort before visiting a cardiologist.</p>
<p>This defies common sense and logic. The heart beats about <a href="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/heart/heartfacts.html" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:8,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/heart/heartfacts.html&quot;}}">35 million times</a> a year or 2,765,000,000 times over the average life span. (That’s almost 1000 times more beating than chewing).</p>
<p>Let’s imagine that we implemented a dental model for cardiology. Once a year, students will receive a thorough cardiac evaluation. A technician, using an electrocardiogram or echocardiogram, will examine the heart. The student will exercise on a treadmill so their pulse and recovery can be evaluated. There is still be time to measure blood pressure and weight. Finally, we can draw blood for cholesterol. We look for plaque on teeth twice a year. It makes sense to look for it in the arteries too. We will compare findings year after year, like they do at the dentist. Why is it that we pay more attention to our teeth than our heart?</p>
<p>Heart conditions are the most common <a href="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/chd" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:9,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/chd&quot;}}">birth defect</a>. They are linked to up to <a href="http://cardiovascres.oxfordjournals.org/content/67/3/388" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:10,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;http://cardiovascres.oxfordjournals.org/content/67/3/388&quot;}}">15%</a> of all SIDS deaths. They lead to the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/to-your-health/wp/2016/05/06/sudden-cardiac-arrest-is-a-leading-killer-of-college-athletes-heres-the-ncaas-plan-of-attack/?utm_term=.048736e18a10" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:11,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;sudden-cardiac-arrest-is-a-leading-killer-of-college-athletes-heres-the-ncaas-plan-of-attack/?utm_term=.048736e18a10&quot;}}">#1 cause of death</a> of student athletes. They are behind the <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/fastats/leading-causes-of-death.htm" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener" data-beacon="{&quot;p&quot;:{&quot;mnid&quot;:&quot;entry_text&quot;,&quot;lnid&quot;:&quot;citation&quot;,&quot;mpid&quot;:12,&quot;plid&quot;:&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/fastats/leading-causes-of-death.htm&quot;}}">#1 cause of death</a> of adults in this country, approximately 350,000 each year.</p>
<p>If we believe that regular dental visits can prevent cavities and gum disease, promote better health, and keep costs down, imagine what regular cardiac evaluations could prevent.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/now-spit/">Now Spit</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Financial and Emotional Costs of Heart Screenings</title>
		<link>/blog/the-financial-and-emotional-costs-of-heart-screenings/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2014 15:53:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=6020</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>As I write this, Mason Tellez, a track athlete from Whittier High School, remains hospitalized.  According to a statement by his mother, he collapsed during practice with an undetected heart condition.  “He remains in serious condition, but at this point is breathing on his own.” Our prayers and thoughts are with Mason and his family. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-financial-and-emotional-costs-of-heart-screenings/">The Financial and Emotional Costs of Heart Screenings</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As I write this, Mason Tellez, a track athlete from Whittier High School, remains hospitalized.  According to <a href="http://www.whittierdailynews.com/general-news/20140414/whittier-high-students-rally-to-support-mason-tellez-still-hospitalized-after-collapse">a statement</a> by his mother, he collapsed during practice with an undetected heart condition.  “He remains in serious condition, but at this point is breathing on his own.”</p>
<p><a href="http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/mason-tellez.jpg"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" class="size-full wp-image-6021 alignleft" src="https://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/mason-tellez.jpg" alt="mason tellez" width="400" height="400" /></a>Our prayers and thoughts are with Mason and his family.</p>
<p>Sudden cardiac arrest is the #1 cause of death of student athletes.  It takes the lives of thousands of students every year.  Despite these numbers, checking our children’s hearts is not a standard of care.  As a society, we prefer the wait and see approach.  That strategy didn’t work out too well for my family, and I’m sure that the Tellez family would have preferred another option too.</p>
<p>One of the strongest objections to screening our kids’ hearts is the cost argument.  It’s just too expensive to screen our kids . . .. It is difficult to have a rationale conversation about healthcare costs because the system is so broken. It is hard to ascertain actual costs because there is very little consistency.  However, as Mason is hopefully recovering, I think we should try.</p>
<p>According to <a href="http://www.fchp.org/members/resources/guide-to-costs.aspx">Fallon Health</a> (the first link in my Google search that revealed costs), an average doctor office EKG exam costs $43. There are <a href="http://www.nfhs.org/content.aspx?id=9628">7.7 million</a> high school student athletes in this country.  If each student athlete got an EKG exam, it would cost $331,100,000.</p>
<p>According to a <a href="http://money.cnn.com/2013/05/08/news/economy/hospital-bills/">report filed by CNN</a>, the average bill for treatment of a heart attack <i>without major complications</i> at a hospital is $47,695. This is not a perfect comparison, because a heart attack is not sudden cardiac arrest and a child is not an adult. However, the purposes of this discussion, this figure is good enough.</p>
<p>According to <a href="http://www.beckershospitalreview.com/lists/average-cost-per-inpatient-day-across-50-states-in-2010.html">Becker’s Hospital Review</a>, the average cost of a day in a for-profit hospital is around $1,800, and the <a href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&rct=j&q=&esrc=s&source=web&cd=3&ved=0CDwQFjAC&url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.researchgate.net%2Fpublication%2F23415626_Inter-hospital_variability_in_post-cardiac_arrest_mortality%2Ffile%2F9fcfd50b3c10b43588.pdf&ei=MI5OU923JabH7Abb94HgCA&usg=AFQjCNGD8tkxTxM7z0IeivtMAvyiVn5FoA&bvm=bv.64764171,d.ZGU">average hospital stay</a> of an adult following cardiac arrest is 3.8 days.</p>
<p>Combining all of the information above, it costs $47,695 to treat the heart attack and $6,840 for the hospital stay, for a total cost of $54,535.</p>
<p>If we divide the cost of screening all of our student athletes ($331,100,000) by the average cost of treating an adult for a heart attack ($54,535), we get 6,071. To put another way, we could screen 8,000,000 students for the same cost of treating 6,071 students who were hospitalized from sudden cardiac arrest.</p>
<p>Are there 6,000 students that suffer from cardiac arrest and survive?  Probably, but we don’t have a good understanding of that number because we’ve never tracked it. Last October, the CDC and NIH finally established a sudden cardiac arrest registry for youth.</p>
<p>But let’s look at this another way.  Youth heart screenings, in addition to discover heart conditions that lead to sudden cardiac arrest and death in our children, also reveal risk factors of hyptertension and obesity – the precursors to heart disease. Heart disease is the #1 cause of death of adults in this country – about 400,000 per year.  By preventing heart disease among students, is there additional cost savings?</p>
<p>It’s hard to imagine that a society who has the tools to detect and prevent heart disease and sudden death among children doesn’t use them. It’s hard to believe that $1 out of every $6 spent on health care is for cardiovascular disease, or $444 billion per year. The cost to screen all of the hearts of the high school student athletes .007% of that big billion dollar number.</p>
<p>So, if you’re one of those numbers or economic folks who likes to assess the return on investment, what’s a better strategy? Oh, and before you answer, pretend that Mason is your child. Consider the financial toll on the system and the emotional toll on his family. It all probably could have been avoided with a heart screening.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/the-financial-and-emotional-costs-of-heart-screenings/">The Financial and Emotional Costs of Heart Screenings</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Heart Screening at Final Four</title>
		<link>/blog/heart-screening-at-final-four/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 14:31:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=4595</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Download Press Release Atlanta – (February 11, 2013) – Less than an hour from the Georgia Dome, the day before the NCAA Championship Game, over 300 students will be screened for potentially fatal heart conditions that cause sudden cardiac arrest (SCA) and death, the #1 killer of student athletes. Demand for the screening was so high in [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/heart-screening-at-final-four/">Heart Screening at Final Four</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href=" http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/Final-Four-3.9.13.pdf" rel="attachment wp-att-4592">Download Press Release</a></p>
<p>Atlanta – (February 11, 2013) – Less than an hour from the Georgia Dome, the day before the NCAA Championship Game, over 300 students will be screened for potentially fatal heart conditions that cause sudden cardiac arrest (SCA) and death, the #1 killer of student athletes. Demand for the screening was so high in this community, which has lost two student basketball players and a high school coach to SCA in the last 18 months, that two hours after registration opened, the event filled up – there are now over 300 people on a waiting list.</p>
<p><strong>About the Screening</strong></p>
<p>When: Sunday, April 7, 8:30 a.m. to 4 p.m.</p>
<p>Where: The Cardiovascular Group, 755 Walther Road, Lawrenceville, GA</p>
<p><strong>Saving Lives to Honor Fallen Children</strong></p>
<p>The heart screening is sponsored by Simon’s Fund, a Philadelphia based organization that has screened 5,500 students; 49 have discovered heart conditions. The John Stewart Foundation, based in Indiana, will be participating in the screening as well. John was a high school basketball standout who died of SCA during a March Madness basketball tournament in 1999, just days after being recruited by Tubby Smith for the University of Kentucky Wildcats. At 7’2”, John Stewart was most certainly on a road to the Final Four.</p>
<p>Last year, in a suburb of Atlanta, Buford High School junior, Adam Smith, and Buford Junior High School student, Jeremy Nelson, died from SCA. They were both basketball standouts. Both may have been on the road to the Final Four.</p>
<p>SCA ended their journeys, as well as the journeys of two thousand other students who died last year from SCA, according to the American Academy of Pediatrics.</p>
<p>SCA is the #1 medical cause of death in the NCAA. Recently, Utah State&#8217;s Danny Berger collapsed from an undetected heart condition, and Utah’s Star Lotulelei was diagnosed with a heart condition at the NFL Combine.</p>
<p><strong>Speaking Up to Prevent a Silent Killer</strong></p>
<p>Sudden cardiac arrest is an often-silent killer, whose symptoms – shortness of breath and fainting to name a few – are easily confused by students, parents and coaches with signs of dehydration or exhaustion. An ECG exam can detect up to 80 percent of the conditions that cause sudden cardiac arrest. An ECG exam, coupled with a physical and medical history, is the most effective way to prevent sudden cardiac death in student athletes according to a study in the American Medical Society for Sports Medicine (2012).</p>
<p>“As coaches, we spend so much time preparing our players, because we don’t we don’t to lose a game. We need to focus on sudden cardiac arrest, because losing a student athlete is much worse,” said Phil Martelli, men’s basketball coach of the St. Joseph’s University Hawks and first vice president of the National Association of Basketball coaches, which is meeting in Atlanta during the Final Four.</p>
<p><strong>Our 1 Percent: 1 in 100 Students Has Undetected Heart Condition</strong></p>
<p>At the screening, every student will complete a medical history, have vital signs checked, and receive an ECG – a painless, non-invasive test that takes a couple of minutes. Cardiologists from The Cardiovascular Group, Children’s Cardiovascular Medicine and Pediatric Cardiology Services will review all of the information and determine whether the students need to get an echocardiogram, also available at the screening.</p>
<p>Darren and Phyllis Sudman founded Simon’s Fund in 2005 after their seemingly healthy 14-week old son, Simon, died from sudden cardiac arrest during his nap. One in every 100 children screened by Simon’s Fund and its brethren organizations nationwide is found to have a heart condition. These are the same conditions diagnosed regularly in pro basketball players, during their mandated heart screenings.</p>
<p>“At birth, we screen our children for rare genetic conditions. In elementary school, we screen their eyes and ears. How is it that we ignore their hearts, the most important organ in their bodies, when we know that thousands die every year,” says Darren Sudman, Executive Director of Simon’s Fund and Simon’s dad.</p>
<p><strong>About Simon’s Fund</strong></p>
<p>In addition to providing heart screenings, Simon’s Fund advocates for legislation to protect student athletes from sudden cardiac arrest. The organization is behind the first such legislation in the country, Pennsylvania’s Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act. Since its passage in May of last year, Simon’s Fund has worked with five more states to introduce similar legislation, including Indiana, home of the NCAA.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/heart-screening-at-final-four/">Heart Screening at Final Four</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Upper Dublin Screening &#8211; An Email to Jill</title>
		<link>/blog/upper-dublin-screening-an-email-to-jill/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2012 20:34:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Past Screenings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[awareness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[child]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[community]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hearts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lives]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mitzvah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tragedy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3995</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The best way to capture the success and sentiment from the Upper Dublin Heart Screening is to share an email that we sent to Jill Florin. Jill&#8217;s daughter, Paige, invited us to come to Upper Dublin. This was her bat mitzvah project. Jill &#8211; Phyllis and I want to know how happy, honored, proud and [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/upper-dublin-screening-an-email-to-jill/">Upper Dublin Screening &#8211; An Email to Jill</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The best way to capture the success and sentiment from the Upper Dublin Heart Screening is to share an email that we sent to Jill Florin. Jill&#8217;s daughter, Paige, invited us to come to Upper Dublin. This was her bat mitzvah project.</p>
<p>Jill &#8211;</p>
<p>Phyllis and I want to know how happy, honored, proud and pleased we are to have worked with your family on the Upper Dublin heart screening.  When your kid dies, you don&#8217;t know how or if you&#8217;ll be able to make it.  You fight to convince yourself that things will get better and that maybe there was a reason.  You don&#8217;t necessarily believe it, but you try.</p>
<p>Then, as the years go by, you get to meet new people and engage in new activities as a result of the horrible tragedy.  Also, if you are lucky, you get to make someone else&#8217;s life a little better and safer.</p>
<p>We would not have met your family, but for Simon&#8217;s death.  We would not have experienced the sunshine and maturity of Paige, and the tireless passion and dedication of you.  We would not have worked along side Larry and Evan or any of the other amazing people you brought to the event.  We would not have raised awareness in your community.  We would not have touched 315 student lives in Upper Dublin.</p>
<p>There is a good chance that four kids will live safer lives as a result of Paige&#8217;s mitzvah project.  That&#8217;s defines mitzvah, right?</p>
<p>When our kids turn 13, they automatically become a bat mitzvah.  By turning, 13, they are recognized as an adult.  The service is just a way for our children to acknowledge this responsibility.  We know that Paige is going to be amazing.</p>
<p>However, as far as we&#8217;re concerned, Paige fulfilled her responsibility to the Jewish community on Sunday when she helped to check hearts and save lives.</p>
<p>All the best,</p>
<p>Phyllis and Darren</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/IMG_5236-copy1.jpg"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-3999" title="IMG_5236 copy" src="https://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/IMG_5236-copy1-225x300.jpg" alt="" width="225" height="300" /></a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/upper-dublin-screening-an-email-to-jill/">Upper Dublin Screening &#8211; An Email to Jill</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>If only . . . then.</title>
		<link>/blog/if-only-then/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dsudman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jul 2012 21:25:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Heart Screening]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Just a Thought]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/?p=3826</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m not big of the &#8220;if only . . . then&#8221; game. This can be played in many ways, some more trivial than others. If they had only changed the pitcher in the seventh. If we had only taken the backroads instead of the highway. If we had only gotten our baby&#8217;s heart checked. Most [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/if-only-then/">If only . . . then.</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m not big of the &#8220;if only . . . then&#8221; game. This can be played in many ways, some more trivial than others. If they had only changed the pitcher in the seventh. If we had only taken the backroads instead of the highway. If we had only gotten our baby&#8217;s heart checked.</p>
<p>Most of the work that we do today is focused on the hearts of students. Our regularly scheduled screenings are for students. The Sudden Cardiac Arrest Prevention Act is for students. However, our story began with a baby . . . our baby.</p>
<p>Today, I visited the Corrine Santerian Newborn Center at Abington Hospital for the first time. Almost two years ago, we decided to provide ECG exams to newborns. Every baby seen at this clinic receives a free ECG exam as part of their wellness exam.  Nobody else is doing it, and there is no data on the hearts of newborns despite the fact that up to 15% of all SIDS deaths are attributed to Long QT Syndrome.</p>
<p>Today, I met Noah. He&#8217;s getting a level of care that Simon didn&#8217;t get. He&#8217;s getting a level of care that no other baby gets. I&#8217;m really proud of Abington Memorial Hospital and Simon&#8217;s Fund for being leaders in this area. Today wasn&#8217;t about asking what if. Honestly, I don&#8217;t care about the answer to that question. Today was about imagining what can and should be.</p>
<p><a href="http://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/IMG_0589.jpg"><img decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-3827 alignleft" title="IMG_0589" src="https://simonsoriginal.local:8080/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/IMG_0589-300x224.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="224" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="/blog/if-only-then/">If only . . . then.</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="/">- Simon&#039;s Heart</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
